<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-05T14:00:42+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal as part of the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree programme.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Week 1 - The Creative Piece</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/04/week-one-creative-assignment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week 1 - The Creative Piece" /><published>2019-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/04/week-one-creative-assignment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/04/week-one-creative-assignment.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;jam-master&quot;&gt;Jam Master&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;As long as we have each other we will never run out of problems&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line seems to resonate with something I have some experience with, i.e. music. This phrase could easily have been written about music itself, which can be easily seen as the presentation and attempted resolution of a series of problems. Apart from some very determined attempts in the realm of the avant-garde to detach musical production from its human-centred origins, much of what drives this production is our social nature and our determination to move forward with new ideas and to formulate responses to what has come before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began to think of how this process may be formalised into actions that could be crystallised into the medium of an app. I focused on the idea of multiple musicians creating musical ideas that pose questions that demand responses from their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at how musicians in a band often write songs together, whether this is via a relatively loose process of ‘jamming’ or by sitting down and meticulously working through and developing ideas, I began to see it as essentially a process whereby possible solutions are developed in response to being confronted with a series of musical problems.  In this case, the chosen, ‘successful’ solution, is the one that wins through on consensus.  It is the one that draws the most admiration from those participating. Essentially, it is a form of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working through this idea, I began with a formal, solution-based concept to the problem of bringing dispersed musicians together in order to collaborate on writing musical pieces together, that is working together from across distances that would not normally allow such activity.  As the idea developed, I began to see how it could be developed and structured along similar workflow lines as a game.  Below is an attempt at mapping this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game would be initialised by providing, at the outset, the limits of a simple, widely-recognised, song structure, such as &lt;em&gt;ABABCBD&lt;/em&gt; – or &lt;em&gt;verse, chorus, verse, chorus, middle eight, chorus, outro&lt;/em&gt;. This structure could potentially be amended during the game – see the more detailed outline below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other formal structure could be agreed upon – this is highly likely under most circumstances – such as measure and tempo – e.g. &lt;em&gt;4/4 time at 120bpm&lt;/em&gt;. Drum beats could be provided if requested, or a backing track or chord progression. Otherwise a metronome will do. The players will select their instruments and a simple interface provided to allow playing and musical data entry. It’s likely that this would be via a piano-style keyboard.  As there are obvious limitations with this approach for some musicians, for instance a guitarist may not be happy about the unfamiliarity of a keyboard, then a welcome enhancement could be to allow real instruments to be played and recorded via a microphone and digitised raw audio data used instead of MIDI data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians – or ‘players’ - would decide if one of them is to start the process by providing the first phrase, theme or ‘riff’, or to allow the computer to kick start proceedings with an internally-generated or a pre-recorded theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each player will then be given the opportunity to play their response to that theme. Once all players have submitted their responses, everyone will vote on their favourite. Players cannot vote for their own. The winner will be appended to the track and the other put into a ‘Theme Pot’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players build up points when their idea is voted in.  Game-play could build on the points system by allowing players with sufficient points to replace phrases/themes with ones they favour from the Theme Pot, or to suggest changes to the arrangement itself. They could even build enough points to replace existing phrases with new ones of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game would end when the arrangement plan put forward at the start (and potentially amended during game-play) has been completed. The winner will have the most points and will have had the biggest influence on the resulting song / track / masterpiece!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\jam-master-map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;jam-master-map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Jam Master</summary></entry></feed>