<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-11T14:31:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Artefact Design Map</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/10/artefact-design-map.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artefact Design Map" /><published>2021-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/10/artefact-design-map</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/10/artefact-design-map.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;last-updated-march-10th-2021&quot;&gt;Last updated: March 10th 2021&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/GAM750/artefact-design-map.jpg&quot;&gt;Click here to open&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\GAM750\artefact-design-map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Design Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last updated: March 10th 2021</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/10/reflections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections" /><published>2021-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/10/reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/10/reflections.html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I set out to use the opportunities presented by this project to explore the potential of a multiplayer, virtual environment as a platform for creative endeavour in theatre, whilst building on my own skills as a researcher, developer and artist.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have succeeded in my goal of building an environment that meets the stakeholders’ requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have developed a technical stack to achieve these aims.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have learned about multiplayer technologies and, in Normcore, found a very useable, cost-effective and forward-thinking solution for future projects.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have learned about media streaming, and bringing video from outside and into the virtual environment. Furthermore, have built a way for communication to happen between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have had a great oportunity to work with other artists and to think about the creative process, both in terms of theatre and in a more abstract, general sense. I have begun to understand how an immersive, virtual environment can be used for creative ends, and even maybe enhance creativity. It certainly provides new ways of thinking about creative practice, beyond traditions.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The research I have done is just the start - I have discovered areas that provide fascinating oportunities for further research.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As an artist myself, I have ideas for future projects that will combine what I have learned here with my own creative practice.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The students’ own presentations reveal a variety of creative responses, demonstrating both an ease of engaging with the unfamiliar environment and the environment itself as a tool for exploring new ways of thinking about, and making, theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The work done by the students shows they way the environment has been embraced, and how fears have, apparently, been overcome.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is impossible to be sure that this is the case, though, until full user-testing has been undertaken, including surveys, discussions and interviews, in order to get the students and the expert stakeholders’ views and opinions.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Preparations are currently underway for the continuing development of Not Near Enough.  Most immediately, it has been confirmed that the work will be presented at the 2021 National Student Drama Festival, and plans are being put in place to publish a peer-reviewed academic paper discussing the project.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The festival submission, due to the pandemic, will involve 360 degree capture from within the audience environment.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Future work will involve developing the artefact to make it more user-friendly for users from non-technical backgrounds to be able to start making work with it, with the flattest learning curve possible.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In this way, it has the potential to become a commercial product. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the sense that this is, in fact, just the beginning is enticing me to take forward what has been learned, particularly in relation to the controller app, so as to further progress as a researcher, developer, artist and practitioner, and to drive what I am certain will become a rich source for further research and development, exploring issues of embodiment and identity, whilst investigating collaborative creation within virtual multiplayer settings.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The research I have done is just the start - I have discovered areas that provide fascinating oportunities for further research.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The area around the breaking down of the reality-virtuality continuum is particularly exciting, and my intention is to continue to  create work that explores the combining of different ‘levels’ of virtuality.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An exciting and more immediate prospect, however, is that, as a result of what I have learned from working on Not Near Enough, I have been invited to teach undergraduate theatre students at Falmouth University, as a visiting lecturer, about this area of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is an interesting and new area for me, and one which I hope will lead to more of the same.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It will not only allow me to help and enthuse students to explore these areas of creative practice, but will feed into my own research, development and my own creative practice.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I set out to use the opportunities presented by this project to explore the potential of a multiplayer, virtual environment as a platform for creative endeavour in theatre, whilst building on my own skills as a researcher, developer and artist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stereo 360 Image and Video Capture</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/10/stereo-360-image-and-video-capture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stereo 360 Image and Video Capture" /><published>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/10/stereo-360-image-and-video-capture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/10/stereo-360-image-and-video-capture.html">&lt;p&gt;The intention is for &lt;strong&gt;Not Near Enough&lt;/strong&gt; to be showcased at the 2021 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsdf.org.uk/what-we-do/our-yearly-festival/&quot;&gt;National Student Drama Festival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Clearly, given the pandemic, it will not be possible to present the project in the usual manner, with real equpment and real people together in a real space. However, the intention is to create a 360 degree video capture from inside the virtual space. Here, I will explore possibilities for its creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early 2018 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.unity3d.com/2018/01/26/stereo-360-image-and-video-capture/&quot;&gt;Unity blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; introduces a method to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that in 2018.1 creators can now capture stereoscopic 360 images and video in Unity. Whether you’re a VR developer who wants to make a 360 trailer to show off your experience or a director who wants to make an engaging cinematic short film, Unity’s new capture technology empowers you to share your immersive experience with an audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is based on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/vr/jump/rendering-ods-content.pdf&quot;&gt;Google’s Omni-directional Stereo (ODS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is that I am using Unity 2020.1, which no longer supports the old XR (Activate the feature: Edit &amp;gt; Project Settings &amp;gt; Player &amp;gt; XR Settings &amp;gt; 360 Stereo Capture). At this stage I am not certain if this technique will work at all with Unity 2020.1. I expect this to involve some trial and error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;however&quot;&gt;However…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity Recorder&lt;/strong&gt; is available via Unity’s Package Manager. This allows recording of 360 video (along with other, more regular formats) in the editor. This appears to do the job that is required. I would still like to find a way to record 360 video from a camera (or, even better, multiple cameras) placed within the virtual environment, that captures each scene, including pre-prepared video, streamed video and all player-avatars as they enter and interact with the environment. This would preferably be during ‘game play’, rather than edit mode. Wouldn’t it be nice if you could just select this from the ‘share’ menue in Quest Home, as an option when chosing to record, or to share, live stream/game-play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the Unity package, &lt;em&gt;Unity Recorder&lt;/em&gt;, in the Unity editor, I have been able to record 360 video footage from the main camera. It is, it seems, possible to select more than one camera, and I will explore this later. However, I used the Controller App to enter into the virtual space and placement was at the centre of one of the scene formations. I cued up a set of videos for a NNE student-created scene, started recording, and set the videos to start. Once I’d recorded a few minutes, I used &lt;em&gt;Google’s 360 video metadata tool&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/google/spatial-media/releases/tag/v2.0&quot;&gt;Spatial Media Metadata Injector&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - to ‘inject’ the metadata required to represent the video in the correct format for publication, and uploaded it to YouTube and Vimeo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trial 360 video, pre-metadata-injected&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:640px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; muted=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\GAM750\360-trial-1.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a 3D video that can be viewed on a regular flat screen using the mouse to move around, on a mobile device by moving the devices orientation in realtime, or using a phone and Google Cardboard to view a stereo version that reponds to movements of the head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works well. My only concern is the quality of the video - there does appear to be some pixelation that would be nice to avoid if possible. I will be examining the possibilities of enhancing the quality of the video, but for now, this is a good result with excellent potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/511245233&quot;&gt;View the video on Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metadata-injected 360 video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:640px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; muted=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\GAM750\360-trial-capture-2.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The intention is for Not Near Enough to be showcased at the 2021 National Student Drama Festival. Clearly, given the pandemic, it will not be possible to present the project in the usual manner, with real equpment and real people together in a real space. However, the intention is to create a 360 degree video capture from inside the virtual space. Here, I will explore possibilities for its creation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Homuncular Flexibility</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/homuncular-flexibility.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Homuncular Flexibility" /><published>2021-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/homuncular-flexibility</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/homuncular-flexibility.html">&lt;p&gt;This is connected to the study of &lt;em&gt;‘embodiment’&lt;/em&gt; in virtual reality (see earlier post, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/05/embodiment-in-virtual-reality.html&quot;&gt;embodiment in virtual reality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homuncular flexibility is the idea that one can inhabit and control a body that is different from one’s own, potentially radically so. The term was introduced by Jarad Lanier in 2006, and is derived from Penfield’s &lt;em&gt;“homunculus”&lt;/em&gt;: “in general the homunculus refers to the idea of a map of the body in the brain.” 
(Won, A.S. et al, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This appears to give licence to experiment with the user avatar, to stretch what could be possible when placing players within a virtual environment - playing with ideas of identity of self and others - whilst maintaining a healthy level of grounding and the sense of occupying one’s own ‘body’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The concept of homuncular flexibility (Lanier, 2006) proposes that users can learn to control bodies different from their own by changing the relationship between tracked and rendered motion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Human embodiment is flexible. Injuries like amputation and stroke can change the sense of where bodies begin and end. For example, after amputation, cortical mapping may shift such that areas that previously innervated the hand may shift to other parts of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Various experiments have suggested that “people can be led to alter their body schema by sensory input.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Won, A.S. et al, 2015)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well known experiment is known as the &lt;em&gt;“rubber hand illusion”&lt;/em&gt; (Botvinick and Cohen, 1998), and has been further studied in the more specific context of the reality-virtuality continuum (IJsselsteijn et al, 2006)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;participants saw a rubber hand on the table in front of them and observed it being stroked by a soft brush while feeling synchronous touch on their real hand hidden under the table. Participants gained a sense of ownership of the hand, such that they flinched when it was threatened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These feelings of ownership, or being present in the simulated body, provide clues to how a sense of presence may be created in an avatar body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Won, A.S. et al, 2015)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;research has provided evidence that simply perceiving a virtual body from a first-person perspective can create a sense of identification with an avatar, or “body transfer”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Slater, Spanlang, Sanchez-Vives, &amp;amp; Blanke, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Won, A.S., Bailenson, J., Lee, J. and Lanier, J., 2015. Homuncular flexibility in virtual reality. Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication, 20(3), pp.241-259.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lanier, J., 2006. Homuncular flexibility. Edge: The World Question Center.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Botvinick, M. and Cohen, J., 1998. Rubber hands ‘feel’touch that eyes see. Nature, 391(6669), pp.756-756.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;IJsselsteijn, W.A., de Kort, Y.A.W. and Haans, A., 2006. Is this my hand I see before me? The rubber hand illusion in reality, virtual reality, and mixed reality. Presence: Teleoperators and Virtual Environments, 15(4), pp.455-464.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slater, M., Spanlang, B., Sanchez-Vives, M. V. &amp;amp; Blanke, O. (2010). First person experience of body transfer in virtual reality, PLoS One, 5(5), 10564.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is connected to the study of ‘embodiment’ in virtual reality (see earlier post, embodiment in virtual reality).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Reality-Virtuality Continuum</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/03/the-reality-virtuality-continuum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Reality-Virtuality Continuum" /><published>2021-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/03/the-reality-virtuality-continuum</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/03/the-reality-virtuality-continuum.html">&lt;p&gt;The virtuality continuum is a continuous scale ranging between the completely virtual, a virtuality, and the completely real, reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\GAM750\Virtuality_Continuum_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Reality-Virtuality Continuum&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1994 Paul Milgram and Fumio Kishino defined a mixed reality as “…anywhere between the extrema of the virtuality continuum”, where the Virtuality Continuum extends from the completely real through to the completely virtual environment with augmented reality and augmented virtuality ranging between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This paper focuses on Mixed Reality (MR) visual displays, a particular subset of Virtual Reality (VR) related technologies that involve the merging of real and virtual worlds somewhere along the &lt;em&gt;“virtuality continuum”&lt;/em&gt; which connects completely real environments to completely virtual ones. Probably the best known of these is Augmented Reality (AR), which refers to all cases in which the display of an otherwise real environment is augmented by means of virtual (computer graphic) objects. The converse case on the virtuality continuum is therefore Augmented Virtuality (AV). Six classes of hybrid MR display environments are identified. However, an attempt to distinguish these classes on the basis of whether they are primarily video or computer graphics based, whether the real world is viewed directly or via some electronic display medium, whether the viewer is intended to feel part of the world or on the outside looking in, and whether or not the scale of the display is intended to map orthoscopically onto the real world leads to quite different groupings among the six identified classes, thereby demonstrating the need for an efficient taxonomy, or classification framework, according to which essential differences can be identified. The ‘obvious’ distinction between the terms &lt;em&gt;“real”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“virtual”&lt;/em&gt; is shown to have a number of different aspects, depending on whether one is dealing with real or virtual objects, real or virtual images, and direct or non-direct viewing of these. An (approximately) three dimensional taxonomy is proposed, comprising the following dimensions: Extent of World Knowledge (&lt;em&gt;“how much do we know about the world being displayed?”&lt;/em&gt;), Reproduction Fidelity (&lt;em&gt;“how ‘realistically’ are we able to display it?”&lt;/em&gt;), and Extent of Presence Metaphor (&lt;em&gt;“what is the extent of the illusion that the observer is present within that world?”&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Milgram, P. and Kishino, F., 1994. A taxonomy of mixed reality visual displays. IEICE TRANSACTIONS on Information and Systems, 77(12), pp.1321-1329.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The conventionally held view of a Virtual Reality (VR) environment is one in which the participant-observer is totally immersed in, and able to interact with, a completely synthetic world. Such a world may mimic the properties of some real-world environments, either existing or fictional; however, it can also exceed the bounds of physical reality by creating a world in which the physical laws ordinarily governing space, time, mechanics, material properties, etc. no longer hold. What may be overlooked in this view, however, is that the VR label is also frequently used in association with a variety of other environments, to which total immersion and complete synthesis do not necessarily pertain, but which fall somewhere along a virtuality continuum. In this paper we focus on a particular subclass of VR related technologies that involve the merging of real and virtual worlds, which we refer to generically as Mixed Reality (MR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Milgram, P., Takemura, H., Utsumi, A. and Kishino, F., 1995, December. Augmented reality: A class of displays on the reality-virtuality continuum. In Telemanipulator and telepresence technologies (Vol. 2351, pp. 282-292). International Society for Optics and Photonics.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;magic-book&quot;&gt;Magic Book&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a mixed reality interface that draws upon Paul Milgram’s “reality-virtuality continuum” taxonomy.  This imagines the reader having the ability to view and enter scenes from different points along the continuum, where “VR users can see other VR users represented as life-sized virtual avatars, while AR users will see VR users as miniature avatars in the scene.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Billinghurst, M., Kato, H. and Poupyrev, I., 2001, March. MagicBook: transitioning between reality and virtuality. In &lt;em&gt;CHI’01 extended abstracts on Human factors in computing systems&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 25-26).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-not-near-enough-approach&quot;&gt;The Not Near Enough approach&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The approach taken with the Not Near Enough project&lt;/strong&gt; plays with notions and ideas that are expressed within discussions surrounding the concept of a reality-virtuality continuum. This big &lt;em&gt;‘playground’&lt;/em&gt; we have been creating attempts to break down the continuum, or to link up parts of the continuum. We have video streaming and audio streaming coming into the VR. This plays with the boundaries between virtual reality and reality and the ways they connect; the boundaries between &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; realities and the &lt;em&gt;‘realities’&lt;/em&gt; of theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NNE audience is placed in a space created as virtual reality. Taking Milgram’s idea of the converse case of &lt;em&gt;Augmented Reality (AR)&lt;/em&gt; on the virtuality continuum being &lt;em&gt;Augmented Virtuality (AV)&lt;/em&gt;, there appears to be a correlation with the way in which the NNE virtual theatre space is augmented by live (as well as pre-prepared) video and audio feeds brought in from the world &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the virtual world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real-time interactions that take place between real and the virtual can be represented by interactions between points on the continuum, as can notions of the different modes of control: &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;intrinsic&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;extrinsic&lt;/em&gt;; control over the mechanics of the virtual objects and over how media is displayed from external sources, can be exerted both from within the virtual space and external to it. The experimentation with OSC takes this further, by providing the potential for standard theatre contol equipment to effect change within the virtual space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationships between performers, audience and stage managers, in terms of not only their differing roles, but also their positioning and nature of their interactions within and across the continuum, is also interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What motivates the audience compared with what motivates the performers?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do limitations and affordances affect motivation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does witnessing and experiencing other points on the continuum, from the perspective of their own, affect this? Is it a little like being aware of the concept of a fourth dimension, and having the ability to imagine it, when reality dictates that one only has access to three dimensions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is interesting that theatre is already a kind of virtual way of viewing the world&lt;/strong&gt;. It is already about making these crazy virtual worlds where anything can happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow – theatre &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; ‘VR’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VR is perfect for theatre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theatre-is-perfect-for-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;Theatre is perfect for virtual reality!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps VR is the stage. In a similar way that old wooden stage is, or TV, or Film. But even more-so.
Is it that, what we have here with VR is, by its very nature, another very natural place for theatre? 
The concept of the virtual Avatar is relatively new, but could this be analogous to costume and make-up? 
Is the idea of embodiment in VR so different to simply getting into character? These are natural questions raised by the nature of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, is it going too far to suggest that &lt;strong&gt;theatre IS virtual reality&lt;/strong&gt;?! When we create theatre, no matter what form it takes, it is a kind of Virtual Reality, in a form of its very own. If this is the case, then, as the human condition appears to need to create theatre, then does VR tap into something very similar? In the same way that video games tap into and immerse us into alternative realities, allowing us to become someone else or to experience something from another person’s perspective, within a situation that is not ‘real’, but is an &lt;em&gt;alternative&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;virtual-reality-is-absolutely-made-for-theatre&quot;&gt;Virtual Reality is absolutely made for theatre!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in this way, the NNE version of the &lt;strong&gt;reality-virtuality continuum&lt;/strong&gt; is the continuum between performers in reality, being realised in virtual reality, where they are consumed, interacted with, affected, before being relayed back into reality (via the controller app).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The virtuality continuum is a continuous scale ranging between the completely virtual, a virtuality, and the completely real, reality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/reflections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/reflections.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-challenges&quot;&gt;The Challenges&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a distributed multiplayer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communicate the complexity of the system as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a complex experiment, where I drop research and practice together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outlier, the interest -  for some absurd reason I tried to fit VR around theatre. Attempting to rebuild some of the concepts and models that exist in theatre, in VR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The request was to build something that already exists physically, in VR. It is safer to the theatre makers to do this. But perhaps this will open up opportunities for them to consider bringing the technology to the theatre makers, allowing them to embrace alternative modes of performance and of theatre environmental control. In a sense I have been a guide, showing them the potential. The hope is that they will see the potential of VR environments for what they can bring in their own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creativity&quot;&gt;Creativity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-performances&quot;&gt;The performances&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Challenges</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Preparing for deployement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/preparing-for-deployment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing for deployement" /><published>2020-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/preparing-for-deployment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/preparing-for-deployment.html">&lt;p&gt;Last minute changes, fixed etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controller app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘base 10’ video selection buttons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;teleport every player to final scene - mutliplayer wire-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final scene:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;360 degree video,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;skybox,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;teleport to new spawn point some distance away,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remove floor,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move overhead camera with players.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem with sound from screen videos - not noticed before as no sound included on videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An annoying problem as there appears to have been a number of changes over the years regarding how to set up audio on video clips. Eventually, a forum thread led to the answer, which is specific for clips playing from URL sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://forum.unity.com/threads/video-player-is-not-playing-audio.486924/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Audio settings seem to work differently when playing from a clip and from a URL. For playing from a URL, in 2018.1.2f1, the correct sequence to set up the player is this. First, set up the player; player must be stopped for this, and not been Prepare()d yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// We want to play from a URL.
// Set the source mode FIRST, before changing audio settings;
// as setting the source mode will reset those.
videoPlayer.source = VideoSource.Url;

// Set mode to Audio Source.
videoPlayer.audioOutputMode = VideoAudioOutputMode.AudioSource;

// We want to control one audio track with the video player
videoPlayer.controlledAudioTrackCount = 1;

// We enable the first track, which has the id zero
videoPlayer.EnableAudioTrack(0, true);

// ...and we set the audio source for this track
videoPlayer.SetTargetAudioSource(0, audioSource);

// now set an url to play
videoPlayer.url = &quot;...some url...&quot;
Aftwards, in a coroutine, prepare and play:

Code (CSharp):
videoPlayer.Prepare();

while (!videoPlayer.isPrepared) {
    yield return new WaitForEndOfFrame();
}

videoPlayer.Play();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of time for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;names above players&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;360 video capture in scenes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I’ll find time to add these during the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 360 videos, in particular, would be helpful for the students to document the work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last minute changes, fixed etc.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creativity, Collaboration and Learning In Virtual Reality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/creativity-and-virtual-reality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creativity, Collaboration and Learning In Virtual Reality" /><published>2020-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/creativity-and-virtual-reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/creativity-and-virtual-reality.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;definitions-of-creativity&quot;&gt;Definitions of creativity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, I have been keen to explore the idea of not only providing a virtual environment where creative processes can happen, but as a means for the promotion and enhancement of creativity itself. According to Margaret A. Boden, “Many psychologists define creativity as the novel combination of familiar ideas” (Boden, M.A., 1996). This definition appears to neatly fit the idea of bringing along familiar theatre practice and creative patterns and treating them in order to be parsed through an unfamiliar and novel environment defined by the unique set of affordances provided by virtual reality in general, and this theatre environment in particular. This is reinforced by M. Rhodes, who asked “Isn’t creativity, in simple language, the process of reorganizing knowledge (general or specific knowledge), and of articulating that synthesis so that other people can understand the meaning” (Rhodes, M., 1961). Again, the idea is that creativity involves articulating the familiar in unfamiliar terms, such that people are able to understand, to attach themselves to the way the ideas have been put forward, albeit in unfamiliar forms or contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the enhancement of creativity is more tricky: “relatively few empirical studies have directly addressed the question of whether and, if so, how creativity might be enhanced.” (Nickerson, R. S. 1999). However, breaking existing and recognised ‘rules’ appears to be one way (Xinyue Wang et al, 2018). So, the idea of taking something familiar, breaking the accepted rules and norms, and articulating it so that it is understandable to everyday people, could be a way of understanding how VR can enhance creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nickerson, R.S., 1999. Enhancing creativity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wang, X., Lu, K., Runco, M.A. and Hao, N., 2018. Break the “wall” and become creative: enacting embodied metaphors in virtual reality. Consciousness and cognition, 62, pp.102-109.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Creativity in general is the ability to come up with new ideas that are surprising yet intelligible, and also valuable in some way. This is true for all cases of creativity, whether within science, art, politics, cookery, whatever”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Three different types of creative thinking: combinational, exploratory and transformations (Boden, 1990; 1994)”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Combinational creativity produces new ideas by combining (associating) old ideas in unfamiliar ways.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Both exploratory and transformational creativity require knowledge of a rather different type. Namely, they arise out of some culturally accepted style of thinking, or structured conceptual space, that the person as learnt – and, to some extent, mastered.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exploratory creatively “investigates the possibilities inherent in the space: just what do the rules enable one to do?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boden, M., 2001. Creativity and knowledge. Creativity in education, pp.95-102.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boden, M.A., 1996. Creativity. In Artificial intelligence (pp. 267-291). Academic Press.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the definition of creativity is problematic for four reasons. The first problem is that positive evaluation is essential to the concept. An idea counted as creative must be interesting. This judgment often rests on social and historical factors, and no purely psychological theory could explain these evaluations. The second problem concerns the question whether the originator must recognize the value of an idea for it to be called creative. If so, then someone who has a good idea but rejects it as uninteresting is not creative. The third difficulty is the tension between psychological (P) and historical (H) senses. An idea is P-creative if it is creative with respect to the mind of the person concerned, even if others have had that idea already. An idea is H-creative if it is P-creative and no other person has had the idea before. H-creativity is more glamorous, but P-creativity is more fundamental. The fourth problem is that the familiar operational definition fits only some cases. Many psychologists define creativity as the novel combination of familiar ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rhodes, M., 1961. An analysis of creativity. The Phi Delta Kappan, 42(7), pp.305-310.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Isn’t creativity, in simple language, the process of reorganizing knowledge (general or specific knowledge), and of articulating that synthesis so that other people can understand the meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creativity-and-narrative&quot;&gt;Creativity and narrative&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The most ambitious promise of the new narrative medium is its potential for telling stories about whole systems. The format that most fully exploits the properties of digital environments is not the hyper-text or the fighting game but the simulation: the virtual world full of interrelated entities, a world we can enter, manipulate, and observe in process. We might therefore expect the virtuosos of cyber drama to create simulated environments that capture behavioural patterns and patterns of interrelationships with a new clarity.” (Murray, J.Y., 1997: 280)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Murray, J.H., 1997. Hamlet on the holodeck: The future of narrative in cyberspace. Massachusetts. MIT press.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;enhancing-creativity&quot;&gt;Enhancing creativity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fink, A., Grabner, R.H., Gebauer, D., Reishofer, G., Koschutnig, K. and Ebner, F., 2010. Enhancing creativity by means of cognitive stimulation: Evidence from an fMRI study. NeuroImage, 52(4), pp.1687-1695.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cognitive stimulation via the exposure to ideas of other people is an effective tool in stimulating creativity in group-based creativity techniques.
Cognitive stimulation was effective in improving originality, and this performance improvement was associated with activation increases in a neural network&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;virtual-reality-and-the-enhancement-of-creativity-and-innovation&quot;&gt;Virtual reality and the enhancement of creativity and innovation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Thornhill-Miller and Dupont, 2016)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thornhill-Miller, B. and Dupont, J.M., 2016. Virtual reality and the enhancement of creativity and innovation: Under recognized potential among converging technologies?. Journal of Cognitive Education and Psychology, 15(1), pp.102-121.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://connect.springerpub.com/content/sgrjcep/15/1/102&quot;&gt;https://connect.springerpub.com/content/sgrjcep/15/1/102&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“perhaps the safest, most fully developed of the emerging technologies of cognitive enhancement”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“an underused tool for the enhancement of creativity”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“researchers, educators, trainers, designers, managers, and others concerned with innovation should be more informed about virtual reality technologies (VRTs) both because of their widespread and growing accessibility and because of the significant, synergistic contributions they can make to human performance and understanding”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“VRTs offer a cost-effective means of implementing and optimizing nearly all conventional individual and collaborative creativity enhancement techniques while also offering potent new possibilities and combinations not available by other means”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“five ways VR can be used to enhance creativity and problem solving: (a) by changing aspects of the self and self-perception; (b) by optimizing interactions and collaboration with others; (c) by optimizing environmental conditions and influences; (d) by facilitating guidance or gamification of the problem-solving process; and (e) by offering an arena for the integration of other technologies of creativity enhancement such as pharmacological enhancement, brain stimulation, and neurofeedback.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;paint-with-me-stimulating-creativity-and-empathy-while-painting-with-a-painter-in-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;Paint with me: Stimulating creativity and empathy while painting with a painter in virtual reality&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Gerry, 2017)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discusses embodiment and collaboration resulting in empathy and hightened creative potential. These are aspects of VR that I believe are important to the success of NNE’s interactive, creative environment. The abilty to put oneself in someone else’s shoes, and to view the world from outside one’s own reality, gives a different perspective that stimulates the senses and imagination. (see &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/12/05/embodiment-in-virtual-reality.html&quot;&gt;embodiment in virtual reality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-in-virtual-reality-effects-on-performance-emotion-and-engagement&quot;&gt;Learning in virtual reality: Effects on performance, emotion and engagement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Allcoat and von Mühlenen, 2018)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study appears to show clear advantages of VR over other mediums for learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recent advances in virtual reality (VR) technology allow for potential learning and education applications. For this study, 99 participants were assigned to one of three learning conditions: traditional (textbook style), VR and video (a passive control). The learning materials used the same text and 3D model for all conditions. Each participant was given a knowledge test before and after learning. Participants in the traditional and VR conditions had &lt;strong&gt;improved overall performance&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. learning, including knowledge acquisition and understanding) compared to those in the video condition. Participants in the VR condition also showed &lt;strong&gt;better performance for ‘remembering’&lt;/strong&gt; than those in the traditional and the video conditions. Emotion self-ratings before and after the learning phase showed an &lt;strong&gt;increase in positive emotions and a decrease in negative emotions&lt;/strong&gt; for the VR condition. Conversely there was a decrease in positive emotions in both the traditional and video conditions. The Web-based learning tools evaluation scale also found that participants in the VR condition &lt;strong&gt;reported higher engagement&lt;/strong&gt; than those in the other conditions. Overall, VR displayed an &lt;strong&gt;improved learning experience&lt;/strong&gt; when compared to traditional and video learning methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;being-there-in-the-midst-of-the-story-how-immersive-journalism-affects-our-perceptions-and-cognitions&quot;&gt;Being There in the Midst of the Story: How Immersive Journalism Affects Our Perceptions and Cognitions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Sundar et al, 2017)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically relating to journalism, but the similarity and comparison of the response to theatrical ‘story-telling’ is fairly clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Immersive journalism in the form of virtual reality (VR) headsets and 360°-video is becoming more mainstream and is much touted for &lt;strong&gt;inducing greater “presence”&lt;/strong&gt; than traditional text. But, does this presence influence psychological outcomes of reading news, such as memory for story content, perceptions of credibility, and empathy felt toward story characters? We propose that &lt;strong&gt;two key technological affordances of VR (modality and interactivity) are responsible for triggering three presence-related cognitive heuristics (being-there, interaction, and realism), which influence news readers’ memory and their perceptions of credibility, empathy, and story-sharing intentions&lt;/strong&gt;. We report a 3 (storytelling medium: VR vs. 360°-video vs. Text) × 2 (story: “The displaced” and “The click effect”) mixed-factorial experiment, in which participants (N = 129) experienced two New York Times stories (that differed in their emotional intensity) using one of three mediums (VR, 360°-video, Text). Participants who experienced the stories using VR and 360°-video &lt;strong&gt;outperformed those who read the same stories using text with pictures, not only on such presence-related outcomes as being-there, interaction, and realism, but also on perceived source credibility, story-sharing intention, and feelings of empathy&lt;/strong&gt;. Moreover, we found that &lt;strong&gt;senses of being-there, interaction, and realism mediated the relationship between storytelling medium and reader perceptions of credibility, story recall, and story-sharing intention&lt;/strong&gt;. These findings have &lt;strong&gt;theoretical implications for the psychology of virtual reality&lt;/strong&gt;, and practical applications for immersive journalism in particular and interactive media in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reasons-to-use-virtual-reality-in-education-and-training-courses-and-a-model-to-determine-when-to-use-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;Reasons to use virtual reality in education and training courses and a model to determine when to use virtual reality&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Pantelidis, 2010)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper discusses a significant number of studies that demonstrate the use and advantages of VR in an education environment. As a tool for learning, VR appears to display many useful traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Studies show that a virtual environment can “stimulate learning and comprehension, because it provides a tight coupling between symbolic and experiential information” (Bowman, Hodges, Allison, &amp;amp; Wineman, 1998)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Numerous studies have focused on how children and young learners interact and learn in a 3D environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;potential of spatial and social technologies in a virtual learning environment (VLE) through presence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gerry, L.J., 2017. Paint with me: Stimulating creativity and empathy while painting with a painter in virtual reality. IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics, 23(4), pp.1418-1426.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thornhill-Miller, B. and Dupont, J.M., 2016. Virtual reality and the enhancement of creativity and innovation: Under recognized potential among converging technologies?. Journal of Cognitive Education and Psychology, 15(1), pp.102-121.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allcoat, D. and von Mühlenen, A., 2018. Learning in virtual reality: Effects on performance, emotion and engagement. Research in Learning Technology, 26.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sundar, S.S., Kang, J. and Oprean, D., 2017. Being there in the midst of the story: How immersive journalism affects our perceptions and cognitions. Cyberpsychology, Behavior, and Social Networking, 20(11), pp.672-682.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pantelidis, V.S., 2010. Reasons to use virtual reality in education and training courses and a model to determine when to use virtual reality. Themes in Science and Technology Education, 2(1-2), pp.59-70.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Definitions of creativity</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embodiment in Virtual Reality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/embodiment-in-virtual-reality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodiment in Virtual Reality" /><published>2020-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/embodiment-in-virtual-reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/embodiment-in-virtual-reality.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;inducing-illusory-ownership-of-a-virtual-body&quot;&gt;Inducing illusory ownership of a virtual body&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/neuro.01.029.2009/full&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slater, M., Pérez Marcos, D., Ehrsson, H. and Sanchez-Vives, M.V., 2009. Inducing illusory ownership of a virtual body. Frontiers in neuroscience, 3, p.29.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Virtual reality additionally provides power to investigate these illusions at the whole body level. In Figure 2 we show an example of what can be seen when someone wears a tracked head-mounted display, &lt;strong&gt;looks down, and sees a virtual body in place of their real one&lt;/strong&gt;. The very act of looking down, changing head orientation in order to gaze in a certain direction, with the visual images changing as they would in reality is already a powerful clue that you are located in the virtual place that you perceive. We argue elsewhere that multisensory contingencies that correspond approximately to those employed to perceive physical reality provide a necessary condition for the illusion of being in the virtual place (Slater 2009 ). Now imagine that you move, and the virtual body moves in correspondence with your movements, or you see something touch your virtual body and you feel the touch in the corresponding location in your real body. These events add significantly to the reality of what is being perceived – &lt;strong&gt;not only are you in the virtual place, but you also have the illusion that the events occurring are real – therefore increasing the likelihood that you would respond realistically to virtual events and situations&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This realisation is important for the development of virtual reality applications because it means that one is not restricted to ultra-realistic simulations and high definition visual displays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-audience-avatar&quot;&gt;The Audience Avatar&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creation of the audience’s avatars did not elicit much developmental time. However, this is a subject area that deserves more thought – and it will do so as the project continues.  Interestingly, this subject was picked up quite early on by the students. Somehow, a sense of individual identity is a property that is desired but currently lacking. Virtual social media has recently placed emphasis on the individuality of the avatar, but perhaps this aspect gets in the way of experiencing the performance itself, as the main attraction.  I have certainly felt this to be the case when attending viewings of performances in such social media platforms as AltspaceVr and VRChat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-choice-references-and-worthwhile-reading&quot;&gt;Some choice references and worthwhile reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Including the occasional response/thought of my own&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;are-we-already-living-in-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;Are We Already Living in Virtual Reality?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A new technology — virtual embodiment — challenges our understanding of who and what we are.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rothman, J., 2018. Are we already living in virtual reality. The New Yorker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/04/02/are-we-already-living-in-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/04/02/are-we-already-living-in-virtual-reality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very interesting read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“On some level, the brain doesn’t know the difference between real reality and virtual reality. And a character on a 2-D screen is completely different from one that’s your height and looks you in the eye.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With a team of various collaborators, Slater and Sanchez-Vives have created many other-body simulations; they show how inhabiting a new virtual body can produce meaningful psychological shifts. In one study, participants are re-embodied as a little girl. Surrounded by a stuffed bear, a rocking horse, and other toys, they watch as their mother sternly demands a cleaner room. Afterward, on psychological tests, they associate themselves with more childlike characteristics. (When I tried it, under the supervision of the V.R. researcher Domna Banakou, I was astonished by my small size, and by the intimidating, Olympian height from which the mother addressed me.) In another, white participants spend around ten minutes in the body of a virtual black person, learning Tai Chi. Afterward, their scores on a test designed to reveal unconscious racial bias shift significantly. “These effects happen fast, and seem to last,” Slater said. A week later, the white participants still had less racist attitudes. (The racial-bias results have been replicated several times in Barcelona, and also by a second team, in London.) Embodied simulations seem to slip beneath the cognitive threshold, affecting the associative, unconscious parts of the mind. “It’s directly experiential,” Slater said. “It’s not ‘I know.’ It’s ‘I am.’ ”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-we-experience-immersive-virtual-environments-the-concept-of-presence-and-its-measurement&quot;&gt;How we experience immersive virtual environments: the concept of presence and its measurement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slater, M., Lotto, B., Arnold, M.M. and Sanchez-Vives, M.V., 2009. How we experience immersive virtual environments: the concept of presence and its measurement. Anuario de psicología, 40(2), pp.193-210.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slater and Sanchez-Vives&lt;/strong&gt; - these two researchers (who happen to be married) have produced a number of papers that are worth, at the very least, a cursory reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terms to be researched: out-of-body experiences, body ownership, body transfer illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NB&lt;/strong&gt;: Emphasis my own&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a review of the concept of presence in virtual environments and associated literature (Sanchez-Vives &amp;amp; Slater, 2005) it was reported that experimental studies have found that &lt;strong&gt;factors that contribute to high reported presence are mainly concerned with the form of how data is displayed to participants and how they are able to interact, rather than with the level of realism of the displays&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, wide field of view, low latency, high frame-rate, surround sound, haptic feedback, stereo rather than mono displays, head-tracking all seem to contribute to higher reported presence. In addition the ability to interact with the environment making use of whole body interaction in a natural way appears to favour higher reported presence in comparison with “button-press” types of interaction more suited to two-dimensional displays. &lt;strong&gt;What does not seem to be important is high fidelity visual realism&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, a person giving a talk in an immersive virtual environment to an audience of virtual characters who appear to be responding to the talk is likely to react to the behaviour of the virtual characters as if they were real –in spite of the absolute knowledge that there is no audience there, and in spite of the low level of realism of the characters (Pertaub et al., 2002).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sanchez-Vives, M.V. and Slater, M., 2005. From presence to consciousness through virtual reality. Nature Reviews Neuroscience, 6(4), pp.332-339.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pertaub, D.P., Slater, M. and Barker, C., 2002. An experiment on public speaking anxiety in response to three different types of virtual audience. Presence: Teleoperators &amp;amp; Virtual Environments, 11(1), pp.68-78.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-sense-of-embodiment-in-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;The Sense of Embodiment in Virtual Reality&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1162/PRES_a_00124&quot;&gt;https://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1162/PRES_a_00124&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kilteni, K., Groten, R. and Slater, M., 2012. The sense of embodiment in virtual reality. Presence: Teleoperators and Virtual Environments, 21(4), pp.373-387.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does it feel like to own, to control, and to be inside a body? The multidimensional nature of this experience together with the continuous presence of one’s biological body, render both theoretical and experimental approaches problematic. Nevertheless, exploitation of immersive virtual reality has allowed a reframing of this question to whether it is possible to experience the same sensations towards a virtual body inside an immersive virtual environment as toward the biological body, and if so, to what extent. The current paper addresses these issues by referring to the Sense of Embodiment (SoE). Due to the conceptual confusion around this sense, we provide a working definition which states that SoE consists of three subcomponents: the sense of self-location, the sense of agency, and the sense of body ownership. Under this proposed structure, measures and experimental manipulations reported in the literature are reviewed and related challenges are outlined. Finally, future experimental studies are proposed to overcome those challenges, toward deepening the concept of SoE and enhancing it in virtual applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not accessible without payment, but the three main ‘subcomponents’ are worth considering and exploring: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the sense of self-location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the sense of agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the sense of body ownership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-in-the-wild-experiment-on-presence-and-embodiment-using-consumer-virtual-reality-equipment&quot;&gt;An ‘In the Wild’ Experiment on Presence and Embodiment using Consumer Virtual Reality Equipment&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7383331&quot;&gt;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7383331&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steed, A., Frlston, S., Lopez, M.M., Drummond, J., Pan, Y. and Swapp, D., 2016. An ‘in the wild’experiment on presence and embodiment using consumer virtual reality equipment. IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics, 22(4), pp.1406-1414.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“a study on presence and embodiment within virtual reality”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“a self-avatar had a positive effect on self-report of presence and embodiment”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;connected-to-my-avatar&quot;&gt;Connected to my avatar&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biocca, F., 2014, June. Connected to my avatar. In International Conference on Social Computing and Social Media (pp. 421-429). Springer, Cham.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We review some of psychological effects of avatar identification and embodiment including evidence of the effects of avatar identification and embodiment on changes in behavior, arousal, learning, and self-construal. Furthermore, some avatar based changes in perception, cognition, and behavior may carry over and extend into changes into user’s real world perception and behavior&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-immersive-is-enough-a-meta-analysis-of-the-effect-of-immersive-technology-on-user-presence&quot;&gt;How Immersive Is Enough? A Meta-analysis of the Effect of Immersive Technology on User Presence&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cummings, J.J. and Bailenson, J.N., 2016. How immersive is enough? A meta-analysis of the effect of immersive technology on user presence. Media Psychology, 19(2), pp.272-309.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The concept of presence, or “being there” is a frequently emphasized factor in immersive mediated environments. It is often assumed that greater levels of immersive quality elicit higher levels of presence, in turn enhancing the effectiveness of a mediated experience…
results show that increased levels of user-tracking, the use of stereoscopic visuals, and wider fields of view of visual displays are significantly more impactful than improvements to most other immersive system features, including quality of visual and auditory content&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;paint-with-me-stimulating-creativity-and-empathy-while-painting-with-a-painter-in-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;Paint with me: Stimulating creativity and empathy while painting with a painter in virtual reality&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gerry, L.J., 2017. Paint with me: Stimulating creativity and empathy while painting with a painter in virtual reality. IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics, 23(4), pp.1418-1426.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“On March 25, 2014, Facebook CEO and Founder Mark Zuckerberg announced that Facebook had purchased Oculus VR, the leader in virtual reality technology. In his announcement, Zuckerberg suggests that virtual reality will be the new platform for social media, enabling a more personal and immersive exchange of experiences. Marc Andreessen, an Oculus VR angel investor, proclaims that the Oculus will “redefine fundamental human experiences.” (Oculus Blog, December 13, 2013) “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Termed “embodied experiences” (Ahn, Le, &amp;amp; Bailenson, 2015) or “embodied simulations (Bertrand, Franco, Pointeau, &amp;amp; Cherene, 2014), immersive virtual environment technology (IVET) can allow users to embody the first-person point-of-view of another person while seeing and hearing sounds from the experiential locus of another person, as though the viewer can wear another person’s sensory apparatus. This simulation allows for the illusion of being in another person’s shoes and embodying their perspective, a situation perhaps best represented by Spike Jonze’s 2006 film Being John Malkovich, wherein characters enter a portal that allows them to see, feel, and hear through John Malkovich’s body. Because this new communication medium allows people to share a new mode of access one another’s experiences, this study hypothesizes that it can facilitate greater intimacy, understanding, and empathy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the opening quote, David Foster Wallace summarizes one of the greatest obstacles of human communication: the attempt to translate the felt immediacy of first-person experience to someone else, and to moreover understand someone else’s experience. Wallace states that all of our experiences are rendered through an embodied point of view, and that this orientation places the subject at the center of his or her experiences. However, recent advances in filmed, streamed, and simulated virtual reality environments allow subjects to see &lt;strong&gt;first-personally from the point-of-view of another person, character, or avatar. Thus, in this sense, it could be argued that through this technology it is now possible to have exactly the type of experience that Wallace suggests our day-to-day mode of being occludes: an experience in which a person is not the absolute center of their own experience. Instead, through this technology the individual is placed in the center of someone else’s experience&lt;/strong&gt;. This inductive study explores how this virtual simulation can transform our ability to relate to and learn from one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My thoughts: -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“one of the greatest obstacles of human communication: the attempt to translate the felt immediacy of first-person experience to someone else, and to moreover understand someone else’s experience”… “all of our experiences are rendered through an embodied point of view, and that this orientation places the subject at the center of his or her experiences”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of the ‘player’ in the mutlplayer environment can not be completely replicated and expererienced in exactly the same way, but it is important to at least replicate the environment as near to exactly for all participants. It is then possible to share the player-manipulations of this environment, so as to share in the experience, and some form of common language in order to describe the experience. This became a hugely important factor when ensuring that, not only each player within the space experienced everything exactly the same as any other, but also, those who are responsible for manipulating the space and, therefore, the experience of those within the space, should not be removed any degree more than is absolutely necessary. The controller, as designed, therefore, is an attempt to allow exertion of control and manipulation, but at the same time, removing, or at least reducing, the distance and potential separation, between stage management, performer, and audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we are not ‘just’ experiencing someone else’s experience,  this is our own experience, experienced for ourselves. Yet, perhaps, it is the inexcapable distance held between the player and their avatar, within the virtual space, that allows a degree of consideration and contemplation of the particular cicumstances of that ‘other’ entity, which would otherwise be difficult to separate from first-person experience, that allows a degree of objectivity to come into play in an area where the subjectivity of the first person would normally cloud any potential, deep understanding of a potential connection between the player and their environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, perhaps this is over-thought and overblown. But we are certainly finding ourselves in a place where worlds can be created and experienced at first-hand, as an individual inseperably part of them, able to interact and affect them, but yet also emphasising one’s removal from the real physical world that allows us to breath, eat, flurish and also to fall ill, starve, suffocate and die. Evocations of empathy and a creative, collaborative response to these virtual surroundings, is not difficult to imagine. In fact, imagination is all but provided for and stiumulated, in much the same way that it would be in any ‘immersive’ environment. Perhaps the main difference here is that of ‘agency’, the ability to make changes and to be involved in the creation, to varying levels, of the environment itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The distance between the placement and experience of the user’s avatar and the somewhat contrived and artificial situation in which they find themselves, unexpectedly provides a sense of hightened reality; perhaps this is because the limited control afforded and the resulting sense of helplessness combine to emphasise feelings of vulnerability; and vulnerability makes one somehow feel ‘alive’.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtual social media has recently placed emphasis on the individuality of the avatar, but perhaps this aspect gets in the way of experiencing the performance itself, as the main attraction.  I have certainly felt this to be the case when attending viewings of performances in such social media platforms as AltspaceVr and VRChat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reflecting-on-the-shelterbox-project&quot;&gt;Reflecting on the ShelterBox project&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy is a condition that I explored in my previous project - a gamified simulation of preparing and deploying overseas disaster-releaf aid for the charity, ShelterBox. The idea of seeing something from someone else’s perspective, experiencing and sharing problems they encounter in their own specific situation, can invoke and enhance feelings of empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;communication-applications-of-virtual-reality&quot;&gt;Communication Applications of Virtual Reality&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;F. Biocca and M. R. Levy, “Communication Applications of Virtual Reality”, Communication in the age of virtual reality, pp. 127-157, 1995.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Inducing illusory ownership of a virtual body</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Controller App</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/controller-app-coming-together.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Controller App" /><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/controller-app-coming-together</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/controller-app-coming-together.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s starting to come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More efficient: -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not attempting to update screens if they already are showing the correct video&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not updating individual screens and then adding to realtime array - now only realtime array is updated, which fires the event in the other clients and updates their arrays.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use local ‘buffer’ for screen media, which is synced locally with RealtimeArray. If an item exists in the RealtimeArray and in the buffer, there is no need to process it at all when a model is added by a remote client. If a player joins late, their local buffer is compared to see what is missing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added screen portal - also uses a buffer. Portal can be set to on for any screen in any scene. Setting it to ‘off’ is a problem at the moment, as RealtimeArray does not have a ‘didChange’ event. There must be a way, but for now I’m having to set it to off locally, and it updates remotely only when another portal is added because a new model is added to the array.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, things are much quicker, with little lag, and screens no longer go blank before having video assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added ability to move and rotate overhead camera.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added VR player, which connects to the VR player’s room and thus is instantiated by remote VR clients and shown in the controller app. This is really very interesting, giving a feeling of &lt;strong&gt;‘god-like’&lt;/strong&gt; control over the VR players’ world!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made players emissive yellow for clarity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instantiating buttons - started with Agora video stream channels as they are created and destroyed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s starting to come together.</summary></entry></feed>