<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-05T12:58:11+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Poly|Caco|Phony</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/05/polycacophony.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poly|Caco|Phony" /><published>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/05/polycacophony</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/05/polycacophony.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\nordic-designer-collaboration.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Musical collaboration&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;polyphony&quot;&gt;Polyphony&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A musical texture created by multiple individual and independent parts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that I will be taking forward for this project is to use Virtual Reality in the creation of an immersive space in which two ‘players’ can join together to create sonic and visual effects and events, though physical actions and interactions. The results of such actions may be seen as ephemeral visual and aural moments that exist for a short time after an event is triggered. The space will be an environment in which the players can experiment and create through playful interactions with the space itself, the objects within it, and the players themselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cacophony&quot;&gt;Cacophony&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A harsh, discordant, jarring, mixture of sounds&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, as the developer, this will be a vehicle to exlore, not only the technical problems, issues and solutions involved in creating such an event, but also to attempt to use the freedom from the physical world afforded by virtual reality in order to transend the nature of objects as we understand them, pushing the possibilities of how we can expect them to react, sonically and visually, as the result of actions directed upon them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to witness not only how participants interact with these stimuli within a shared space, but also how each interacts with the other. Will there be an attempt to create something collaboratively, in the mode of a ‘jam’, or will they find there is too much stimuli to comfortably handle, resulting in the need to escape? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;phony&quot;&gt;Phony&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fake, not genuine or real&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to the immersive environment, how does the nature and artificial aesthetic quality of the virtual space itself affect how the players react to it and each other? And, through the exploration of sound in virtual reality, will it be possible to explore the accoustic qualities of the space and how, for instance, virtual sound waves bounce off virtual surfaces?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be that I find a way to ‘record’ the event so that it can be replayed and experienced from a different perspective, viewed as a creative artefact ‘object’, that is experienced rather differently to the live event that caused it to come into existence. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Create a Game - Dog Walker Simulator</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Create a Game - Dog Walker Simulator" /><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;dog-walker-simulator&quot;&gt;Dog Walker Simulator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crystal is a dog-walker by profession. She has build a trusting client base over the past 5 years and, through the dogs, has made many friends - or at least that’s how she likes to see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this particular, unusual, day, the dogs seem to be behaving rather differently to the lovely calm creatures she has become used to. Fido, for some unfathomable reason, has decided to snap at Tia whenever she comes close. This is a problem, particularly as she is tethered to the lead next to Fido. Thankfully, the app on her phone, which shows the georgeous little pooches via glorious Augmented Reality, allows Crystal to move Tia to the other side of the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this now means that Rusty is next to Fido, and Rusty seems to have picked up a severe case of unwelcome, itchy, leaping, guests (flees). These begin jumping from Rusty onto Fido’s coat. Fido begins scratching, which causes the pack to swerve to the right! Luckily, the app allows Crystal to tug at the lead and bring Fido back into line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Benji has picked up the odor of a freshly-cooked pie that has been left on a windowsill to cool.  Benji lurches to the left, causing the leads to cross and twist and this trips up poor old Sukie. Whilst in the act of untwisting the leads, Crystal notices that Trixy has managed slip her collar, is running down the riverbank and is about to leap into the water after a family of ducks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of dogs that Crystal manages to bring back to their owners in the condition they were entrusted to her care decides whether she can continue another day in her chosen profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app makes use of stylised animated dogs in Augmented Reality, set in the real locale through coupling with Google API and Google Cloud Anchors. This simulates the experience of walking a bunch of very cute, very lively, but extremely distracted dogs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A day in the life of the dog-walker. You couldn’t make it up!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dog Walker Simulator</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/humble-beginnings-part3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 3" /><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/humble-beginnings-part3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/humble-beginnings-part3.html">&lt;p&gt;Considering past rapid ideation and prototyping ideas has thrown up another possibility. 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2019/02/25/week-three-appjam-2.html&quot;&gt;The Odd Word Out&lt;/a&gt; was a simple idea that became an MVP, my intention being to pick it up later for further development. At the time I wrote: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is significant potential for further development of the concept of arcade-style word games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time I had not thought of this in terms of Virtual Reality, but the potential is there for this to be a fun word game with an educational slant. It would not necessarily lose its arcade-style appeal, although it would gain a sophistication that would be interesting to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a 2D space I could have the words, maybe in the form of balls or other 3D objects, bouncing off walls, floors and ceilings within an immersive 3D space. It would the task of the player to knock out words by hurling related - or unrelated - words at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could, for instance, become a kind of shooting game where the principle of eliminating certain words remains, but the method is entirely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many options&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Considering past rapid ideation and prototyping ideas has thrown up another possibility. The Odd Word Out was a simple idea that became an MVP, my intention being to pick it up later for further development. At the time I wrote: -</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/03/humble-beginnings-part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 2" /><published>2020-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/03/humble-beginnings-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/03/humble-beginnings-part2.html">&lt;p&gt;I have found myself struggling somewhat attempting to define more clearly what it is I am hoping to create. Although, to some extent, I feel I am able to fall back on the cushion that is provided by the concept agile development, it has felt as though there is still not quite  enough hard material on whilch ideas can crystalise in order to really get going on the project. I’m not 100% certain that it is necessary, as I a feel capable of allowing the ideas to overcome any inertia and start to flow once underway. But it’s an uncomfortable feeling nonetheless. If I can begin with something in my sights, something that I can start to build a &lt;strong&gt;narrative&lt;/strong&gt; around, then I can start making headway with a sharper initial focus, a real sense of excitement and full of positive expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this kind of frustration can be seen as part of the process of ideation. Or, perhaps, I have been thinking about what it is that I &lt;strong&gt;ought&lt;/strong&gt; to make, rather than what I would &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; to make - it turns out that these concepts are actually not so far apart! However, with the emphasis on the latter, I feel there is greater justification and suddenly I have started feeling those tingles of excitement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how have my ideas moved forward? Firstly, I began to think about my background as a musician and sound artist and, in particular, one of the ambitions I identified near the start of the course - during the first assignment of &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/02/04/week-one-creative-assignment.html&quot;&gt;GAM710&lt;/a&gt; to be precise. In my conclusion I wrote: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The interactive nature of an online music collaboration or jamming concept is fascinatingly open to the potential of enhancement and the development of ideas beyond connecting and interacting in a purely audio environment. I would be interested in exploring the possibilities of connecting visually and immersively, into areas of &lt;strong&gt;virtual and augmented reality&lt;/strong&gt;. The potential for musicians to immerse themselves in a virtual environment in which they could play alongside each other could be extremely exciting. Facial recognition and ‘super-imposition’ technologies could potentially allow musicians to experience &lt;strong&gt;playing alongside anyone, or anything, in a place of their own choosing&lt;/strong&gt;, including with ‘celebrities’ or even fictitious cartoon creations of their own making or purchased from an online library of characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I almost immediately realised that this absolutely satisfies the main ambitions expressed so far on this module, which is to explore the use of Virtual Reality in the creation of a shared immersive space in which some kind of collaboration or interaction between individuals can happen, in an educational or purely creative setting. The potential is there for this to form the basis of a formally-structured game, as it is for laying the foundations for something far looser and more participant-driven, such as simply jamming!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;idea-1&quot;&gt;Idea 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, my first idea is to explore the creation of a shared immersive environment in which I can facilitate player collaboration in the creation of music, or at least, ‘musical’ sound. This will ideally entail the development of some form of game, which will ultimately be integral to the formal musical ‘structure’ that is created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;idea-2&quot;&gt;Idea 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am concerned about the lack of VR headsets at my disposal - I own just the one Oculus Quest. I would like to explore, as an alternative, the potential for one player to make use of a different platform, such as tablet or PC. If this proves to be too problematic, then I have a back-up idea, which is to create a kind of &lt;strong&gt;multi-track&lt;/strong&gt; recording device in VR. The idea would be to &lt;strong&gt;record&lt;/strong&gt; a single sound ‘track’ as it is created by the player - and maybe also the movements and actions of the player along with any other associated visual stimulae - and then to &lt;strong&gt;over-dub&lt;/strong&gt; this with another track, followed by another, then another…&lt;br /&gt;
Ultimately, a mutli-layered world of sound - and potentially visuals - could be created by a single individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel these ideas are sarting to come together. I need to decide if it’s worth starting with &lt;strong&gt;idea 1&lt;/strong&gt; and moving onto &lt;strong&gt;idea 2&lt;/strong&gt; if I am unable to manage the multiplayer aspect, or to simply chose &lt;strong&gt;idea 2&lt;/strong&gt; from the outset. The latter does not fully satisfy my original ambitions for collaboration between more than one individual but, of course, it could in time be made to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;idea-3&quot;&gt;Idea 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering past rapid ideation and prototyping ideas has thrown up another possibility. 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2019/02/25/week-three-appjam-2.html&quot;&gt;The Odd Word Out&lt;/a&gt; was a simple idea that became an MVP, my intention being to pick it up later for further development. At the time I wrote: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is significant potential for further development of the concept of arcade-style word games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time I had not thought of this in terms of Virtual Reality, but the potential is there for this to be a fun word game with an educational slant. It would not necessarily lose its arcade-style appeal, although it would gain a sophistication that would be interesting to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a 2D space I could have the words, maybe in the form of balls or other 3D objects, bouncing off walls, floors and ceilings within an immersive 3D space. It would the task of the player to knock out words by hurling related - or unrelated - words at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could, for instance, become a kind of shooting game where the principle of eliminating certain words remains, but the method is entirely different. There are many options.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have found myself struggling somewhat attempting to define more clearly what it is I am hoping to create. Although, to some extent, I feel I am able to fall back on the cushion that is provided by the concept agile development, it has felt as though there is still not quite enough hard material on whilch ideas can crystalise in order to really get going on the project. I’m not 100% certain that it is necessary, as I a feel capable of allowing the ideas to overcome any inertia and start to flow once underway. But it’s an uncomfortable feeling nonetheless. If I can begin with something in my sights, something that I can start to build a narrative around, then I can start making headway with a sharper initial focus, a real sense of excitement and full of positive expectations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings-part1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 1" /><published>2020-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings-part1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings-part1.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-germ-of-an-idea&quot;&gt;The germ of an idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My initial idea&lt;/strong&gt; stems from twin desires to create a collaborative, interactive, ‘multi-player’ space in Virtual Reality and to develop ways for educational or therapeutic (such as autistic spectrum disorder) activities to take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point will be to create a suitable immersive space to be ‘shared’ by student and teacher. I will explore the use of avatars as representations of the participants and will study this in comparison with a lack of visual human representation. Initially, the student will use the VR headset and the teacher will use a phone or tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will introduce a simple interactive concept based on question and response, or action and reaction. The teacher will ask something of the student and will provide a suitable reward if the response is satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have an interest in sound and music, I will approach this as part of an exploration of sound creation and manipulation within a virtual space. For this to happen, some kind of participant action will clearly be required as will both sonic and visual elements within the space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will enable me to begin studying the possibilities and effectiveness of immersive technologies in therapeutic and education settings. It will also allow me to experiment with visual and aural aesthetics and the inclusion of visual human interaction, all with the potential to gain insights into human response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;as-i-further-develop-my-idea&quot;&gt;As I further develop my idea…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I begin to think about how the narrative, along the lines of &lt;strong&gt;storyworld&lt;/strong&gt; rather than &lt;strong&gt;storyline&lt;/strong&gt;, can be more interesting. If this were to be more of a game rather than &lt;em&gt;simply&lt;/em&gt; responding to a set of given tasks. Perhaps this could be along the lines of a &lt;em&gt;spree&lt;/em&gt;, where the ‘student’ returns a series of &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; responses, only for this to fail as soon as an &lt;em&gt;incorrect&lt;/em&gt; response is given. Similar to a game of &lt;strong&gt;Simon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\simon-electronic-game.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simon Game&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, of course a very simple game - one of the reasons that &lt;em&gt;Simon&lt;/em&gt; appeals to me as a potential vehicle for therapeutic purposes. Anacdotally, and through experience, simple games can be used as a task-driven activity as a form of ‘paring’ exercise, encouraging, amongst other things, inter-personal communication, socialisation and concentration. Of course, there is research to be done to back my statement up, but this is an example of how I envisage a simple game activity that could potentially be used within an immersive therapeutic environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This style of simple interactive game could also form the basis around which the various complex and challenging aspects can be studied and built. For example, the intention to experiement with a multi-player setup with sound, lights, haptics and other sensory feedback. I also wish to look at aesthetics and what difference a well-designed (which is entirely subjective of course) environment can have compared to something considered to be less successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slightly anacdotally, my search for a VR version of Simon only unearthed what I initially thought must be an &lt;em&gt;Augmented Reality&lt;/em&gt; version of the game, requiring a Microft Hololens or something equally sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\simon-headset-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simon Game Box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\simon-headset-game2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simon headset&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in fact it turned out to be a simple piece of hardware that consists of coloured LEDs and motion detectors that respond to the close proximity of the player’s hand. It is interesting that the VR headset was clearly an inspiration and used for its perception as ‘cutting edge’ technology and an associated cudos that it almost certainly does not deserve. I am sure it would become both extremely tiring and annoying in a very short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, a true VR version of Simon does not appear to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;follow-this-link-for-the-next-installment-humble-beginnings-part-2&quot;&gt;Follow this link for the next installment: &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/03/humble-beginnings-part2.html&quot;&gt;Humble Beginnings &lt;strong&gt;Part 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The germ of an idea</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Two - Fictional Worlds &amp;amp; Game Mechanics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/01/week-two-fictional-worlds-and-game-mechanics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Two - Fictional Worlds &amp; Game Mechanics" /><published>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/01/week-two-fictional-worlds-and-game-mechanics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/01/week-two-fictional-worlds-and-game-mechanics.html">&lt;p&gt;A notion of fiction particularly relevant to Creative App Development: -
&lt;em&gt;“An imaginary thing or event, postulated for the purpose of argument or explantion”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User Stories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnas - fictional characters - research&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;speculative-design--design-fiction&quot;&gt;Speculative Design / Design Fiction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ficionalised Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtual Reality&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Neuromancer&lt;/em&gt; - Willilam Gibson, 1984&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consentual Halucinations. Or as facebook would have it: &lt;em&gt;Social VR&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this kind of fiction is about future technologies and the relationships we foster with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Speculative Anything”&lt;/em&gt; - (Doon &amp;amp; Mabby? (link TBC) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-linear, interactive fiction&lt;/strong&gt; - where the user makes choices and is not simply taken on a journey designed by the designer. Concept that has captured the imagination of game developers and interactive artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of my own work, it should be interesting to speculate on how the user interacts with my design and created environment, how their journey unfolds, how they may chose to engage and explore. Non-linear interaction - my users will make the choices, they have agency over their own journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take risks and experiment (this is how I like things!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;narrative-design&quot;&gt;Narrative Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There appears to be a difference between &lt;em&gt;Narrative&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Interaction&lt;/em&gt;
One is linear, a story and is authored
The other is non-linear, more like a conversation and is identifiable as providing input / user-choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-plot&quot;&gt;On Plot&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carefully crafted, designed. &lt;br /&gt;
Players altering a plot can ruin the plot / structure, with loss of narrative.&lt;br /&gt;
Players being forced into plot can result in loss of interactive strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a designer one can create a space in which the player acts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cannot directly control events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can directly control rules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a storyworld, not a storyline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The overaching narrative/goals/challenges can be defined&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also understood in similar ways are &lt;strong&gt;Embedded&lt;/strong&gt; (pre-generated/crafted) and &lt;strong&gt;Emergent&lt;/strong&gt; (arising from the rules of the system, created by the player) Narratives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branching Narrative (chose your own game books, roleplaying games)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linear “Interactive” Narrative (most video games, predetermined plot, FPS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sandbox, on the border, but non-linear. Highly interactive. Little is dicated. Emergent narrative. Can feel directionless (The Sims, Minecraft etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-initial-ideas-for-this-modules-project-can-be-seen-by-following-this-link&quot;&gt;My initial ideas for this module’s project can be seen &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings-part1.html&quot;&gt;by following &lt;strong&gt;this&lt;/strong&gt; link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A notion of fiction particularly relevant to Creative App Development: - “An imaginary thing or event, postulated for the purpose of argument or explantion” User Stories</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing the VR environment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/29/vr-environment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing the VR environment" /><published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/29/vr-environment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/29/vr-environment.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;it-is-becoming-evident-that-notions-of-environment-could-be-a-good-place-to-begin&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is becoming evident that notions of environment could be a good place to begin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am concerned with the immediate virtual space that the immersive experience participant finds themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience creating virtual reality prototypes for ShelterBox in the previous module has encouraged me to consider, in greater depth, the benefits or otherwise of the nature and qualities of the immersive environment. As the single most important aspect of the immersive experience in that it encompasses and affects all others, the created environment appears to be top of the list. Ultimately, I will be looking for ways of encouraging the participant to &lt;em&gt;hang around&lt;/em&gt;, so I will need to consider how and to what extent the nature of environment affects the overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some possible subjects for research and consideration could include: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The use of a familiar environment, such as using the model I created of the family home imported into Unity from Sketch-up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How would familiar environment or familiar objects affect reaction to the environment compared with those that are unfamiliar or custom-made?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How would personal welcome messages and familiar sounds affect the way the environment is received?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could I introduce the use of voice synthesis - perhaps this could be controlled by text input by a teacher/therapist/player?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How environment affects levels of relaxation, stimulation, engagement etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What makes a good therapeutic environment?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In what way is comfort affected by colour and colour schemes?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does the use of sound or music affect the environment and how does the type of music or quality of sound affect the participant’s disposition?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would something like a Zen environment be a suitable place to begin these experiments?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is becoming evident that notions of environment could be a good place to begin</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week One - Game Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/27/week-one-game-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week One - Game Design" /><published>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/27/week-one-game-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/27/week-one-game-design.html">&lt;p&gt;I would not describe myself as a ‘gamer’. I don’t really play games these days, but that’s not to say I do not appreciate the art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module appears to be designed to draw inspiration from games, if not encourage game design or development in itself. I find myself much more drawn to the topic than I would have thought at the start of the course, a year ago. Earlier journal posts, my course work, and during webinars and general conversation, it is fairly clear that my appreciation of the concept of games, in the widest and most loosely-formulated sense, in terms of design and development in relation to their purpose and the roles they can play within the wider sphere of app development, has swiftly become almost integral to my own direction of travel. That is not to say I expect or hope to become a game designer in the purest sense - this is for those who have devoted their lives to gaming and have developed an inate and sympathetic feel for games that maybe I once posessed but have long since left behind. However, games, or the ideas behind what makes a game, how games engage us and capture our attention, spark our imagination, attempt to free us from our more mundane sense of being and challenge us to improve ourselves, does intrigue me. I am interested in how game systems, strategies, rewards and hooks can instigate a drive to compete, progess, succeed and to overcome obstacles and prevail, and how this can be harnessed beyond the pure idea of gaming for the sake of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;peer-discussion&quot;&gt;Peer Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were asked to discuss our ‘favourie game’ - a wide topic, and one that could be taken in many directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is your favourite game and why? It could be anything from board games, party games, video games or even something that involves adding a layer of play on top of your everyday tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m struggling with this one a bit. I don’t really game (I love how this has become a verb) much, any more. I probably started to fry the gaming part of my brain when I was a young teen and then finally frazzled it in my early 30s. Saying that, I’m finding I’m starting to get back into games a little, partly due to  my 11 year old son and partly due to a kind of gentle road-to-Damascus series of rediscovery-renaissance experiences via this MA.  Starting to work in Virtual Reality is playing a significant part in this, as is the concept of gamification and the significance of games in education.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Then again, I’ve always loved a good game of chess.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Games, both of the computer or non-computer variety, have played their part at various stages in my life. Snakes and ladders, ludo, cluedo, monopoly, Escape From Colditz (https://tinyurl.com/qoa39kz (Links to an external site.)) etc. as a child, for example. I have particularly fond memories of the London Cabbie Game (https://tinyurl.com/ua2whqp (Links to an external site.)). Card games were an important part of hanging out in shared housing or as a student.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a young wide-eyed arcade gamer back in the 80s I loved nearly everything that had a 10p or 20p slot (my pocket money and that of my peers must have built this industry). I remember the early ping-pong games appearing in my local chippie.  Followed by Space Invaders,  Pacman, Scramble, Galaxians, Gorf, then platformers like Donkey Kong.  Defender was an unbelievably amazing, crazy game that was about as immersive as a 2D space shoot-em-all game could be back then. The sounds of these games are as memorable as the gameplay, and when I hear the noises now I can smell the arcades. As a proud owner of a BBC Micro Model B, I reserve a particularly special place in my heart for Elite (https://tinyurl.com/vf6s4z8 (Links to an external site.)). This was the most cutting edge game of its time and marks the beginning of a whole new genre of video/console games.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve always loved driving games, but only if they are realistic. Forget style over substance - it has to be authentic, like the real thing. Same for flying, shooting, being in space.  I think this is probably what I am beginning to feel the love for more than anything when it comes to modern gaming. Although I’ve not played this game much myself I’m beginning to get a fascination watching my son play Zelda, Breath Of The Wild.  He loves the freedom it gives him to explore and make his own way whilst feeling about as real as can be,  and it looks amazing!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am now getting excited about the possibilities of virtual, augmented and mixed reality - surely this is going to be huge and has the potential to take the concept of what a game is onto another level.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-brief-thoughts-on-the-module-outline&quot;&gt;In brief: thoughts on the module outline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of my early thinking about this project, I am scatterlogically finding these kind of thoughts bouncing around my head, as a result of what I would like to explore myself and the generally intriguing titles of the, as yet, unlocked weekly content to come. As the course content and requirements become known and, of course, the actual work I do takes form, these will no doubt change to greater or lesser degress and new ideas should form. As ever, it will be interesting to see how this progresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Game Design&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fictional Worlds &amp;amp; Game Mechanics&lt;/strong&gt;. Vital stuff for game creators. Very much looking forward to this as it’s new learning for me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suspension of Disbelief&lt;/strong&gt;. I presume this will be about making the impossible into reality or, as I touched up above, creating worlds that make demands on our imagination and pull us out of our ‘normal’ existence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colour Theory&lt;/strong&gt;. Something I missed out on at art college, but is clearly important in app development. I want my apps to look good as this can make such a difference. I’m sure something that looks good and feels good has an advantage over something that maybe more sophisticated. If user does not like being there, they will stay away. Web design has really developed this field in recent times.
It will be worth considering the importance of an app, or immersive environment or characters within it, looking aesthetically pleasing, in comparison to the importance of being functionally-enticing, useful, exciting, fun etc. Is being able to maniuplate your environment to your own ends more important than a slick-looking environment that is proviced to you from the outset?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concept Art&lt;/strong&gt;. I have spent time considering this, as an undergraduate and generally. I am interested to see how the topic is discussed in relation to our art as app developers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Character Design&lt;/strong&gt;. A new skill for me, and potentially an important one with regard to multi-player / interactive immersive experiences and ways of relating in the virtual world with my target audience, i.e. ASD. Character design versus downloadable professionally-created assets - which is suitable for what purpose?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound Design&lt;/strong&gt;. My bag in my world outside app development and something I’ve been looking forward to engaging with. I’m considering how sound and ‘musical’ sound can be embraced as a means for providing a level of immersion that goes beyond the visual, which is far more prevelant and understood, I think.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound Process&lt;/strong&gt;. Not sure what this is. Is this sound and the process of using it, or ‘sound’ as in ‘stable’, ‘safe’, ‘reliable’?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D Art&lt;/strong&gt;. Clearly an important subject when it comes to VR.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animation&lt;/strong&gt;. I have briefly dabbled with animation - 2D using javascript and javascript libraries and game engines,and 3D via Unity - and it is an area that I am looking forward to focusing on at little more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;first-thoughts-and-development-of-ideas&quot;&gt;First thoughts and development of ideas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtual reality, augmented reality, mixed reality&lt;/strong&gt;. All seem to hold the potential to explore and push the ‘evolution’ of games further along, including notions of what games are, how we understand games in terms of their function as human activity and expressions of human nature. I am interested in how aspects of gaming can potentially be captured and used as tools for learning, particularly when combined with the intensely immersive qualities of VR. With this in mind, the idea of shared virtual experience particularly interests me and I intend to explore some of the potential, if it exists, of ‘multi-player’, ‘chat-room’ or similar platforms to facilitate the building of ‘bonds of trust’ in order to gain the attention of the participant as ‘student’, with the aim of aiding the process of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As has been explained in earlier posts, I have a personal interest in ASD - Autism Spectrum Disorder - and ultimately I would like to take steps to discover if there is the potential for immersive VR to create environments where learning is made easier; or, at least, to create another place where learning can happen, perhaps taking on a different form from those that are more established. The intention is not to create environments that ‘simply’ replace those that are real, natural, unavoidable, in order to provide relief or respite for the participant - although this could be recognised as a noteworthy by-product - or to make life easier for those in close contact, such as family. Instead, I would like to explore whether, perhaps, the clarity of objects - visual, aural, interactive - and of the individuals respresented within these environments, can help to focus the attention of the student and engage them in such a way that action, feedback and reward - in whatever form this may take - are clear and precise to the participant, uncluttered and unaffected by distracting or distressing background ‘noise’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I do not have a formal practical or academic background as an &lt;em&gt;Educationalist&lt;/em&gt;, I am aware that there are questions that I may have that ultimately turn out to have been already discussed, answered or dismissed as irrelevant. However, perhaps some need to be raised again, albeit with a new slant due to the continual advancement of technology, along with the ever-changing nature of society’s response to it. Therefore, I am approaching this topic perhaps a little &lt;em&gt;wide-eyed&lt;/em&gt; and naive. However, the expectation that the GAM720 module is approached from an experimental perspective, backed up by appropriate and thorough research, should make for an interesting journey. I only hope I find some answers and open avenues for further exploration of these thoughts and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-player:&lt;/strong&gt; Looking at ways of more than one person joining in the VR experience. How can student-teacher interaction take place?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 1:&lt;/strong&gt; the student experiences the environment and the teacher remains outside of this, but is able to manipulate the environment in real-time?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 2:&lt;/strong&gt; the student and teacher to join each other in the envoronment with the potential of interacting with each other?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facial expressions:&lt;/strong&gt; can they be simulated within VR? This could be an important part of ASD thereutic research.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;physical interactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Can I move beyond the normal expected kind of user interactions with their environment, such as picking up and throwing objects, pressing buttons, pushing objects etc? I would like to experiment with turning and twisting, clapping, shaking etc. What happens if expected outcomes do not arise but are replaced by the unexpected, scrambling cause and effect? Could this be used to create ‘puzzle’ games? For example where clapping causes water to change colour or pushing a block causes a balloon to expand.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hand tracking:&lt;/strong&gt; recently this become available for the Oculus Quest with no extra hardware or software required.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sound:&lt;/strong&gt; used within immersive environments what effect can sound have on the participant? In what why does it affect how the partipant experiences the visual aspects of the space?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vocalisation:&lt;/strong&gt; How can the participant’s own voice be used to communicate and/or affect the environment. How can it be used in general communication. Maybe speech therapy could be considered as a possible outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;environment&quot;&gt;Environment&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environmental considerations can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/01/29/vr-environment.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;social-vr&quot;&gt;Social VR&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shall be researching &lt;strong&gt;social VR&lt;/strong&gt;. This will involve looking at how Occulus, in particular, are developing the concept of the &lt;strong&gt;Avatar&lt;/strong&gt; in creating a presence in the immersive environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online links I will be studying the following videos: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ATbqtZqoit8&quot;&gt;Bootstraping Social VR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X6XOwtcscnY&quot;&gt;Oculus Avatars: Maximizing Social Presence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HT0nOOZz6QE&quot;&gt;Oculus Connect 5 - Oculus Avatars: Maximizing Social Presence, Part II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86-tHA8F-zU&quot;&gt;Facebook VR Research: Photorealistic Face Tracked Avatars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I would not describe myself as a ‘gamer’. I don’t really play games these days, but that’s not to say I do not appreciate the art.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2020-01-25T16:08:02+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T16:08:02+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR&lt;/code&gt; is a four-digit number, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MONTH&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DAY&lt;/code&gt; are both two-digit numbers, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Eleven</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Eleven" /><published>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven.html">&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed putting together a disaster zone!
Adding force of a value and in a direction (Vector3) when rigidbody enters ‘wind zone’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added HUD display&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made this scene the first - witness the force, then back to base to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roshan - 11 year old has no problem with the mechanics.
Kirti - 47 year old non-gamer has some issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to use the controllers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when the active objects - e.g. table of objects - is not immediately in front of user?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Would a help be useful? - this could be a room where someone explains things. Not everyone has the Oculus First Steps. Could I make a button available which would put everything in front of the player - a comfort button/cushion?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrative / instructions not clear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If prep room activity not completed, should it be possible to still do the personal items collection?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When at airport - perhaps say ‘you didn’t complete the tasks, but here is your package anyway - well done for trying! Have a nice flight!!’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem is that not everyone has experienced VR. Gamers have an easier time of it, but those who do not have much gaming experience could struggle. How to make it easy? Comfortable?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Enjoyed putting together a disaster zone! Adding force of a value and in a direction (Vector3) when rigidbody enters ‘wind zone’.</summary></entry></feed>