<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-17T23:26:30+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dog Walker Simulator - The Interactive Novel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dog Walker Simulator - The Interactive Novel" /><published>2020-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-brief-create-an-interactive-novel&quot;&gt;The brief: create an interactive novel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Create an interactive novel using Ren’Py, loosely based on the game creation activity from Week 2. There must be at least three interactive moments within the novel.&lt;br /&gt;
In line with the previous activity, these decision points might be:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Choosing which character will save the day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Deciding how the character uses your app to save the day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Selecting an action to execute in battle.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ending the game, by choosing what the character will do once they have overcome the challenge, for example, do they go back to their normal life or choose to continue using their power for good or evil?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This activity is designed to encourage you to think outside the box and be creative with how you communicate a concept. There are no boundaries or constraints, apart from the minimum number of interactive moments in the novel. There are also no rights, wrongs or silly ideas. Do whatever feels right in regards to your main concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;renpy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renpy.org/&quot;&gt;Ren’Py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\ren-py-main.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ren’Py seems to be a simple way to produce interactive text (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autzones.com/din6000/textes/semaine09/Aarseth(1997).pdf&quot;&gt;Cybertext&lt;/a&gt;) which requires the reader/player to make choices along the way, causing the narrative to fork and head in directions that are the result of the decision that have been made. Its multi-platform nature and portability makes it particulary interesting due to the possibility of creating simple demos that are easily made available. Ren’Py scripts are simple text files that follow a simple syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fungus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assetstore.unity.com/packages/templates/systems/fungus-34184&quot;&gt;Fungus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\fungus-main.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A free asset for Unity, Fungus describes itself as being &lt;em&gt;great for making Visual Novel, Interactive Fiction, RPG, Point &amp;amp; Click &amp;amp; eLearning games&lt;/em&gt;.
It looks like an interesting option and, because it uses the Unity IDE, workflow and Asset Store, it could be very useful as I  increasingly make use of Unity for my projects. I believe it will also be relatively straight forward to turn the work done using Fungus into a ‘full’ Unity-based project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to trying out Fungus, but for this exercise I will be using Ren’Py, for it’s relatively simple workflow, small file size and ability to easily port to multiple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dog-walker-simulator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html#take2&quot;&gt;Dog Walker Simulator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My narrative will be based on my updated story idea which can be seen &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html#take2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive moments could be: -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The dogs have broken freen from Crystal’s grasp and are heading in different directions. What should be her response?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which dog, or dogs, to go after first?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when she or a dog is facing imminent danger?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when she has collected all the dogs she is able to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to outline interactive moments in such a linear fashion is not as simple as it first appears to be, as the very nature of interactive, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.articleworld.org/index.php/Ergodic_literature&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ergodic literature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is non-linear. For instance, point 3 may not even come to pass depending on decisions made at points 1 or 2. Therefore, the suggestions above cannot be seen as the definitive set of choices available.  Perhaps it would be better to draw up a more complex network of possibiliies. I have a feeling the alternative, of simply making a start creating the narrative and seeing where it leads, could lead to huge confusion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\interactive-novel-sketch1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding images is going to be difficult - will have to make them myself to do a proper job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python - discovering Python through Ren’Py. The use of variables became necessary. Looking at the documentaion indicates that the whole Python vocabulary will be important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vastly reduced the number of possible options by reducing number of dogs from 5 to 3 then to 2 - potential first branches reduced and therefore number of possible outcomes etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began by creating a sketch, on paper, of a vague possible plan of an interactive narrative. At this stage it started to become clear how complex a web this could become given even what appeared at first to be be a reasonable number of points of choice and potential forking onto difference paths - I found it difficult to use this plan verbatim, at least in large part due to this very fact. It made me realise just how linear programming itself can be. The complexities in both providing and following instructions that involve a large number of divergent strands do not seem to sit easily within such a format. It’s a little like trying to describe a three dimensional oject in two dimensions. Or, perhaps it is clearer how difficult this can be when you consider how hard it is to imagine a four dimensional world when viewed from our own perspective as fully paid up and assimilated members of one that is simply three dimensional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, branching is possible but fraught with difficulties avoiding spaghetti and repetition. I used variables to help, for instance, differenciating when revisiting a certain scenario that could have been approached from a number of possible situations, for example, rescuing Trixie after Rusty had been reunited with Crystal, or the same scene, i.e. rescuing Trixie, after Rusty had been taken away by the dog warden. Variables can also be used for maintaining states - I used one for keeping track of energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the complexities of building this interactive novel meant it was more time-intensive than I had imagined it would be - although this would clearly improve with experience. I also found that I had little time to spend searching for good quality and suitable assets, such as character and background images. To do this properly one would really have to make their own, but of course, this is a skill in itself. As it was, I picked images very quickly with little consideration for aethetic quality or cohesive design - doing so would have been unnecessary with regard to the limited intentions of the exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I considered creating my own cartoon-like images, but quickly realised it would take a very long time to do so. I got as far as a single outline sketch, but to turn this into a set of usable png files (which they would need to be in order to have transparent backgrounds) would be a project in its own right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\trixie-dog-sketch.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did use a music track that I created myself - &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/stephen-banbury/movement&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Movement (soundcloud)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - although clearly this was not created specifically for this project. Building a usable library of assets would make creating such an artefact much simpler and far quicker, as well as avoiding potential issues surrounding permissions and copyright. But as this would consume a huge amount of time it is certain that, at least, certain assets will always need to be acquired from suitable resources. The better quality assets are, of course, generally not free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do find it interesting that, awful though my selection of images are, they are still more engaging than none at all. After all, a sequential selection of visual images, even if the quality is questionable, make telling a story more immediate and engaging than textual or verbal forms alone. There is also a significant body of research looking at the use of music in film and TV, as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://rhythmcoglab.coursepress.yale.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/5/2014/10/Music-as-a-Source-of-Emotion-In-Film.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;source of emotional impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that plays its part in &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=YjZN-44Z8AcC&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PP11&amp;amp;dq=film+music&amp;amp;ots=0uDqu6CF7c&amp;amp;sig=LlmWuuKRq5v0hVDJSNLD9h1U48g#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=film%20music&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;setting a ‘tone’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video here demonstrates a number of different possible storylines, each dependent on the player’s choices. The differences here are fairly subtle but are resultant upon choices made earlier by the ‘reader’ who, through the effort required to move the story forward, in effect plays a part beyond simply its telling, but in its creation and, therefore, its manifestation into something real and unique in its own lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dog walker simulator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\dog-walker-simulator.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ren’Py, and other applications with similar aims, such as Fungus, certainly appear to be fairly popular - judging by the number of hits when searching the internet - suggesting they have a number of potential uses. As well as testing ideas for story-oriented or game-like apps, I can see the opportunity for creating interactive presentations that could be very useful for pitching or promoting ideas. It is predominantly for this reason that I am glad to have engaged with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The brief: create an interactive novel</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building The Multiplayer Environment | Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building The Multiplayer Environment | Part 2" /><published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part2.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-and-animating-a-player-character&quot;&gt;Building and animating a player character&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tutorial has a useful introduction to &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.photonengine.com/en-us/pun/v2/demos-and-tutorials/pun-basics-tutorial/player-prefab&quot;&gt;building and animating the player character(s)&lt;/a&gt;. This is not network-specific so comes as an unexpected but welcome addition, as character animation is something that I will need to look into sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The robot prefab is provided for demo/experimental purposes as part of the Photon PUN 2 asset download, as are the animations required to get him moving (running, swinging arms etc.). These require attaching to the robot GameObject along with a character controller and colliders etc. As they pre-exist, it is not necessary to create the animations themselves.  However, it is useful to see how they are used in the overall workings of an animated character. The tutorial provides help on setting up the character and setting it in motion. However, I am clear that I will need to learn in far more depth and to gain experience in creating and animating 3D objects such as this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running and jumping&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\robot-animation-3.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting that, as soon as my almost-twelve-year-old son came home from school and saw what I was doing, he was hooked! This is not entirely surprising; it &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like a game, after all, even if it is not a game (yet). But it is also the magic of making things happen on a screen of some description. This became clear when I came back after a break only to find him adding colour and ‘furniture’ (mainly blocks and a tree stump), and attempting to amend the scripts to allow the robot to jump over, walk on, bounce off them - in other words, &lt;em&gt;interact&lt;/em&gt; with them! Perhaps this is an expression of an innate need to engage with the imagined world; to create; to interfere. I do wonder, if it had looked less like the kind of ‘game’ he recognises, would he have been so interested in deconstructing my creation? &lt;strong&gt;This could be worth investigating.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, this led to my &lt;em&gt;getting involved&lt;/em&gt;, engaging with the playfulness of my son. I found that by playing with colliders and certain GameObject settings - such as the ‘slope’ options - we were able to get the robot to jump over the blocks and to ‘climb’ onto them. From that point, adding more items and encouraging the robot to interact with them, became an imperative, something we just had to do; it was a natural progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, this demonstrates how real-life actions, engagement with the creative process and experimentation, leads to more of the same; it sparks the imagination and encourages moving in new directions, into new territories. We began to imagine a ‘parkour’ type game where points could be scored for the most imaginative way in which an obstacle is hurdled, a wall bounced off, or a platform jumped from. The unavoidable fact is, though, that whatever this becomes, even if it never gets beyond what it is now, it is already more interesting to look at and engage with than it was before that youthful and unattached mind’s attention had been captured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running and jumping.. with style!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\robot-animation-5.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;camera-setup&quot;&gt;Camera Setup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just adding the CameraWork component to the robot GameObject and setting it slightly above him, completely changes the nature of the ‘game’ experience. Suddenly, as the controller, you are much more part of the experience, feeling more involved with what is happening. It feels more natural and less detatched than ‘watching’ from a distance, even if you are controlling the character’s fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Camera attached&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\robot-animation-6.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the &lt;strong&gt;robot character is not easy to control&lt;/strong&gt;, being limited in its ability to stop, turn without running forwards, only jump in a single, slightly ‘parkour’ style and it can only run at a certain speed. Of course, there is much more that can be done to improve things. However, this ‘demo’ does indicate how much more work would need to go into creating a more usable animated character that is enjoyable to engage and to play with.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Building and animating a player character</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building The Multiplayer Environment | Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building The Multiplayer Environment | Part 3" /><published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part3.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;stop&quot;&gt;STOP!!!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;breaking-news&quot;&gt;Breaking News&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shelterbox.org/&quot;&gt;ShelterBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; have asked if I’d be interested in continuing the work on the brief for &lt;em&gt;Conference Booth Games&lt;/em&gt; I undertook for them during the last module - &lt;strong&gt;GAM740: Live Brief Design and Development Project&lt;/strong&gt;. This would be to move the VR prototypes I created for ShelterBox into the production phase. In doing so, it has been agreed with ShelterBox that I am free to use the project as the vehicle for the experimentations and investigations that are encouraged as part of the GAM720 module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intention is for the product to be shown at &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.volunteerexpo.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Volunteer Expo 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;NEC Birmingham&lt;/strong&gt;. 
Unfortunately, this will mean my plans to experiemtn with multiplayer dynamics within my GAM720 project will need to be put on hold. The reason for this is that the Exhibition Centre is unlikely to provide WiFi of sufficient quality for multiplayer networking to take place. A practical solution appears beyond the constraints of the limited timeframe and resources available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will, however, continue to explore the possibilities of multiplayer and social VR, particularly with educational aims in mind, and I hope to incorporate this work in the future - possibly my final MA project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">STOP!!!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Three - Suspension Of Disbelief</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/10/week-three-suspension-of-disbelief.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Three - Suspension Of Disbelief" /><published>2020-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/10/week-three-suspension-of-disbelief</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/10/week-three-suspension-of-disbelief.html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part2.html&quot;&gt;Building The Multiplayer Environment - Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/12/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part3.html&quot;&gt;Building The Multiplayer Environment - Part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel.html&quot;&gt;Dog Walker Simulator - The Interactive Novel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Building The Multiplayer Environment - Part 2 Building The Multiplayer Environment - Part 3 Dog Walker Simulator - The Interactive Novel</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building The Multiplayer Environment | Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/09/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building The Multiplayer Environment | Part 1" /><published>2020-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/09/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/09/building-the-multiplayer-environment-part1.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;photon-pun-2--unity&quot;&gt;Photon PUN 2 &amp;amp; Unity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Photon PUN documentation, which appear to be as clear as I’d hoped, provides what looks to be a fairly straightforward &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.photonengine.com/en-us/pun/v2/demos-and-tutorials/pun-basics-tutorial/intro&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; towards creating a simple multiplayer enabled application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API documentation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc-api.photonengine.com/en/pun/v2/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;connections-and-joining-rooms&quot;&gt;Connections and joining rooms&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first piece of code, attached to an empty GameObject, is to connect to the Photon Cloud server and attempt to join a random room - if no room exists then one is created and that is joined. This was one of those rare magic moments, when it worked first time! Unity PlayerPrefs is used to strore the player’s entered user name across states, thus maintaining it for the next time the app is started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Tutorial, as is usually the case with kind of thing, is not specifically aimed at the kind of work I intend to do.  Instead, it appears to use a fairly generic game pattern - I’ve yet to penetrate deaply enough to truly be sure as to how generic - as a vehicle for introducing the core ideas and concepts behind Photon PUN 2. I have often found in these cases that it is generally useful to continue the course, if not to its completion, then at least some way in to it - or at least until it is felt that enough core concepts have been unearthed for work to begin with the confidence that anything new and unknown can be researched as and when it is required. The balancing trick is in assessing whether this point has been reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I created four scenes, each representing a room in which the players can enter. I used the convention whereby the name of the room follows the number of players that have joined, and so, as a new player joins, all the players move to the corresponding room. Conversely, as a player leaves, all players move to a room with 1 less player in its title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use is made of the PUN callbacks (exposed through &lt;strong&gt;MonoBehaviourPunCallbacks&lt;/strong&gt;, which extends the standard Unity MonoBehaviour class) to detect if players join or leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\pun-connect-2.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Photon PUN 2 &amp;amp; Unity</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Multiplayer research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/multiplayer-research-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiplayer research" /><published>2020-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/multiplayer-research%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/multiplayer-research-copy.html">&lt;p&gt;My wish to create events within a shared virtual space will require some method of inviting two or more individuals to participate within a single environment. There appear to be a number of options that I will need to research in order to better understand the potential differences, similarities, advantages and disadvantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;past-musings&quot;&gt;Past musings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having never made a multiplayer game I’m starting from a very low base. However, more than one of my ideas for a creative app during ideation for GAM730 - the co-creative project - included multiplayer settings. At the time, without undertaking any serious research, I considered using a Firebase &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/docs/firestore&quot;&gt;Firestore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; database as a central hub, to which multiple clients could connect. This appeared to offer the most important aspect of interconnectivity - a full-duplex connection that immediately pushes any changes made to the database, by any connected client app, out to all other connected client apps. Beyond this, I did not do much further investigating. As I am about to embark on a full scale research activity I will find out just how naive this thinking was. Or not, as the case may be. I’m sure it’s not going to be as simple as this, but the fundamentals of WebSocket-style connectivity and a central database must, surely, be a major part! I shall find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-no-particular-order-options-recommended-returned-as-search-results-and-other-discoveries-along-the-way&quot;&gt;In no particular order: options recommended, returned as search results, and other discoveries along the way&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity Networking: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.unity3d.com/hc/en-us/articles/360001252086-UNet-Deprecation-FAQ&quot;&gt;Depricated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;UNet, Unity’s legacy multiplayer solution, does not meet the needs of many multiplayer game creators. To reach the performance, scale, and security goals of Unity creators, we’ve reached the difficult decision that completely new technology is required, including lightweight and fast networking, and a dedicated game server model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.photonengine.com/en-US/PUN&quot;&gt;Photon PUN 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Photon is a real-time multiplayer game development framework that is fast, lean and flexible. Photon consists of a server and multiple client SDKs for major platforms - &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc-api.photonengine.com/en/pun/v2/&quot;&gt;Photon API documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The Photon Unity Networking library (PUN) immediately stands out due to its integration with Unity.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It supports peer-to-peer networking, rather than all messages needing to transmit via the host. This means PUN is pretty fast, accoring to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raywenderlich.com/1142814-introduction-to-multiplayer-games-with-unity-and-photon&quot;&gt;raywenderlich.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, when compared with, say, Unity’s own networking solution.
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\unity-photon-api-difference.png&quot; alt=&quot;Unity Transport Layer API&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PUN provides 20 Concurrent Users (CCU) for free, along with 8000 monthly activities and 500 messages per room, plus an option of $95 for three years, including 100 CCUs and 40K monthly activities. This is certainly interesting for small indie developers, who are certain to be on a budget.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It appears that tutorials and documentation are a strong point and there are a decent number of tutorial videos available on YouTube.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This immediately looks interesting as I do not want to spend much of the 9 weeks development time available (three sprints of 3 weeks each) setting up complex structures of my own, such as multiplayer server, database and websocket connections. The fact that this is free for low-level development, and reasonably-priced should I need to step up a level, also adds appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-is-photon-bolt-and-how-does-it-differ-to-photon-pun-2&quot;&gt;So what is &lt;strong&gt;Photon Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; and how does it differ to Photon PUN 2?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.photonengine.com/bolt&quot;&gt;Bolt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are game networking middleware. 
A comparison is provided &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.photonengine.com/en-us/pun/v2/reference/pun-vs-bolt&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic summary of difference: &lt;strong&gt;Host Client (Bolt) Vs. Dedicated Server (PUN)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;PUN&lt;/strong&gt;, if the Master Client (i.e. special client that acts in a similar way to a dedicated host) quits, another actor -if available- will become the new Master Client. And so on, until there are no more clients.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;Bolt&lt;/strong&gt;, on the other hand, the server is “static”; the “client” that starts up the game and choose to become the server, will stay as the server. If the host client (server) quits, none of the other clients will become a server (and all of them will be disconnected, of course.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bolt appears to be take more control away from the developer, which can be a time-saver. I’m leaning towards the greater control provided by PUN as I would like to gain a greater depth of understanding of the processes involved. In any case, I like to have more control over what I am doing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automatic compression is a bonus for Bolt, whereas the PUN developer may have to implement it themself. However, PUN sends data from client to other peers through the relay by default (without passing through the master-client). Conversely, Bolt &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; has to pass through the hosting machine, thus adding latency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/gcp/introducing-agones-open-source-multiplayer-dedicated-game-server-hosting-built-on-kubernetes&quot;&gt;Google Agones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open-source, multiplayer, dedicated game-server hosting built on Kubernetes. This is something I’d like to find out more about. In particular the fact that it uses Kubernetes, another technology I’ve had in my sights for some time, and it is Google, which is certainly not one of the smaller companies. The fact that it is still relatively early days perhaps makes it less appealing when I’m looking for something to get set up and running quickly and is supported by a large base of users and documentation. However, I’m sure it, or its successors, will have a big future in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heroiclabs.com/docs/&quot;&gt;Nakama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nakama is an open-source scalable server for building social and realtime apps and games.
Looks very interesting but maybe a bit heavyweight for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t spent an exhaustive amount of time researching theses options and I’m sure there are even more out there. The task is made more difficult because I am researching a subject I know little to nothing about and, therefore, I find myself not completely certain if the diffent products I am reading about exist for the same purpose or if the apparent subtle differences are, in fact, major ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Agones and Nakama look interesting, but I am uncertain if how they would be put into use. If I had more time then perhaps I’d look further into their potential, but for now, I feel they will demand too much of my time when I really want to get on with building something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photon PUN 2 and Photon Bolt are both interesting and, in comparison with the offerings from Google and Nakama, I find the quantity and clarity of documentation, tutorials and general discussion surrounding them to to be helpful to my understanding of their purpose. Pricing structure for both is the same. However, despite the apparent greater simplicity of Bolt over PUN, the latter is more appealing due to the greater control and potential for learning and acquiring a greater depth of understanding through its use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I shall begin delving deeper into the potential of &lt;strong&gt;Photon PUN 2&lt;/strong&gt; as a multiplayer server solution for my project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VRTK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with PUN?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.oculusvr.com/developer/discussion/76611/does-oculus-quest-support-photon-unity-networking&quot;&gt;Good news!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am researching about possibilities to make multi user experiences for the Quest and have been wondering if Photon would help?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;yes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/quintesse/PlayoVR&quot;&gt;PlayoVR, a VRTK-PUN-Voice Demo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My wish to create events within a shared virtual space will require some method of inviting two or more individuals to participate within a single environment. There appear to be a number of options that I will need to research in order to better understand the potential differences, similarities, advantages and disadvantages.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Multiplayer research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/multiplayer-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiplayer research" /><published>2020-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/multiplayer-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/multiplayer-research.html">&lt;p&gt;My wish to create events within a shared virtual space will require some method of inviting two or more individuals to participate within a single environment. There appear to be a number of options that I will need to research in order to better understand the potential differences, similarities, advantages and disadvantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;past-musings&quot;&gt;Past musings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having never made a multiplayer game I’m starting from a very low base. However, more than one of my ideas for a creative app during ideation for GAM730 - the co-creative project - included multiplayer settings. At the time, without undertaking any serious research, I considered using a Firebase &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/docs/firestore&quot;&gt;Firestore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; database as a central hub, to which multiple clients could connect. This appeared to offer the most important aspect of interconnectivity - a full-duplex connection that immediately pushes any changes made to the database, by any connected client app, out to all other connected client apps. Beyond this, I did not do much further investigating. As I am about to embark on a full scale research activity I will find out just how naive this thinking was. Or not, as the case may be. I’m sure it’s not going to be as simple as this, but the fundamentals of WebSocket-style connectivity and a central database must, surely, be a major part! I shall find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-no-particular-order-options-recommended-returned-as-search-results-and-other-discoveries-along-the-way&quot;&gt;In no particular order: options recommended, returned as search results, and other discoveries along the way&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity Networking: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.unity3d.com/hc/en-us/articles/360001252086-UNet-Deprecation-FAQ&quot;&gt;Depricated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;UNet, Unity’s legacy multiplayer solution, does not meet the needs of many multiplayer game creators. To reach the performance, scale, and security goals of Unity creators, we’ve reached the difficult decision that completely new technology is required, including lightweight and fast networking, and a dedicated game server model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.photonengine.com/en-US/PUN&quot;&gt;Photon PUN 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Photon is a real-time multiplayer game development framework that is fast, lean and flexible. Photon consists of a server and multiple client SDKs for major platforms - &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc-api.photonengine.com/en/pun/v2/&quot;&gt;Photon API documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The Photon Unity Networking library (PUN) immediately stands out due to its integration with Unity.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It supports peer-to-peer networking, rather than all messages needing to transmit via the host. This means PUN is pretty fast, accoring to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raywenderlich.com/1142814-introduction-to-multiplayer-games-with-unity-and-photon&quot;&gt;raywenderlich.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, when compared with, say, Unity’s own networking solution.
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\unity-photon-api-difference.png&quot; alt=&quot;Unity Transport Layer API&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PUN provides 20 Concurrent Users (CCU) for free, along with 8000 monthly activities and 500 messages per room, plus an option of $95 for three years, including 100 CCUs and 40K monthly activities. This is certainly interesting for small indie developers, who are certain to be on a budget.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It appears that tutorials and documentation are a strong point and there are a decent number of tutorial videos available on YouTube.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This immediately looks interesting as I do not want to spend much of the 9 weeks development time available (three sprints of 3 weeks each) setting up complex structures of my own, such as multiplayer server, database and websocket connections. The fact that this is free for low-level development, and reasonably-priced should I need to step up a level, also adds appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-is-photon-bolt-and-how-does-it-differ-to-photon-pun-2&quot;&gt;So what is &lt;strong&gt;Photon Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; and how does it differ to Photon PUN 2?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.photonengine.com/bolt&quot;&gt;Bolt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are game networking middleware. 
A comparison is provided &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.photonengine.com/en-us/pun/v2/reference/pun-vs-bolt&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic summary of difference: &lt;strong&gt;Host Client (Bolt) Vs. Dedicated Server (PUN)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;PUN&lt;/strong&gt;, if the Master Client (i.e. special client that acts in a similar way to a dedicated host) quits, another actor -if available- will become the new Master Client. And so on, until there are no more clients.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;Bolt&lt;/strong&gt;, on the other hand, the server is “static”; the “client” that starts up the game and choose to become the server, will stay as the server. If the host client (server) quits, none of the other clients will become a server (and all of them will be disconnected, of course.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bolt appears to be take more control away from the developer, which can be a time-saver. I’m leaning towards the greater control provided by PUN as I would like to gain a greater depth of understanding of the processes involved. In any case, I like to have more control over what I am doing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automatic compression is a bonus for Bolt, whereas the PUN developer may have to implement it themself. However, PUN sends data from client to other peers through the relay by default (without passing through the master-client). Conversely, Bolt &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; has to pass through the hosting machine, thus adding latency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/gcp/introducing-agones-open-source-multiplayer-dedicated-game-server-hosting-built-on-kubernetes&quot;&gt;Google Agones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open-source, multiplayer, dedicated game-server hosting built on Kubernetes. This is something I’d like to find out more about. In particular the fact that it uses Kubernetes, another technology I’ve had in my sights for some time, and it is Google, which is certainly not one of the smaller companies. The fact that it is still relatively early days perhaps makes it less appealing when I’m looking for something to get set up and running quickly and is supported by a large base of users and documentation. However, I’m sure it, or its successors, will have a big future in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heroiclabs.com/docs/&quot;&gt;Nakama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nakama is an open-source scalable server for building social and realtime apps and games.
Looks very interesting but maybe a bit heavyweight for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t spent an exhaustive amount of time researching theses options and I’m sure there are even more out there. The task is made more difficult because I am researching a subject I know little to nothing about and, therefore, I find myself not completely certain if the diffent products I am reading about exist for the same purpose or if the apparent subtle differences are, in fact, major ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Agones and Nakama look interesting, but I am uncertain if how they would be put into use. If I had more time then perhaps I’d look further into their potential, but for now, I feel they will demand too much of my time when I really want to get on with building something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photon PUN 2 and Photon Bolt are both interesting and, in comparison with the offerings from Google and Nakama, I find the quantity and clarity of documentation, tutorials and general discussion surrounding them to to be helpful to my understanding of their purpose. Pricing structure for both is the same. However, despite the apparent greater simplicity of Bolt over PUN, the latter is more appealing due to the greater control and potential for learning and acquiring a greater depth of understanding through its use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I shall begin delving deeper into the potential of &lt;strong&gt;Photon PUN 2&lt;/strong&gt; as a multiplayer server solution for my project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VRTK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with PUN?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.oculusvr.com/developer/discussion/76611/does-oculus-quest-support-photon-unity-networking&quot;&gt;Good news!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am researching about possibilities to make multi user experiences for the Quest and have been wondering if Photon would help?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;yes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/quintesse/PlayoVR&quot;&gt;PlayoVR, a VRTK-PUN-Voice Demo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My wish to create events within a shared virtual space will require some method of inviting two or more individuals to participate within a single environment. There appear to be a number of options that I will need to research in order to better understand the potential differences, similarities, advantages and disadvantages.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">poly.caco.phony</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/05/polycacophony.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="poly.caco.phony" /><published>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/05/polycacophony</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/05/polycacophony.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\nordic-designer-collaboration.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Musical collaboration&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;polyphony&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polyphony&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A musical texture created by multiple individual and independent parts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that I will be taking forward for this project is to use Virtual Reality in the creation of an immersive space in which two ‘players’ can join together to create sonic and visual effects and events, though physical actions and interactions. The results of such actions may be seen as ephemeral visual and aural moments that exist for a short time after an event is triggered. The space will be an environment in which the players can experiment and create through playful interactions with the space, the objects within it, and the players themselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cacophony&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cacophony&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A harsh, discordant, jarring, mixture of sounds&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, as the developer, this will be a vehicle to exlore, not only the technical problems, issues and solutions involved in creating such an event, but also to attempt to use freedom from the physical world in order to transend the nature of objects as we understand them, pushing the possibilities of how we can expect them to react, sonically and visually, as the result of actions directed upon them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to witness not only how participants interact with these stimuli within a shared space, but also how each interacts with the other. Will there be an attempt to create something collaboratively, in the mode of a ‘jam’, or will they find there is too much stimuli to comfortably handle, resulting in the need to escape? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;phony&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phony&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fake, not genuine or real&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to the immersive environment, how does the nature and aesthetic quality of the virtual space itself affect how the players react to it and to each other? And, through the exploration of sound in virtual reality, will it be possible to explore the accoustic qualities of the space and how, for instance, artificial sound waves bounce off virtual surfaces?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be that I find a way to ‘record’ the event so that it can be replayed and experienced from a different perspective, viewed as a creative artefact ‘object’, that is experienced rather differently to the live event that caused it to come into existence. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Create a Game - Dog Walker Simulator</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Create a Game - Dog Walker Simulator" /><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief&quot;&gt;Brief:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sometimes average people are called to extraordinary measures. It happens all the time in movies, books and on television. Innumerable action movies pit people against one another and push them past the point where the ‘common man or woman’ become quite uncommon: Erin Brockovich is a classic example of such a person. 
For this activity, your task is to select a common man or woman in a normal job in a fairly average world: there is nothing that might cause you to think twice about them. To test this, ask yourself ‘would I presently watch a movie that covered the last week in the life of this person?’, if the answer is yes, then the odds are you do not find them common at all. Think of a common but not specific person you meet in your everyday life: a grocery-store employee; construction worker; bus driver; or cab / taxi driver. Any profession that is common will do. 
Now, think of how you could build a game based on the character’s everyday life when it suddenly takes a dramatic turn. The situation changes suddenly and the person is forced to step up and go beyond what they thought was humanly possible. Luckily, they have your trusty app to give them extra superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverables:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A brief description of a common man or woman character (this could be based on some persona development).
Details of a realistic, inciting moment that makes the character uncommon. 
A non-digital game design, based on the character, that utilises your app as part of the gameplay to bestow superpowers upon the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested process:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Pick a common profession and a common man or woman. Create a persona for them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Determine what the inciting moment will be. It could be something like the death of a loved one and the desire for revenge (Max Payne) or as seemingly trivial as the race to fill seats and serve people at a restaurant (Diner Dash).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Determine a type of game to build. What kind of core dynamics would suit the character and how would they use your app to save the day?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Create a deliverable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Activity derived from: Brathwaite, B. and Schreiber, I. (n.d.). Challenges for Game Designers. (p.184)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dog-walker-simulator&quot;&gt;Dog Walker Simulator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crystal is a dog-walker by profession. She has build a trusting client base over the past 5 years and, through the dogs, has made many friends - or at least that’s how she likes to see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this particular, unusual, day, the dogs seem to be behaving rather differently to the lovely calm creatures she has become used to. Fido, for some unfathomable reason, has decided to snap at Tia whenever she comes close. This is a problem, particularly as she is tethered to the lead next to Fido. Thankfully, the app on her phone, which shows the georgeous little pooches via glorious Augmented Reality, allows Crystal to move Tia to the other side of the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this now means that Rusty is next to Fido, and Rusty seems to have picked up a severe case of unwelcome, itchy, leaping, guests (flees). These begin jumping from Rusty onto Fido’s coat. Fido begins scratching, which causes the pack to swerve to the right! Luckily, the app allows Crystal to tug at the lead and bring Fido back into line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Benji has picked up the odor of a freshly-cooked pie that has been left on a windowsill to cool.  Benji lurches to the left, causing the leads to cross and twist and this trips up poor old Sukie. Whilst in the act of untwisting the leads, Crystal notices that Trixy has managed slip her collar, is running down the riverbank and is about to leap into the water after a family of ducks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of dogs that Crystal manages to bring back to their owners in the condition they were entrusted to her care decides whether she can continue another day in her chosen profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app makes use of stylised animated dogs in Augmented Reality, set in the real locale through coupling with Google API and Google Cloud Anchors. This simulates the experience of walking a bunch of very cute, very lively, but extremely distracted dogs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A day in the life of the dog-walker. You couldn’t make it up!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;take2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dog-walker-simulator--take-2&quot;&gt;Dog Walker Simulator | Take 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m updating my idea to better fit the brief.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\beagle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beagle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crystal is out on one of her dog-walking excursions. She has five or six dogs each on a lead. As she begins to turn off the pavement alongside a busy road, a passing fire engine suddenly and unexpectedly turns on its very loud and piercing siren..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WEEE-OOOO-WEEE-OOOO…..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startled, the dogs yank themselves free and run off, leads attached, into the park in various different directions! OMG!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Momentarily panicking, Crystal does not know what she is going to do, and thoughts turn to how on earth she is going to explain this to the owners when she returns without their darling doggies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But.. she remembers that the dogs have GPS devices attached to their leads and she has an app on her phone so they can be tracked. How very forward-thinking of her!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She starts up the app and within 30 seconds all dogs have been located on a Google map. She immediately starts off in the direction of Rusty, who appears to be heading towards a dangerous looking dual carriageway. She decides she’ll come back for those that are more close-by as soon as Rusty is safe..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliverable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app will use geofencing, with fences located on randomly moving points. The player must find the virtual pooches, by locating the moving geofences, before they are lost for good or, worse, they meet a sticky end or they get caught by the dog-warden! The dog characters are represented using Anime-cartoon-style graphics and a checklist is provided to tick off the dogs as they are brought back to safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Woof’ if you think all the dogs can be found withing the time-limit!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Brief:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/humble-beginnings-part3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Humble beginnings | Ideation Part 3" /><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/humble-beginnings-part3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/04/humble-beginnings-part3.html">&lt;p&gt;Considering past rapid ideation and prototyping ideas has thrown up another possibility. 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2019/02/25/week-three-appjam-2.html&quot;&gt;The Odd Word Out&lt;/a&gt; was a simple idea that became an MVP, my intention being to pick it up later for further development. At the time I wrote: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is significant potential for further development of the concept of arcade-style word games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time I had not thought of this in terms of Virtual Reality, but the potential is there for this to be a fun word game with an educational slant. It would not necessarily lose its arcade-style appeal, although it would gain a sophistication that would be interesting to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a 2D space I could have the words, maybe in the form of balls or other 3D objects, bouncing off walls, floors and ceilings within an immersive 3D space. It would the task of the player to knock out words by hurling related - or unrelated - words at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or it could, for instance, become a kind of shooting game where the principle of eliminating certain words remains, but the method is entirely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many options&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Considering past rapid ideation and prototyping ideas has thrown up another possibility. The Odd Word Out was a simple idea that became an MVP, my intention being to pick it up later for further development. At the time I wrote: -</summary></entry></feed>