<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-25T16:48:47+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2020-01-25T16:08:02+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T16:08:02+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR&lt;/code&gt; is a four-digit number, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MONTH&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DAY&lt;/code&gt; are both two-digit numbers, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Eleven</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Eleven" /><published>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven.html">&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed putting together a disaster zone!
Adding force of a value and in a direction (Vector3) when rigidbody enters ‘wind zone’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added HUD display&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made this scene the first - witness the force, then back to base to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roshan - 11 year old has no problem with the mechanics.
Kirti - 47 year old non-gamer has some issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to use the controllers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when the active objects - e.g. table of objects - is not immediately in front of user?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Would a help be useful? - this could be a room where someone explains things. Not everyone has the Oculus First Steps. Could I make a button available which would put everything in front of the player - a comfort button/cushion?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrative / instructions not clear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If prep room activity not completed, should it be possible to still do the personal items collection?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When at airport - perhaps say ‘you didn’t complete the tasks, but here is your package anyway - well done for trying! Have a nice flight!!’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem is that not everyone has experienced VR. Gamers have an easier time of it, but those who do not have much gaming experience could struggle. How to make it easy? Comfortable?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Enjoyed putting together a disaster zone! Adding force of a value and in a direction (Vector3) when rigidbody enters ‘wind zone’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Ten</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/27/week-ten.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Ten" /><published>2019-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/27/week-ten</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/27/week-ten.html">&lt;p&gt;Week 10 -Finishing the main phase - happy with holding the prototype where it is.
Agreed with client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To spend the majority of the remaining time experimenting with other ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to experiment with force / forces
looked at Unity Terrain, but it seems this is a bit of a ‘fabrication’ - wind zones make grass and trees sway, but this it not quite what I’m interested in. I want to create a ‘real’ force on objects caused and affected by ‘wind’ force. I want it to make trees and cars fly through the air, waves crash on the coastline and walls to fall down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iCMhrKOuBZg&quot;&gt;Unity3d Creating Rigidbody Wind Zones&lt;/a&gt; will help.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Week 10 -Finishing the main phase - happy with holding the prototype where it is. Agreed with client.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Six - Intellectual Property Law</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/04/week-six-intellectual-property-law.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Six - Intellectual Property Law" /><published>2019-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/04/week-six-intellectual-property-law</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/04/week-six-intellectual-property-law.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sprint-retrospective&quot;&gt;Sprint Retrospective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What went well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What went wrong&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The key challenges / obstacles to be overcome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21/11/2019
There has been lots and lots of experimentation with movement. Building a teleporation system. How to get it to work in a way that is usable and intuative. Is it required at all? Can we combine it with joystick movement? Should we use joystick alone? If so, should we reduce the size of the world? Can we stop orientation making it extra confusing - would like to just have head pointing the same way no matter where it is oriented before, during or after teleportation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can spend too long on these issues. Even though it is clearly sometimes better to put it aside for now and come back to it later, to allow faster prototyping, it is often difficult to let go! A discipline that needs working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Focusing&lt;/em&gt; on specific areas - set goals that are targeted and clearly defined. I’ve discovered the importance of this. This is where sprint becomes important, and using the kanban board efficiently and precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My client is happy to see what I come up with. But because of this I need to be clearer and more targeted in my approach - it’s up to me to be this way. If not, if too loose and open to meandering, how does one assess one’s direction of travel? Goals need to be set in order to know how to gaugue progress and ensure you are on track. They also mean that the client is able to come on the journey with you and see where it all is leading. It provides them the oportunity to make suggestions and requrests from an informed position, rather than just seeing where you end up and then, maybe too late, making judgement calls on the results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Sprint Retrospective</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Five - Business Models</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/21/week-five-business-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Five - Business Models" /><published>2019-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/21/week-five-business-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/21/week-five-business-models.html">&lt;p&gt;Leon Brown - a few different business models for the creative app developer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software Development as a Service (SDaaS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software as a Product (SaaP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software as a Service (SaaS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SDaaS - monetisation of your skills, trading your time for developing software. 
Low risk. Minimal cost. Flexible (your time, you decide).
Precarious. No guarantees. Low profic margins. Competition - always someone who will do it cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SaaP - developer builds the product and reaps the rewards. Create a team of experts - product managers, graphic designers, front/back-end developers, marketers etc..
Control of vision. Freedom, flexibility, potential for profit.
Cost - heavier seeding financially. Time waiting for a return. Risk. Failure = debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\product-lifecycle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Product Lifecycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SaaS - monetise the output of software rather than the software itself, through monthly subscriptions or yearly payments etc.
Pros and cons similar to SaaP, plus :
Pros - the potential for more diverse income streams, responding to feedback, continuous income
Cons - upkeep costs, duty of care to users - boring details such as payment methods, data storage, authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canvanizer&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://canvanizer.com/&quot;&gt;Canvanizer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Model Canvas Components&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\bus-model-canvas-components.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Business Model Canvas Components&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-will-be-my-preferred-business-model&quot;&gt;What will be my preferred business model?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve been building software for a while now and it is my day-job. I don’t really see myself continuing in this vein for much longer. Being a ‘code-monkey’ (any perceived slighting of the trade is not indentional) and continuualy learning new languages, platforms, techniques etc. whilst constantly striving to be close to the top of your profession, is certainly an interesting and stimulating activity. But as a be all and end all, I feel I would not / do not gain the pure satisfaction from this career as I once would have / did. To earn as much as I feel I need to as I and my young family gets older would add to this particular pressure. So, SDaaS is not my future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saap and SaaS are more interesting to me. Both have attractions. I think it depends on the type of product envisaged as much as what kind of model you would prefer to follow. It seems many products that would once have been part of the SaaP domain have moved into the SaaS domain. So there is some burring here. Perhaps SaaS is gaining a greater share of the market for a good reason. It is probably the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-prototype&quot;&gt;First prototype&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of Sprint 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past two weeks I have been rapidly building my first prototype. I am fairly close to a MVP, one which I will be happy to show to my client for the purpose of discussion and feedback in order to progress to another level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototype has so far been built upon the original idea, which came from early discussions with my client; that is, from what I have understood of their requirements, loose and free though they are. This freedom has, in fact, been excellent for this process, allowing my imagination the space to explore with the almost certain knowledge that what I come up with will be seriously considered as a foundation for building something more rounded, solid, developed. I really am very much looking forward to showing my progress thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How is my experience going to inform my proposal and business model?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Leon Brown - a few different business models for the creative app developer:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Four - Client Contracts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/14/week-four-client-contracts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Four - Client Contracts" /><published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/14/week-four-client-contracts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/14/week-four-client-contracts.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\emergency-control-centre-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Crisis Control Centre 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\emergency-control-centre-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Crisis Control Centre 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/cross-platform/unity-scripting-upgrade?view=vs-2019#targetText=NuGet%20is%20the%20package%20manager,are%20regenerated%2C%20undoing%20necessary%20configurations&quot;&gt;Adding NuGet packages in Unity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;client-contracts&quot;&gt;Client Contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having had little experience of this, the course material provides useful guidance for how to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LO1 - Explain why it is important to use client contracts.
LO2 - Describe the structure of a client contract.
LO3 - Develop a client contract appropriate to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful resources include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freelancersunion.org&quot;&gt;The Freelancers Union&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/076116488X/ref=ox_sc_act_title_1?smid=A3P5ROKL5A1OLE&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;The Freelancer’s Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clientsfromhell.net&quot;&gt;Clients from Hell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an article for shopify, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shopify.co.uk/partners/guides/grow-vol-1/how-to-write-a-contract&quot;&gt;Ryan Foster explains&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Keeping the contract short, focused and easy to understand helps reduce friction,
allowing you to start the project quicker (and get your deposit invoice paid sooner!).
Without a contract, your client may not clearly understand what they are paying for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps avoid Feature Creep and other misunderstandings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defence mechanism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who owns the work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid changes that are unreasonable halfway through project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prices and hours need to be sorted at the start&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A larger reputable company may have their own contract/agreement they want you to sign. If this is the case consider using this document as your own agreement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide your own agreement to smaller clients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are unsure they will pay, ask for an upfront deposit (make sure it it mentioned in the signed document)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some advisors would suggest &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; asking for an upfront deposit, no matter who the client is, unless you feel it is an important and valuable client and it may jeopordise getting the work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be careful what you sign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get an independent third party to check it if you are unsure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is easy to let your enthusiasm for the client and the brief get the best of you but keeping
your feet on the ground and taking your time to dot the i’s and cross the t’s will insure that
both your and the client’s expectations align and there will be no major misunderstanding
further down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;example-structure&quot;&gt;Example structure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The company details (for both parties)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A statement of intent (could be subject to change over the course of the project)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scope and deliverables
  The details of what is going to be developed. This is a chance for you to constrain the project
  and avoid feature creep. Concentrate on specifying the finer details such as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What platforms will be targeted?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How much content will be produced?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What formats will be used?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What performance benchmarks will be set?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What is the process of review?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revisions and Alterations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;important that you protect yourself from a never ending cycle of alterations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;maybe specify the maximum allowance of alterations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;opportunity to apply a fee once the maximum has been passed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;gives the client the freedom to make changes beyond the scope of the original contract but they will do it at a cost and not for free&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadlines &amp;amp; Approvals
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when should the work be completed and are there any consequences to missing deadlines?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;how the work will be broken down and what criteria will it be measured against for completion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who is the point of contact for agreeing the completion at each point in the development process (named in the contract)?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Matters
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How much will the work cost?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Are you charging by the hour or costing for the whole job?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Always ask for a deposit, usually 10 - 30%.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Termination
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sometimes things go wrong&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;allows you set the terms for termination that are balanced&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is shared but you do not end up fully out of pocket.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;important that the contract stipulates who owns the work before and after the project is complete&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signatures
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;making the contract binding&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;contract-generators&quot;&gt;Contract Generators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://gist.github.com/malarkey/4031110&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://docontract.com/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.freelancersunion.org/contract/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;non-disclosure-agreement-nda&quot;&gt;Non-disclosure Agreement (NDA)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both parties to promise not to release information about the invention before it comes to
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-disclosure-agreements&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Templates&lt;/em&gt; are good for getting started but It is important that you invest time
creating a contract that is unique to your business needs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are concerned that your contract is not appropriate to your needs then always get a second opinion from a
professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.sitepoint.com/5-critical-contracts-for-mobile-app-developers/
http://99u.com/articles/21927/dont-get-screwed-the-contract-provisions-every-creative-needs-to-know
http://www.hongkiat.com/blog/freelance-contract-clauses/
https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2009/10/freelance-contracts-dos-and-donts/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Three - Estimation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/07/week-three-estimation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Three - Estimation" /><published>2019-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/07/week-three-estimation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/07/week-three-estimation.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;chosen-brief&quot;&gt;Chosen Brief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light a firework… I have chosen a brief!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the … drum roll….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shelter Box &lt;em&gt;Conference Booth Games&lt;/em&gt; Project!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having had two very constructive conversations with both potential clients, the main thing that swung it was the requirement of the Cornwall NHS Trust &lt;em&gt;Sowenna Sensory Room&lt;/em&gt; project to use their equipement, which is in Cornwall, wareas I am 6 hours away in Cardiff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consideration was that the product should be deliverable in a ‘finished’ state in March. This neither sits easily within the time frame available for the immediate project, nor for the one that is to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was a very positive conversation I had with the project leader and we both expressed interest in my involvement in work related to future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-a-proposal-for-the-shelter-box-project&quot;&gt;Writing a proposal for the Shelter Box project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began forming an idea for a prototype in my &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/10/05/week-two-envisioning.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;previous post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst I have further refined my ideas I don’t wish to put them down too early, to allow for an iterative, agile approach in which the idea can develop as it progresses. So for now I will put together a proposal that is little more than an outline and a statement of one possible goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prototype of a game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player responds to incoming information / news about disasters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Puts together a suitable Shelter Box from the available resources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assigns the box to a team who take it away&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As resources are depleated, the player will need to replenish them by ordering a fund-raising campaign or digging into existing reserves etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The intensity and speed of incoming disasters increases over time, increasing sence of jeapordy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game-play could be vary from simply grabbing resources from shelves, hangers, bags or hooks, to for example, floating around ready to grab as they pass.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A player can never win in this game, but can achieve successes and suffer failures, accumulating points along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;returning-to-envisioning-as-a-process&quot;&gt;Returning to Envisioning as a process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have put together the following: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through an engaging and enjoyable experience, using the emersive nature of a Virtual Reality environment, the product will inform the uninitiated of the core work undertaken by Shelter Box. User-interaction within a gamified experiencial environment, in which direct involvment is encouraged with the process of responding to crisis and emergency, will form the basis of a lasting and memorable experience, raising awareness and increasing the likelihood of potential involvment, at whatever level, with Shelter Box’s work in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backlog Creation / Epic&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yodiz.com/blog/what-is-epic-in-agile-methodology-definition-and-template-of-epic/&quot;&gt;see definition&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a virtual ‘control centre’ setting, the ‘player’ will be confronted with a number of disaster scenarios that have recently or are currently taking place. The object will be, through actions such as directing appropriate resources and effective actions, to respond effectively in order to provide relief ‘on the ground’ whilst, at the same time, avoiding the obstacles and hindrances that inevitably serve to frustrate the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product Roadmap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A roadmap outlining my releases will be in line with my sprints. I will work in three sprints of three weeks each. Suffice to say, sprint 1 begins at the start of week 4 and I intend to have a shippable product by the end of week 6. This will be a minimum viable product and will achieve the central goal already outlined - it will be playable, fun and informative, with the proviso that this is an agile process and things can, and probably will, change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, change will be welcomed and change will be embraced!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Chosen Brief</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Two - Envisioning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/05/week-two-envisioning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Two - Envisioning" /><published>2019-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/05/week-two-envisioning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/05/week-two-envisioning.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;scrum-envisioning--product-planning&quot;&gt;Scrum Envisioning / Product Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thorough research&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reducing the brief down into the most crucial elements&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Key phrases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identify similar products on the market&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Collate as much information as possible to inform ideation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The ideation stage should then begin to formulate the essence of an idea that has the potential to develop into a product&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Envisioning&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Formalise what you have so far into a document outlining the higher level product&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use this document as a form of proposal or agreement of the work to be carried out for the client&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Also used in scrum as a planning document to intiate product development&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product charter&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Created through completion of the envisioning process&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Will become the foundation for your proposal&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;struggling-with-a-decision&quot;&gt;Struggling with a decision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m struggling to make a decision, one that needs to be made very soon, as to which brief - &lt;a href=&quot;https://sowenna.cornwallft.nhs.uk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NHS Trust Sowenna Sensory Room&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shelterbox.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shelter Box Conference Booth Games&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - to take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Shelter Box&lt;/strong&gt; project is more loosely defined. Our initial conversation was interesting and the enthusiasm for the project was palpable, but there was little put forward in terms of vaguely firm ideas for what form the ‘conference booth games’ would take. This could be a positive or a negative thing, depending on how it is viewed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Sowenna&lt;/strong&gt; project is likely to be based around the idea of a beach environment. The young people invovled in the CAMHS project have put forward what they would like - one, or maybe two, have been completed or are close to completion, whilst the one remaining is the beach environment. It’s easy to start envisioning a product armed with this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shelter Box&lt;/strong&gt; have not stipulated any specific equipment must be used. They seem open to exploring my own suggestions, which would probably be for the Oculus Quest, seeing as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have purchased one and this is what I would like to use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is relatively inexpensive as no powerful computer is required and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is untethered and therefore not limited to specific spacial requirements in the same way as ‘standard’ headsets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sowenna&lt;/strong&gt; project stipulates what equiment is to be used. I do not yet know if I would be provided with their equiment to use for development as the main project lead has not yet been available to discuss this. But if I were not provided with this then development would be more difficult and if equipment were provided then I’d need to spend more time learning a different development path on an unfamiliar platform and technical setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both projects could potentially continue after this initial stage. In the case of the Sowenna project this could include the possibility of the research side of things. Maybe this could be something I could involve myself in regardless of whether or not I take on this particular brief. I sense from the Shelter Box project that this could be just the start. Potentially, I could involve myself in futher development of these ideas and help take them forward into different virual and real-life locations, such as going ‘on tour’ in festivals and exhibitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-thoughts-on-ideation&quot;&gt;Initial thoughts on ideation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- Sowenna -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lying on a beach is generally a calming experience. It’s easy to understand why it was chosen by the young people as one of their prefered ideas for a VR sensory environment. Using this as a starting point for developing ideas, I can envisage lying down watching clouds rolling by, birds flying overhead, birds soaring or holding their position against the breeze. A sun lamp could be used to to provide real heat to suplement the virtual sun; an electric fan could provide the breeze. Turning your head towards the horizon would bring the pulsating sea into view, with waves hitting and breaking on the shore. Drift wood would undulate on its surface. The mesmerizing, repetitive sound of the rolling waves would be relaxing and sleep-inducing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- Shelter Box -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a starting point, I can imagine a kind of game, where the ‘player’ is in a disaster control centre awaiting incoming reports of different kinds of disasters, as they happen. It would be necessary to quickly grab, from shelves and hooks, the equipment that would be required for the particular disaster - be it a hurricane causing villages to be destroyed, floods destroying crops and causing potential food shortages, or conflict causing mass displacement of people - and to put this equipment in a blue Shelter Box. The time scale for this would be unrealistic, but designed to put the player under pressure and add to the sense of jeopardy. There could be a budget to which the player would need to stay within, which would be used up by the resources being placed into the box. The budget could be periodically refreshed by the addition of funds via charitable support - perhaps this could be in the form of game-style ‘power-ups’, or via the requirement to periodically instigate a public information event to replenish funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;envisioning&quot;&gt;Envisioning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;product level planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capturing the essence of the product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a lightweight alternative to &lt;em&gt;product chartering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a fast process to allow us to &lt;em&gt;test assumptions, build tangible prototypes and iron out the finer details of the product&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;priorities tend to change over time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avoid &lt;em&gt;analysis paralysis&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. spending too much time defining, not enough actual building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenneth Rubens’ Essential Scrum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We don’t want to spend too much time or effort envisioning because we want to quickly advance past the guessing stage, where we think we know the needs of the customer and the potential solution, to the fast feedback stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to get closer and closer to product perfection through a continuous cycle of planning, implementation, testing and evaluation - i.e. the Agile process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial envisioning - just enough info to help define the first minimal release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rubin suggests,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Plan to Learn Fast and Pivot When necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output of the envisioning stage is commonly known as the product charter. This document should contain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The product vision, a simple summary statement that defines the project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Target Customer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key Benefits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purpose of the project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information about roles and responsibilities (if working in a team - but as an individual it will help manage client’s expectations by communicating what you agree to take on).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Scrum Envisioning / Product Planning</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Two - Early Client Contact</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/02/week-two-early-client-contact.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week  Two - Early Client Contact" /><published>2019-10-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/02/week-two-early-client-contact</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/02/week-two-early-client-contact.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I think I am going to chose one of the briefs put forward by the university.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there are one or two that cover my bases and I can then concentrate on honing my ideas to the brief, which has got to be a good skill to practice, has it not?
I could do it the other way around in order to develop my technical skills, i.e. I could decide what I want to learn and practice, technically, and put together a brief that fits, but I’m not sure that this would outweigh what I would learn if I were to ‘do it real’. 
There is also the greater potential to end up with a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; portfolio piece - one that will have been achieved for a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; client on a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; project. 
As a piece of work based on &lt;em&gt;Virtual Reality&lt;/em&gt;, this would be a refreshing grounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wish I was better on the phone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always think of what I would like to have said after the phone has been put down and I begin the process of remembering what it was I really wanted to know or to contribute to the conversation. It is made worse by the knowledge that this ain’t trivial! It’s important! I need to be able to come away from these dismembered meetings knowing that there is nothing left to add or to glean except for “is there any way we can do this even quicker, because that was one amazing get-together and I don’t know if we can wait much longer to get started!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t always anticipate everything that will be said and how to repond, but it’s worth putting in the time imagining these scenarios. I think, then, over time, with practice it will be possible to automatically get head into phone-mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughts and lists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I want to say? .. don’t forget don’t forget don’t forget!&lt;br /&gt;
.. put down thoughts and create lists. &lt;br /&gt;
Imagine what is likely to be discussed?&lt;br /&gt;
.. more thoughts and lists. &lt;br /&gt;
What will my responses be to these imagined scenarios?&lt;br /&gt;
.. thoughts and lists. &lt;br /&gt;
Lists and thoughts. &lt;br /&gt;
Thoughts and lists. &lt;br /&gt;
NEVER forget..&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I think I am going to chose one of the briefs put forward by the university.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week One - Considering The Briefs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/28/week-one-considering-the-briefs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week  One - Considering The Briefs" /><published>2019-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/09/28/week-one-considering-the-briefs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/28/week-one-considering-the-briefs.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;chosing-a-brief&quot;&gt;Chosing a brief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three potential briefs provided by the University that I am considering: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelter Box: Conference Booth Games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NHS Foundation Trust: Sowenna Sensory VR Environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tretherras School: Animal Farm KS4 Revision Guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also am considering putting together my own brief along with an identified client. More details of which I outline below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided that I will be using this module to develop skills in the area of Virtual Reality.
Over the course of the previous two modules I have come to the realisation that there are a number of areas of &lt;em&gt;App Development&lt;/em&gt; that I find interesting. Settling on one, or if more than one, a focused way of incorporating a small number, continues to be a challenge. However, it is &lt;strong&gt;Augmented/Mixed Reality&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Virtual Reality&lt;/strong&gt; that demandes my attention more than any other. As highlighted in my final post of &lt;strong&gt;GAM710&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/05/04/week-twelve-1-what-next.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What Next?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I have become fascinated in the potential for both &lt;strong&gt;gamification&lt;/strong&gt; and VR/AR to enhance the process of learning. I have also identified Autism as a condition whose needs, in terms of therapy and learning, could be explored through VR/AR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end I have purchased a VR headset - an Oculus Quest - and have begun studying and following tutorials in VR and the use of Unity to build 3-dimensional. I am keeping an open mind as to whether Unity or WebVR / WebXR is the most suitable way forward, but Untiy seems to be a good way in for me at this juncture, as it is the most intuative way to learn about something in which I currently have little to no experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter-box-conference-booth-games&quot;&gt;Shelter Box: Conference Booth Games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We go to the ends of the earth to reach the most remote communities that have been devastated by disaster. Our highly trained ShelterBox response teams then go the extra mile to find the people left most vulnerable after a disaster&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The aims of this brief is to generate ideas for technological solutions that can be deployed at public events to highlight the important work we do and generate discussions that raise public awareness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The challenge is to find a balance between entertainment and serious, thought provoking engagement. How can we create playful and challenging experiences that also convey a message and urgency for our cause?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The oportunity to involve myself in a project where VR can be the driving technology is exciting. Shelter Box’s brief specifically states they are interested in VR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no expectation in terms of equipment, but ShelterBox are interested in experimenting with immersive experiences such as AR, VR and mixed reality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the idea of exploring a game-style, or game influenced solution in order to inform and educate the public of their work, interests me greatly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nhs-foundation-trust-sowenna-sensory-vr-environment&quot;&gt;NHS Foundation Trust: Sowenna Sensory VR Environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Young people … will be offered a choice of guided mindfulness exercises with a member of staff or the use of the VR sensory environment as part of their treatment. They will be able to touch, feel, walk around or even lie down during their five minute long experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some apparently specific requirements in terms of technical setup, hardware and sofware, but it’s not clear if these are set in stone or simply being made available should they be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brief has clear alignments with my ideas for ASD, but I will need to make enquiries to establish requirements in more depth and for more specific details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tretherras-school-animal-farm-ks4-revision-guide&quot;&gt;Tretherras School: Animal Farm KS4 Revision Guide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gamification of study materials … students require the ability to memorise the functions of key characters; recite quotations off by heart; remember Orwell’s purpose for writing … need a facility that enables them to do low stakes quizzing to test their knowledge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The aim of this brief is to generate a technological solution that would enable students to test their knowledge on these aspects of the novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We currently have struggles to motivate primarily middle ability boys. How can we use technology to help them focus and develop their knowledge and memory skills?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The challenge is to find a balance between fun, engaging and educational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No mention specifically of VR/AR so I would need enquire about this. But the idea of gamification of an educational objective is interesting, finding a way to engage students who are struggling with traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three look interesting and to have their own points of interest. I intend writing to each of their points of contact in order to obtain further information before making a decision whether or not to offer my services to one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-my-own-brief&quot;&gt;Creating my own brief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having discussed with my module tutor, Dr Jamie White, the potential for devising my own brief in conjunction with a potential client, I am also exploring this possibility. This way would allow me to create a brief allowing me to more specifically identify and target a combination of subject matter I am interested in with skills I wish to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current thoughts on this are that I have an eight-year-old autistic son and a wife who works for the NHS. There is here, then, the possibility to develop a brief to create a VR app targeting an educational or theraputic need within the realm of autism. This option is becoming very attractive!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Chosing a brief</summary></entry></feed>