<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-18T22:21:12+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Starting The Game</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/game-starting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting The Game" /><published>2020-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/game-starting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/game-starting.html">&lt;p&gt;How to start and end the game? The player needs to be prepared and ready for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;starting-the-game&quot;&gt;Starting the game&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up spending much time on this and getting it right is not a simple thing.  I imagine it to be something that is helped hugely by experience in game design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The environment now resembles a theatre in some respects. There is a ‘stage’, where the action happens, a curtain of sorts that keeps all the initial preparation for the ‘performance’ from the audience’s view, and a futher curtain that I refer to as the ‘fire curtain’, again after the theatre. This final curtain came about as a means to hide what is in effect the means to get the game going. Initially I began the game with a spoken narrative welcoming the player and explaining the situation, before presenting them with a button to press to open the main curatin and start working on disaster deployment. However, I discovered that this was actually placing the player too far into the introduction, and really, it is they that needs to set the game in motion - hence the final ‘fire’ curtain, which only opens when the ‘play’ button has been pressed. It is at this point that the introductions begin, resulting in the user being offered the keyboard in order to enter their name (which will ulitmately be used to update the leaderboard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these curtain were a bit boring to watch, so I updated the fire curtain to an animation of the word &lt;em&gt;ShelterBox&lt;/em&gt; - perfectly satisfactory for the pupose of providing enough interest whilst explaining the game without providing too much of a distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering the player’s name allows the welcome to be personalised with a message on the backdrop. I may update this to become some form of &lt;strong&gt;placard or a gilded sign&lt;/strong&gt;, extending the personal touch and further engaging the player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All taken into concideration, this reasonably satisfactory, and should suffice for the purpose of this game in the shorter term, but I expect to make improvements at some point once the all-important gameplay is working well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How to start and end the game? The player needs to be prepared and ready for action.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Points Scoring</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/points-scoring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Points Scoring" /><published>2020-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/points-scoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/15/points-scoring.html">&lt;p&gt;Keep it simple to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then build complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially I am thinking of earning a standard small number of points for each item assigned to a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gain a larger number of points for completing a deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gain points with respective funds raised&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lose some points for dropping an item on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lose points for assigning to an incorrect scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lose points for assigning when you have already assigned the item to that scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lose points for going into the red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reset score to zero?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lose arbitrary number of points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gain arbitrary number of points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public enum ScoreType
{
    ResetScore = 0,
    LosePoints = 1,
    GainPoints = 2,
    ItemAssigned = 3,
    DeploymentCompleted = 4,
    FundsRaised = 5,
    ItemDropped = 6,
    IncorrectItemAssigned = 7,
    ItemAlreadyAssigned = 8,
    BalanceIntoRed = 9
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Keep it simple to start.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Giving The Game A Voice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/12/game-speech-and-narrative.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giving The Game A Voice" /><published>2020-04-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/12/game-speech-and-narrative</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/12/game-speech-and-narrative.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;synthesised-speech-used-throught-the-game&quot;&gt;Synthesised speech used throught the game&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speech is used in order to attempt to connect and bond the player with the game and with the game’s motives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text taken from my introduction, or ‘prologue’ to the game, will be used. The question is, do I use it all at once, at the start, or would it be better to distribute it throughout the game at poignant moments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Welcome. Thank you for volunteering. We have a critical situation. There are a number of disasters that require your urgent attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your willingness to help is much appreciated. We are currently experiencing extremely high levels of disruption to everyday lives on a global scale. Current pressure ratings are at dangerous levels. We are relying on your calm efficiency, pragmatism and intelligence to help bring us back to within calm and sustainable levels. Are you willing to engage?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These resources are precious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please assign them carefully to the disasters with which you are confronted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t forget: be cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Be careful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Diligent planning will help more people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Too much attention to a single cause can mean failure for so many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text to speech service I have been using provides a satisfying balance between realistic and synthesised, where the voice is noticably unreal but also pleasant, calming and soothing in a very human way. Although very different in tone, it encompasses some of the character I wanted to emulate that is present in the wonderfully recongnisable and now ubiquitous standard for artificial intelligence that is the voice of &lt;strong&gt;HAL 9000&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My failed attempts to find a suitably similar speech synthesiser did not actually last very long. I did not want to use the exact same voice - it would be a little too derivative my taste and too denotive of something that I am not trying to re-create. But it was the character that I wanted to harness. I want to keep the player aware of their relationship with the game, to continue to let them know they are part of something that is not an actual and genuine attempt at a pretence to pass itself off as real, and this may be emphasised by the slightly separate and other-worldly nature of the immersive environment. As Doug Brown … [citation - fourth wall breakage in The Suspension of Disbelief]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Synthesised speech used throught the game</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gameplay and The Suspension of Disbelief</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/gameplay-and-suspension-of-disbelief.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gameplay and The Suspension of Disbelief" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/gameplay-and-suspension-of-disbelief</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/gameplay-and-suspension-of-disbelief.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-making-the-game-more-like-a-game-makes-it-more-like-reality&quot;&gt;How making the game more like a game makes it more like reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;this-is-strange-isnt-it&quot;&gt;This is strange, isn’t it?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been striving to make my game more like a ‘proper’ game, knowing that this will aid the sense of immersion for the player. However, I wasn’t really ready for how much this really does happen! It doesn’t matter that the actions within the game - animations, sounds, responses to input and stimulii - could potentially be increasingly removed from what is real, in terms of actually real and expected within normal real-world physical situations and resulting from real-world physical interactions. The feeling of immersion increases as I increase the number of animations and game devices, as long as they adhere to a ‘seriousness’ and are not too frivolous in a way that could be viewed as self-indulgent. If the game believes it, then the player is asked to also believe it, and the player is all too happy to oblige.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we are so used to games in modern culture that these have been accepted into and as reality. Media such as film, TV, games etc, along with the increasing aborbsion into the mainstream of ways to interact with our world via artiface and interface, have formed a kind of new relationship with reality and, in fact, caused a playful ‘fourth wall’ to come into being - in order to be broken - between ourselves and our reality. Reality is boring. Let’s create an alternative one that distorts or enhances it. This is much more fun! The 20th Century was in many ways, the centure of drugs and alternaive ways of seeing, opening the ‘doors of perception’. It’s perfectly fitting and proper that we should feel comfortable immersing ourselves within a made up world, as long as the world itself can convince us that it is real. Even better if it adds value and it an improvement on what we are currently lumbered with!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How making the game more like a game makes it more like reality</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keyboard Data Input</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/keyboard-input.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keyboard Data Input" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/keyboard-input</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/keyboard-input.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;attempts-at-finding-a-way-to-input-player-credentials-in-vr&quot;&gt;Attempts at finding a way to input player credentials in VR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has proved to be not a simple as I’d expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard input methods using Unity are not so easy to customise. That’s not to say it can’t be done, but unless you are a very experienced and knowledgable Unity / VR developer, it does not appear as anything close to a straightforward process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible I have missed something that ought to be obvious, but missed it I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found some assets on the Unity App Store - the free options I could not get working. Again, it could be possible to work with these and perhaps I am being a little hasty in my dismissal of them, but I do not have a lot of time and, unless there is accompanying documentation or something comes up from a few Google searches or checking out YouTube tutorials, then my patience is stretched beyond breaking point. It’s then time to move on to something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One that looked interesting was VR Keyboard, which uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q_kUlVTyRag&quot;&gt;xylaphone-style mallets to hit the keys&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q_kUlVTyRag&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/Q_kUlVTyRag/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;VR Keys&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I could not get this to work in my Oculus Quest setup. But then I found VRKB which is very similar, is newer (July 2019), has no reviews, no feedback anywhere. But it costs $10 - not a huge amount of money, but what if it does not work - it’s money down the drain. But it does have &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.unity.com/threads/released-vrkb-virtual-reality-keyboard.735905/&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; an accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=90&amp;amp;v=J1dHujWH23s&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot;&gt;video on YouTube&lt;/a&gt; in which the develop demonstrates how easy it is to set up. The video has no likes, no dislikes and no comments, which is a concern, but it exists and that counts for something!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also found two other potential suiters in the asset store - $4.99 and $15 respectively. Like VRKB they do not specifically mention Oculus Quest, but I am tempted by them, in the order of cheapest first. They are more standard in their operation - the $4.99 one looks like it uses gazing predominantly, but has possibly been recently updated to use lazer pointing. But I do like the idea of those xylophone mallets… hmmm…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-aside-this-is-very-interesting&quot;&gt;An aside: this is very interesting&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not something for this project - far from it - but very interesting none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qFGweUpAs8I&quot;&gt;VR-OS: Keyboard and Mouse - Custom hardware and software implementation&lt;/a&gt;. I’m mentioning it purely for its fascination value - I would love to be in a position to play around with this kind of thing. It uses a physical setup, tracking hand movements as they interacting with a physical keyboard and trackable mouse, using this data in realtime in a VR environment. So there is no need to use a virtual keyboard/mouse or to remove the headset in order to use the physical objects. It’s fun and practical. However, as Augmented Reality grows in use and potential, this kind of thing should become an interesting footnote in the onward march of virtual technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went for VR UIKit. $35 including tax. More than just the keyboard - also includes other useful-looking UI snippets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it’s not as easy to set up as I’d hoped. But still a good learning curve continuation that will help in the long-haul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MGEWR4J6F4o&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need laser for this: https://developer.oculus.com/downloads/package/oculus-utilities-for-unity-5/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But where is it? There is no Laser Input Module, as demonstrated in the video!
Look like it has been depricated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Attempts at finding a way to input player credentials in VR</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Am I Doing? Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/02/what-am-i-doing-part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Am I Doing? Part 2" /><published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/02/what-am-i-doing-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/02/what-am-i-doing-part2.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;attempts-at-finding-a-way-to-make-this-game-compelling&quot;&gt;Attempts at finding a way to make this game compelling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;leader-board&quot;&gt;Leader board&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tapping into the competitive nature of (most) human beings, and the reason for the actual existence of (most) games (that’s a statement I will need to back up with some sound research!), it may be worth developing the &lt;em&gt;competitive&lt;/em&gt; side of the game. Introducing a scoring system and a subsequent &lt;em&gt;leader board&lt;/em&gt; could achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’d like to incorporate a multi-player aspect to this game at some point, this could be looked at from a number of perspectives. Competition between individuals playing individually, is one thing, but there could also be competition between individuals playing as a team. It may be that individuals get rewarded for being more successful than their co-player, but is could also be that individuals get rewarded for being more team-oriented. These are concepts I will further explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-to-do-when-a-disaster-scenario-has-been-fully-deployed&quot;&gt;What to do when a disaster scenario has been fully deployed?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replace with a new mission:&lt;/strong&gt; I have played with ideas around replacing a completed mission with a new one. This involved selecting a report from the list - i.e. the list that a random selection is taken from at the start of the game - and replacing the completed report.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Close down the screen:&lt;/strong&gt; with style! Screen spins round, shrinks and vanishes! Will need suitable sound effects for this. I imagine this being tied up with the points scoring system, whereby a completed mission is worth a large amount of points, to be added to the points scored by assigning resource objects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;wind-zone&quot;&gt;Wind zone&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An increasingly gusty wind zone to blow resources off course. I could use Unity’s ‘wind-zone’ object or, as I did in the &lt;em&gt;disaster scenario&lt;/em&gt; scene of my prototype, define a large collider that applies directional forces to objects that enter within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitKraken ‘Glo’ Kanban Board&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\gitkraken-glo-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GitKraken 'Glo' Kanban Board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;haptic-feedback&quot;&gt;Haptic feedback&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I want to include some tactile feedback for the user when picking up objects and touching buttons and screens etc., as usual I searched the internet for documentation, advice and tutorials. As is often the case, the Oculus documentation is limited and did not examine a real-world scenario. The instruction provided is to use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; static void OVRInput.SetControllerVibration(float frequency, float amplitude, Controller controllerMask)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.oculus.com/documentation/unity/unity-haptics/?locale=en_GB&quot;&gt;Oculus documentation: Unity Haptics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;so calling &amp;gt; OVRInput.SetControllerVibration(1, 1, OVRInput.Controller.RTouch); 
should do the trick. Except it is very uncontrollable. I want a short burst and this lasts for 2 seconds. This would mean I would have to contrive a a short burst using a coroutine in order to instigate a short delay before stopping the feedback (i.e. with zero values for frequency and amplitude). 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, as it often the case, further searching found better, more usable, solutions. In particular one from Valem (Valam is a very handy guy to have around, as I’ve mentioned elsewhere) provided a thoughtful and useful solution. His can either use a sound file to control the nuances of the haptic feedback or can take parameters that define the frequency, duration and strength in a much more controllable way when compared to Oculus’s own API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9KJqZBoc8m4&quot;&gt;Valem: How to make a VR game in Unity - Part 5 - Controller Vibration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images\haptic-valem-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The haptic parameter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Attempts at finding a way to make this game compelling</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Am I Doing? Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/27/what-am-i-doing-part1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Am I Doing? Part 1" /><published>2020-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/27/what-am-i-doing-part1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/27/what-am-i-doing-part1.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;attempts-at-finding-a-way-to-make-this-game-compelling&quot;&gt;Attempts at finding a way to make this game compelling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explore ideas I will, no doubt about it, find that some of my attempts to make this game compelling, simply fail. Others, hopefully, can be rescued and built upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource object time-out:&lt;/strong&gt; I have added a timer to the collectable resource objects, which begins count-down the moment an object is picked up. If the object is still being held when the counter reaches zero then object is destoyed and placed back in its box. The mechanic is in place, but how it is used is not defined just yet. Currently, the length of time available for the player to keep hold of the object before dispatching it to a disaster scenario reduces as the game progresses, but the potential is there for this to be used as an added complexity, perhaps adding an incentive to keep the budget levels high.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources cost money:&lt;/strong&gt; Each resource object has a price tag, and the availble budget is reduces by each resource deployment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funds can be raised:&lt;/strong&gt; A random fund-raising event is displayed on the computer screen next to the player and the player has the option to initiate one of these when the budget gets low. Currently this just sets the budget back to its initial value, but I will be working on the mechanic to add complexity. For instance, each event has an estimated potential funding return which can be used as a base for a psuedo random actual value. I also imagine the event to take some time before any funds are made available - after all, realistically time must be allowed for planning etc. and an event can only take place some time after it has been given the go-ahead. I am also thinking of giving a short window to select the event before it vanishes. It may be that the player has to wait with no funds before another event becomes available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Attempts at finding a way to make this game compelling</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 - The Lockdown</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/covid-19-lock-down.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 - The Lockdown" /><published>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/covid-19-lock-down</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/covid-19-lock-down.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-gives&quot;&gt;What gives?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we’re all on government-inforced lock-down. Generally, this is already having a significant effect on everyday life, but how will it effect my MA development work and studies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m working from home&lt;/strong&gt;. This in itself is not a huge issue - it’s something I’ve done regularly for many years, albeit not for every day of the week and for such a prolonged period is this is set to be. However, this is not working from home (WFH) under normal cicumstances due to the fact that…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schools are closed&lt;/strong&gt;. My elder, year-7, Key Stage 2 son is home from school and needs a certain amount of ‘assistance’ (or maybe coersion) with getting on with the limited quantity of available online schooling, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My younger son&lt;/strong&gt;, who is home-schooled on an ABA (Applied Behaviour Analysis) programme, &lt;strong&gt;finds himself with no tutor&lt;/strong&gt; - one is self-isolating whilst the other is.. well, staying home. He is unable to be left to his own devices and requires full intensive interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My lovely wife is also working from home&lt;/strong&gt;. Between us, we have quite a load. We will need to use some - hopefully not all- of our annual leave to keep son two’s education going. Unfortunately, how I can find time for my usual once-per-week study day is not certain. Today, it was impossible. It’s now nearly 8pm and I’m just getting going - unfortunately I’m further delayed by writing about these issues!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will the NEC Expo go ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; Apparently so, but it has been postponed to 7th-9th May 2021! That’s right.. &lt;strong&gt;2021!&lt;/strong&gt; So it doesn’t really feel like it is postponed but, rather, cancelled for this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will the 2020 Rotary Convention in Honolulu go ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; Nope - it’s been cancelled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I’m thinking I will continue to build the app as though my deadline for a complete working version has not changed. Hopefully there will be further events this year and, in any case, whatever happens, it will be ready ‘off-the-shelf’ should it be required. I feel sure it will be - it’s the ‘when’ that is uncertain right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-pivot-or-not-to-pivot-that-is-the-question&quot;&gt;To pivot, or not to pivot. That is the question.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I decide to take this tack, then I will be continuing to use this module as an extension of the last - GAM740 - which was all about working with a client in delivering a ‘product’ in response to a brief. I have been informed, of course, that this is absolutely fine with the university. However, what about all those Unity, Oculus, general VR and game development techniques that I’m still learning? I keep coming across new nuggets of game programming techniques or patterns that are new to me and I am itching to learn and put into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the one hand&lt;/strong&gt;, I have been absolutely fine putting these tempting morsels to one side for the time being in order to ensure that a usable product is created in time for the looming deadline. I’ll be able to come back to these, is the thinking. In fact, it’s great that I’m stock-piling empty boxes and, although I know they will eventually need filling, at least I have an idea of the tasks that lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the other hand&lt;/strong&gt;, this could now be a chance to start filling some of these boxes, whilst still aiming for a usable viable product. At the end of such a process, I will have increased my knowledge and ability to tackle problems in the future. However, this is set against the vagueness of the targetted final result in respect of the need to take a finished product off the peg, if required to do so, once this virus has been quashed and the world of expos and conventions is open once more for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the one hand&lt;/strong&gt;, I will be deciding to concentrate on game narrative and dynamics over game development techniques. For instance, how to progress a (the) game, make it interesting, consider issues of winning and losing - if this is actually necessary - or just seeing how far you can get as a player, with odds stacking up against you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the other&lt;/strong&gt;, I will be improving my programming skills in relation to hard game development techniques. For example, what’s a Lerp? How do Unity Vector3 transformations work, and why are they important (I know they are).  There’s an absolutely huge amount I do not know about, let alone how to make use of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these two seemingly separate identifiable areas for targeting my efforts and concentration do actually go hand-in-hand. I suppose it may be more productive to concentrate on the game itself, as in what it sets out to achieve, and how, and then to work on the techniques as they are required in order to achieve these aims, in a kind of &lt;strong&gt;form follows function&lt;/strong&gt; paradigm. The issue here is that I am not yet a master craftsman in this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But.. I will only really learn by responding to need. I therefore propose to avoid the temptation to pivot, but to continue to develop the game towards an ideal agreed between myself and ShelterBox.  In so doing, I will look to incorporate techniques that are new to me, if and wherever possible - I will not seek to take the easy path just because it is available to me. &lt;strong&gt;Where I see more can be gained in the long-term through a litte hard work and an embracing of an experimental attitude, informed from the constraints and perspective of the brief, this is a path I will take.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What gives?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting down to building the app</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/17/getting-down-to-building-the-app.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting down to building the app" /><published>2020-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/17/getting-down-to-building-the-app</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/17/getting-down-to-building-the-app.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;serious-business&quot;&gt;Serious business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototyping phase was in large part about taking on an air of whistfulness and experimenting without too much to worry about - after all, the worst that could happen would be that things go wrong, you blog about it, learn your lessons, make improvements and decisions, and continue to iterate towards a working prototype. Ultimately, while of course you want to make something great and hope for it to be accepted to be taken forward for further development, only you and your client (including stakeholders) will get to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now in a whole new ball-park. Now, I’m thinking, “Gulp”! After all, the NEC will be watching!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have begun easing myself back into developing the app. It’s still surprising how difficult it can be to get going after three months away from it. Remembering where I was, how it works… all stuff that seemed so close to my psyche that I was living it and dreaming it has now become almost alien code in some places. I’ve been at it for a few days (a few hours each day) now and it’s come back on the whole. There’s a lot of code I’ve had to do away with because I’m only working not on one of the three main prototype ideas, but I am keeping it in place for now as I may regret losing it. It’s safety first here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve eased myself back into the process by bringing in gentle improvements: aesthetically at first, such as increasing the size of the monitors, replacing the free asset treasure chests with self-made boxes. I then added the rudiments for a new gameplay feature - the reducing budget. Each resource now has an associated cost which is used to respectively recude the starting budget everytime a resource is deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then organised that, in the prototype, random pile of resource objects are thrown into the boxes with an ordered selection, organised per type into their own resource ‘bins’. By this point I’m getting comfortable with coding this app again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added video players to each monitor screen - but now I’m aware I need to create videos as the ShelterBox asset bank does not appear to contain any - I had though they had. I think I’ll be able to cobble some slide-based videos together using photos. Not ideal, but it will do if I don’t find anyinb better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These additions, though, only go to highlight that a &lt;strong&gt;narrative&lt;/strong&gt; needs to be created and implemented. What happens with this budget when I get to zero! This is a moment when the narrative has stopped allowing the player to sit back. Ideas that I had that were slightly vague and unfocused are now needing to focus and move from the ephemeral to something that is real, existing in an actual gamespace and achieving goals that are predefined. There is still plenty of experimentation, plenty of unknown territory. But now this is underpineed and, in many ways, resulting form the new position I and my creation have found themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… what does happen when the budget has been exhausted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;power-up-the-budget&quot;&gt;Power-up the budget&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could potentially entirely replace the countdown timer. As a gameplay device, the countdown is not necessarily a great tool - an artificial way to create pressure. It would maybe worth finding a playful way to disguise the timer element in a gameplay device that is less obvious or crude. This is worth researching, but it would seem better to build the jeopardy into the narrative itself. For example, if it is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Game Over&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; when budget reaches £0.00 then keeping the budget in the black is essential. If it becomes increasingly difficult to do so, then this is the defining characteristic of the game’s problem. If it is made to be extremely difficult to play beyond 5 minutes then this becomes, in effect, the timer in another form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some thoughts on gameplay: How could a power-up work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The budget runs down as you assign resources and it needs regular replenishment. There are a number of fund-raising activities to chose from - selected from a touch-screen next to the player.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Or selected from a panel of buttons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each time an object is picked up there is a short countdown in which time the player has to assign the resource, or else it vanishes. This time gradually reduces as the game progresses. Alternatively, the time reduces as the budget decreases. The trick would be make sure that replenishing the budget is not too easy, or gets harder as the game progresses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Throw something through a hoop or hole, or at a target to replenish the budget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phone rings intermittently and a voice offers new donations to boost budget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The control room is gradually ripped apart by an increasingly fierce hurracane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter I would love to play with if I have time. It would require incorporating one of my prototypes from GAM740 - the disaster scene with high winds picking up and throwing cars and park benches etc. Perhaps I could place the control room in this high wind zone and add colliders to the building’s walls, ceiling, furniture etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Serious business</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colour Scheme Design Experiments</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/29/colour-scheme-design-experiments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colour Scheme Design Experiments" /><published>2020-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/29/colour-scheme-design-experiments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/29/colour-scheme-design-experiments.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;colour-wheel&quot;&gt;Colour Wheel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A simple colour wheel created using pastels. Guache or acrylic paint will have done a better job.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I will update this with a more professional job shortly!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\colour-wheel-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;colour-wheel-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;colour-palettes-created-from-photographs&quot;&gt;Colour palettes created from photographs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task is to create our own palettes from our own images. As time is limited for me, I chose to use some of my favourite pictures from my travels in Central and South America some time back. The diverse habitats and colours to be found in Peru and Bolivia are stunningly diverse and have remained strong in my memory. I’m sure they will for a long time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to experiment with some of the online colour tools mentioned in my post on &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/19/colour-scheme-design-apps.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;colour tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I enjoyed the results, in terms of the number of colours that could be picked from to make a palette, produced by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colourlovers.com/photocopa&quot;&gt;ColourLovers Photocopa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by the makers of &lt;strong&gt;Copasa&lt;/strong&gt;. You do have to create an account - which is free - to be able to use this tool, but there are a number of benefits, such as being able to save your palettes and sharing with others in the &lt;strong&gt;ColourLover&lt;/strong&gt;’s online community of colour enthusiasts. It is possible to access the hexadecimal and RGB values for each colour - although it’s not as easy a task as it should be or is possible in some of the other apps. However, the ColourLovers site also includes a number of other useful-looking tools for a variety of colour work and image creating tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palettes extracted from photos taken on a trip in Central and South America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-1a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-5b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-5b&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-7&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-13&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-19&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a palette from a photo in Photocopa and adding it to Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\playing-with-palettes.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Colour Wheel</summary></entry></feed>