<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-03T00:18:41+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Week Two - Humble beginnings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Two - Humble beginnings" /><published>2020-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;forming-an-idea&quot;&gt;Forming an idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My initial idea&lt;/strong&gt; stems from twin desires to create a collaborative, interactive, ‘multi-player’ space in Virtual Reality and to develop ways for educational or therapeutic (such as autistic spectrum disorder) activities to take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point will be to create a suitable immersive space to be ‘shared’ by student and teacher. I will explore the use of avatars as representations of the participants and will study this in comparison with a lack of visual human representation. Initially, the student will use the VR headset and the teacher will use a phone or tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will introduce a simple interactive concept based on question and response, or action and reaction. The teacher will ask something of the student and will provide a suitable reward if the response is satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have an interest in sound and music, I will approach this as part of an exploration of sound creation and manipulation within a virtual space. For this to happen, some kind of participant action will clearly be required as will both sonic and visual elements within the space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will enable me to begin studying the possibilities and effectiveness of immersive technologies in therapeutic and education settings. It will also allow me to experiment with visual and aural aesthetics and the inclusion of visual human interaction, all with the potential to gain insights into human response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;as-i-further-develop-my-idea&quot;&gt;As I further develop my idea…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I begin to think about how the narrative, along the lines of &lt;strong&gt;storyworld&lt;/strong&gt; rather than &lt;strong&gt;storyline&lt;/strong&gt;, can be more interesting. If this were to be more of a game rather than &lt;em&gt;simply&lt;/em&gt; responding to a set of given tasks. Perhaps this can be along the lines of a &lt;em&gt;spree&lt;/em&gt;, where the ‘student’ returns a series of &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; responses, only for this to fail as soon as an &lt;em&gt;incorrect&lt;/em&gt; response is given. Similar to a game of &lt;strong&gt;Simon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\simon-electronic-game.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simon Game&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, of course a very simple game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My search for a VR version of Simon only unearthed what I initially thought must be an &lt;em&gt;Augmented Reality&lt;/em&gt; version of the game, requiring a Microft Hololens or something equally sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\simon-headset-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simon Game Box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\simon-headset-game2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simon headset&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in fact it turned out to be a simple piece of hardware that consists of coloured LEDs and motion detectors that respond to the close proximity of the player’s hand. It is interesting that the VR headset was clearly an inspiration in order make it appear to hvae a cudos that it probably does not deserve. I am certain it would become extremely tiring and annoying in a very short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, a true VR version of Simon does not appear to exist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Forming an idea</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Two - Fictional Worlds &amp;amp; Game Mechanics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/01/week-two-fictional-worlds-and-game-mechanics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Two - Fictional Worlds &amp; Game Mechanics" /><published>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/01/week-two-fictional-worlds-and-game-mechanics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/01/week-two-fictional-worlds-and-game-mechanics.html">&lt;p&gt;A notion of fiction particularly relevant to Creative App Development: -
&lt;em&gt;“An imaginary thing or event, postulated for the purpose of argument or explantion”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User Stories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personnas - fictional characters - research&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;speculative-design--design-fiction&quot;&gt;Speculative Design / Design Fiction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ficionalised Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtual Reality&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Neuromancer&lt;/em&gt; - Willilam Gibson, 1984&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consentual Halucinations. Or as facebook would have it: &lt;em&gt;Social VR&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this kind of fiction is about future technologies and the relationships we foster with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Speculative Anything”&lt;/em&gt; - (Doon &amp;amp; Mabby? (link TBC) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-linear, interactive fiction&lt;/strong&gt; - where the user makes choices and is not simply taken on a journey designed by the designer. Concept that has captured the imagination of game developers and interactive artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of my own work, it should be interesting to speculate on how the user interacts with my design and created environment, how their journey unfolds, how they may chose to engage and explore. Non-linear interaction - my users will make the choices, they have agency over their own journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take risks and experiment (this is how I like things!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;narrative-design&quot;&gt;Narrative Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There appears to be a difference between &lt;em&gt;Narrative&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Interaction&lt;/em&gt;
One is linear, a story and is authored
The other is non-linear, more like a conversation and is identifiable as providing input / user-choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-plot&quot;&gt;On Plot&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carefully crafted, designed. &lt;br /&gt;
Players altering a plot can ruin the plot / structure, with loss of narrative.&lt;br /&gt;
Players being forced into plot can result in loss of interactive strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a designer one can create a space in which the player acts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cannot directly control events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can directly control rules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a storyworld, not a storyline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The overaching narrative/goals/challenges can be defined&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-initial-idea-for-this-modules-project-can-be-seen-here&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/02/humble-beginnings.html&quot;&gt;My initial idea for this module’s project can be seen here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A notion of fiction particularly relevant to Creative App Development: - “An imaginary thing or event, postulated for the purpose of argument or explantion” User Stories</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing the VR environment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/29/vr-environment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing the VR environment" /><published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/29/vr-environment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/29/vr-environment.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;it-is-becoming-evident-that-notions-of-environment-could-be-a-good-place-to-begin&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is becoming evident that notions of environment could be a good place to begin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am concerned with the immediate virtual space that the immersive experience participant finds themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience creating virtual reality prototypes for ShelterBox in the previous module has encouraged me to consider, in greater depth, the benefits or otherwise of the nature and qualities of the immersive environment. As the single most important aspect of the immersive experience in that it encompasses and affects all others, the created environment appears to be top of the list. Ultimately, I will be looking for ways of encouraging the participant to &lt;em&gt;hang around&lt;/em&gt;, so I will need to consider how and to what extent the nature of environment affects the overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some possible subjects for research and consideration could include: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The use of a familiar environment, such as using the model I created of the family home imported into Unity from Sketch-up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How would familiar environment or familiar objects affect reaction to the environment compared with those that are unfamiliar or custom-made?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How would personal welcome messages and familiar sounds affect the way the environment is received?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could I introduce the use of voice synthesis - perhaps this could be controlled by text input by a teacher/therapist/player?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How environment affects levels of relaxation, stimulation, engagement etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What makes a good therapeutic environment?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In what way is comfort affected by colour and colour schemes?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does the use of sound or music affect the environment and how does the type of music or quality of sound affect the participant’s disposition?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would something like a Zen environment be a suitable place to begin these experiments?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is becoming evident that notions of environment could be a good place to begin</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week One - Game Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/27/week-one-game-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week One - Game Design" /><published>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/27/week-one-game-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/27/week-one-game-design.html">&lt;p&gt;I would not describe myself as a ‘gamer’. I don’t really play games these days, but that’s not to say I do not appreciate the art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module appears to be designed to draw inspiration from games, if not encourage game design or development in itself. I find myself much more drawn to the topic than I would have thought at the start of the course, a year ago. Earlier journal posts, my course work, and during webinars and general conversation, it is fairly clear that my appreciation of the concept of games, in the widest and most loosely-formulated sense, in terms of design and development in relation to their purpose and the roles they can play within the wider sphere of app development, has swiftly become almost integral to my own direction of travel. That is not to say I expect or hope to become a game designer in the purest sense - this is for those who have devoted their lives to gaming and have developed an inate and sympathetic feel for games that maybe I once posessed but have long since left behind. However, games, or the ideas behind what makes a game, how games engage us and capture our attention, spark our imagination, attempt to free us from our more mundane sense of being and challenge us to improve ourselves, does intrigue me. I am interested in how game systems, strategies, rewards and hooks can instigate a drive to compete, progess, succeed and to overcome obstacles and prevail, and how this can be harnessed beyond the pure idea of gaming for the sake of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;peer-discussion&quot;&gt;Peer Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were asked to discuss our ‘favourie game’ - a wide topic, and one that could be taken in many directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is your favourite game and why? It could be anything from board games, party games, video games or even something that involves adding a layer of play on top of your everyday tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m struggling with this one a bit. I don’t really game (I love how this has become a verb) much, any more. I probably started to fry the gaming part of my brain when I was a young teen and then finally frazzled it in my early 30s. Saying that, I’m finding I’m starting to get back into games a little, partly due to  my 11 year old son and partly due to a kind of gentle road-to-Damascus series of rediscovery-renaissance experiences via this MA.  Starting to work in Virtual Reality is playing a significant part in this, as is the concept of gamification and the significance of games in education.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Then again, I’ve always loved a good game of chess.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Games, both of the computer or non-computer variety, have played their part at various stages in my life. Snakes and ladders, ludo, cluedo, monopoly, Escape From Colditz (https://tinyurl.com/qoa39kz (Links to an external site.)) etc. as a child, for example. I have particularly fond memories of the London Cabbie Game (https://tinyurl.com/ua2whqp (Links to an external site.)). Card games were an important part of hanging out in shared housing or as a student.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a young wide-eyed arcade gamer back in the 80s I loved nearly everything that had a 10p or 20p slot (my pocket money and that of my peers must have built this industry). I remember the early ping-pong games appearing in my local chippie.  Followed by Space Invaders,  Pacman, Scramble, Galaxians, Gorf, then platformers like Donkey Kong.  Defender was an unbelievably amazing, crazy game that was about as immersive as a 2D space shoot-em-all game could be back then. The sounds of these games are as memorable as the gameplay, and when I hear the noises now I can smell the arcades. As a proud owner of a BBC Micro Model B, I reserve a particularly special place in my heart for Elite (https://tinyurl.com/vf6s4z8 (Links to an external site.)). This was the most cutting edge game of its time and marks the beginning of a whole new genre of video/console games.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve always loved driving games, but only if they are realistic. Forget style over substance - it has to be authentic, like the real thing. Same for flying, shooting, being in space.  I think this is probably what I am beginning to feel the love for more than anything when it comes to modern gaming. Although I’ve not played this game much myself I’m beginning to get a fascination watching my son play Zelda, Breath Of The Wild.  He loves the freedom it gives him to explore and make his own way whilst feeling about as real as can be,  and it looks amazing!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am now getting excited about the possibilities of virtual, augmented and mixed reality - surely this is going to be huge and has the potential to take the concept of what a game is onto another level.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-brief-thoughts-on-the-module-outline&quot;&gt;In brief: thoughts on the module outline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of my early thinking about this project, I am scatterlogically finding these kind of thoughts bouncing around my head, as a result of what I would like to explore myself and the generally intriguing titles of the, as yet, unlocked weekly content to come. As the course content and requirements become known and, of course, the actual work I do takes form, these will no doubt change to greater or lesser degress and new ideas should form. As ever, it will be interesting to see how this progresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Game Design&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fictional Worlds &amp;amp; Game Mechanics&lt;/strong&gt;. Vital stuff for game creators. Very much looking forward to this as it’s new learning for me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suspension of Disbelief&lt;/strong&gt;. I presume this will be about making the impossible into reality or, as I touched up above, creating worlds that make demands on our imagination and pull us out of our ‘normal’ existence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colour Theory&lt;/strong&gt;. Something I missed out on at art college, but is clearly important in app development. I want my apps to look good as this can make such a difference. I’m sure something that looks good and feels good has an advantage over something that maybe more sophisticated. If user does not like being there, they will stay away. Web design has really developed this field in recent times.
It will be worth considering the importance of an app, or immersive environment or characters within it, looking aesthetically pleasing, in comparison to the importance of being functionally-enticing, useful, exciting, fun etc. Is being able to maniuplate your environment to your own ends more important than a slick-looking environment that is proviced to you from the outset?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concept Art&lt;/strong&gt;. I have spent time considering this, as an undergraduate and generally. I am interested to see how the topic is discussed in relation to our art as app developers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Character Design&lt;/strong&gt;. A new skill for me, and potentially an important one with regard to multi-player / interactive immersive experiences and ways of relating in the virtual world with my target audience, i.e. ASD. Character design versus downloadable professionally-created assets - which is suitable for what purpose?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound Design&lt;/strong&gt;. My bag in my world outside app development and something I’ve been looking forward to engaging with. I’m considering how sound and ‘musical’ sound can be embraced as a means for providing a level of immersion that goes beyond the visual, which is far more prevelant and understood, I think.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound Process&lt;/strong&gt;. Not sure what this is. Is this sound and the process of using it, or ‘sound’ as in ‘stable’, ‘safe’, ‘reliable’?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D Art&lt;/strong&gt;. Clearly an important subject when it comes to VR.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animation&lt;/strong&gt;. I have briefly dabbled with animation - 2D using javascript and javascript libraries and game engines,and 3D via Unity - and it is an area that I am looking forward to focusing on at little more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;first-thoughts-and-development-of-ideas&quot;&gt;First thoughts and development of ideas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtual reality, augmented reality, mixed reality&lt;/strong&gt;. All seem to hold the potential to explore and push the ‘evolution’ of games further along, including notions of what games are, how we understand games in terms of their function as human activity and expressions of human nature. I am interested in how aspects of gaming can potentially be captured and used as tools for learning, particularly when combined with the intensely immersive qualities of VR. With this in mind, the idea of shared virtual experience particularly interests me and I intend to explore some of the potential, if it exists, of ‘multi-player’, ‘chat-room’ or similar platforms to facilitate the building of ‘bonds of trust’ in order to gain the attention of the participant as ‘student’, with the aim of aiding the process of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As has been explained in earlier posts, I have a personal interest in ASD - Autism Spectrum Disorder - and ultimately I would like to take steps to discover if there is the potential for immersive VR to create environments where learning is made easier; or, at least, to create another place where learning can happen, perhaps taking on a different form from those that are more established. The intention is not to create environments that ‘simply’ replace those that are real, natural, unavoidable, in order to provide relief or respite for the participant - although this could be recognised as a noteworthy by-product - or to make life easier for those in close contact, such as family. Instead, I would like to explore whether, perhaps, the clarity of objects - visual, aural, interactive - and of the individuals respresented within these environments, can help to focus the attention of the student and engage them in such a way that action, feedback and reward - in whatever form this may take - are clear and precise to the participant, uncluttered and unaffected by distracting or distressing background ‘noise’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I do not have a formal practical or academic background as an &lt;em&gt;Educationalist&lt;/em&gt;, I am aware that there are questions that I may have that ultimately turn out to have been already discussed, answered or dismissed as irrelevant. However, perhaps some need to be raised again, albeit with a new slant due to the continual advancement of technology, along with the ever-changing nature of society’s response to it. Therefore, I am approaching this topic perhaps a little &lt;em&gt;wide-eyed&lt;/em&gt; and naive. However, the expectation that the GAM720 module is approached from an experimental perspective, backed up by appropriate and thorough research, should make for an interesting journey. I only hope I find some answers and open avenues for further exploration of these thoughts and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-player:&lt;/strong&gt; Looking at ways of more than one person joining in the VR experience. How can student-teacher interaction take place?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 1:&lt;/strong&gt; the student experiences the environment and the teacher remains outside of this, but is able to manipulate the environment in real-time?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 2:&lt;/strong&gt; the student and teacher to join each other in the envoronment with the potential of interacting with each other?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facial expressions:&lt;/strong&gt; can they be simulated within VR? This could be an important part of ASD thereutic research.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;physical interactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Can I move beyond the normal expected kind of user interactions with their environment, such as picking up and throwing objects, pressing buttons, pushing objects etc? I would like to experiment with turning and twisting, clapping, shaking etc. What happens if expected outcomes do not arise but are replaced by the unexpected, scrambling cause and effect? Could this be used to create ‘puzzle’ games? For example where clapping causes water to change colour or pushing a block causes a balloon to expand.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hand tracking:&lt;/strong&gt; recently this become available for the Oculus Quest with no extra hardware or software required.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sound:&lt;/strong&gt; used within immersive environments what effect can sound have on the participant? In what why does it affect how the partipant experiences the visual aspects of the space?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vocalisation:&lt;/strong&gt; How can the participant’s own voice be used to communicate and/or affect the environment. How can it be used in general communication. Maybe speech therapy could be considered as a possible outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;environment&quot;&gt;Environment&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environmental considerations can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/01/29/vr-environment.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;social-vr&quot;&gt;Social VR&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shall be researching &lt;strong&gt;social VR&lt;/strong&gt;. This will involve looking at how Occulus, in particular, are developing the concept of the &lt;strong&gt;Avatar&lt;/strong&gt; in creating a presence in the immersive environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online links I will be studying the following videos: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ATbqtZqoit8&quot;&gt;Bootstraping Social VR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X6XOwtcscnY&quot;&gt;Oculus Avatars: Maximizing Social Presence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HT0nOOZz6QE&quot;&gt;Oculus Connect 5 - Oculus Avatars: Maximizing Social Presence, Part II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86-tHA8F-zU&quot;&gt;Facebook VR Research: Photorealistic Face Tracked Avatars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I would not describe myself as a ‘gamer’. I don’t really play games these days, but that’s not to say I do not appreciate the art.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2020-01-25T16:08:02+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T16:08:02+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/01/25/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR&lt;/code&gt; is a four-digit number, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MONTH&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DAY&lt;/code&gt; are both two-digit numbers, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Eleven</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Eleven" /><published>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/05/week-eleven.html">&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed putting together a disaster zone!
Adding force of a value and in a direction (Vector3) when rigidbody enters ‘wind zone’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added HUD display&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made this scene the first - witness the force, then back to base to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roshan - 11 year old has no problem with the mechanics.
Kirti - 47 year old non-gamer has some issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to use the controllers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when the active objects - e.g. table of objects - is not immediately in front of user?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Would a help be useful? - this could be a room where someone explains things. Not everyone has the Oculus First Steps. Could I make a button available which would put everything in front of the player - a comfort button/cushion?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrative / instructions not clear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If prep room activity not completed, should it be possible to still do the personal items collection?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When at airport - perhaps say ‘you didn’t complete the tasks, but here is your package anyway - well done for trying! Have a nice flight!!’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem is that not everyone has experienced VR. Gamers have an easier time of it, but those who do not have much gaming experience could struggle. How to make it easy? Comfortable?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Enjoyed putting together a disaster zone! Adding force of a value and in a direction (Vector3) when rigidbody enters ‘wind zone’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Ten</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/27/week-ten.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Ten" /><published>2019-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/27/week-ten</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/27/week-ten.html">&lt;p&gt;Week 10 -Finishing the main phase - happy with holding the prototype where it is.
Agreed with client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To spend the majority of the remaining time experimenting with other ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to experiment with force / forces
looked at Unity Terrain, but it seems this is a bit of a ‘fabrication’ - wind zones make grass and trees sway, but this it not quite what I’m interested in. I want to create a ‘real’ force on objects caused and affected by ‘wind’ force. I want it to make trees and cars fly through the air, waves crash on the coastline and walls to fall down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iCMhrKOuBZg&quot;&gt;Unity3d Creating Rigidbody Wind Zones&lt;/a&gt; will help.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Week 10 -Finishing the main phase - happy with holding the prototype where it is. Agreed with client.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Six - Intellectual Property Law</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/04/week-six-intellectual-property-law.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Six - Intellectual Property Law" /><published>2019-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/04/week-six-intellectual-property-law</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/04/week-six-intellectual-property-law.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sprint-retrospective&quot;&gt;Sprint Retrospective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What went well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What went wrong&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The key challenges / obstacles to be overcome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21/11/2019
There has been lots and lots of experimentation with movement. Building a teleporation system. How to get it to work in a way that is usable and intuative. Is it required at all? Can we combine it with joystick movement? Should we use joystick alone? If so, should we reduce the size of the world? Can we stop orientation making it extra confusing - would like to just have head pointing the same way no matter where it is oriented before, during or after teleportation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can spend too long on these issues. Even though it is clearly sometimes better to put it aside for now and come back to it later, to allow faster prototyping, it is often difficult to let go! A discipline that needs working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Focusing&lt;/em&gt; on specific areas - set goals that are targeted and clearly defined. I’ve discovered the importance of this. This is where sprint becomes important, and using the kanban board efficiently and precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My client is happy to see what I come up with. But because of this I need to be clearer and more targeted in my approach - it’s up to me to be this way. If not, if too loose and open to meandering, how does one assess one’s direction of travel? Goals need to be set in order to know how to gaugue progress and ensure you are on track. They also mean that the client is able to come on the journey with you and see where it all is leading. It provides them the oportunity to make suggestions and requrests from an informed position, rather than just seeing where you end up and then, maybe too late, making judgement calls on the results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Sprint Retrospective</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Five - Business Models</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/21/week-five-business-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Five - Business Models" /><published>2019-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/21/week-five-business-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/21/week-five-business-models.html">&lt;p&gt;Leon Brown - a few different business models for the creative app developer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software Development as a Service (SDaaS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software as a Product (SaaP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software as a Service (SaaS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SDaaS - monetisation of your skills, trading your time for developing software. 
Low risk. Minimal cost. Flexible (your time, you decide).
Precarious. No guarantees. Low profic margins. Competition - always someone who will do it cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SaaP - developer builds the product and reaps the rewards. Create a team of experts - product managers, graphic designers, front/back-end developers, marketers etc..
Control of vision. Freedom, flexibility, potential for profit.
Cost - heavier seeding financially. Time waiting for a return. Risk. Failure = debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\product-lifecycle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Product Lifecycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SaaS - monetise the output of software rather than the software itself, through monthly subscriptions or yearly payments etc.
Pros and cons similar to SaaP, plus :
Pros - the potential for more diverse income streams, responding to feedback, continuous income
Cons - upkeep costs, duty of care to users - boring details such as payment methods, data storage, authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canvanizer&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://canvanizer.com/&quot;&gt;Canvanizer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Model Canvas Components&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\bus-model-canvas-components.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Business Model Canvas Components&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-will-be-my-preferred-business-model&quot;&gt;What will be my preferred business model?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve been building software for a while now and it is my day-job. I don’t really see myself continuing in this vein for much longer. Being a ‘code-monkey’ (any perceived slighting of the trade is not indentional) and continuualy learning new languages, platforms, techniques etc. whilst constantly striving to be close to the top of your profession, is certainly an interesting and stimulating activity. But as a be all and end all, I feel I would not / do not gain the pure satisfaction from this career as I once would have / did. To earn as much as I feel I need to as I and my young family gets older would add to this particular pressure. So, SDaaS is not my future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saap and SaaS are more interesting to me. Both have attractions. I think it depends on the type of product envisaged as much as what kind of model you would prefer to follow. It seems many products that would once have been part of the SaaP domain have moved into the SaaS domain. So there is some burring here. Perhaps SaaS is gaining a greater share of the market for a good reason. It is probably the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-prototype&quot;&gt;First prototype&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of Sprint 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past two weeks I have been rapidly building my first prototype. I am fairly close to a MVP, one which I will be happy to show to my client for the purpose of discussion and feedback in order to progress to another level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototype has so far been built upon the original idea, which came from early discussions with my client; that is, from what I have understood of their requirements, loose and free though they are. This freedom has, in fact, been excellent for this process, allowing my imagination the space to explore with the almost certain knowledge that what I come up with will be seriously considered as a foundation for building something more rounded, solid, developed. I really am very much looking forward to showing my progress thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How is my experience going to inform my proposal and business model?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Leon Brown - a few different business models for the creative app developer:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Four - Client Contracts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/14/week-four-client-contracts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Four - Client Contracts" /><published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/14/week-four-client-contracts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/14/week-four-client-contracts.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\emergency-control-centre-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Crisis Control Centre 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\emergency-control-centre-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Crisis Control Centre 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/cross-platform/unity-scripting-upgrade?view=vs-2019#targetText=NuGet%20is%20the%20package%20manager,are%20regenerated%2C%20undoing%20necessary%20configurations&quot;&gt;Adding NuGet packages in Unity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;client-contracts&quot;&gt;Client Contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having had little experience of this, the course material provides useful guidance for how to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LO1 - Explain why it is important to use client contracts.
LO2 - Describe the structure of a client contract.
LO3 - Develop a client contract appropriate to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful resources include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freelancersunion.org&quot;&gt;The Freelancers Union&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/076116488X/ref=ox_sc_act_title_1?smid=A3P5ROKL5A1OLE&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;The Freelancer’s Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clientsfromhell.net&quot;&gt;Clients from Hell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an article for shopify, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shopify.co.uk/partners/guides/grow-vol-1/how-to-write-a-contract&quot;&gt;Ryan Foster explains&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Keeping the contract short, focused and easy to understand helps reduce friction,
allowing you to start the project quicker (and get your deposit invoice paid sooner!).
Without a contract, your client may not clearly understand what they are paying for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps avoid Feature Creep and other misunderstandings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defence mechanism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who owns the work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid changes that are unreasonable halfway through project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prices and hours need to be sorted at the start&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A larger reputable company may have their own contract/agreement they want you to sign. If this is the case consider using this document as your own agreement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide your own agreement to smaller clients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are unsure they will pay, ask for an upfront deposit (make sure it it mentioned in the signed document)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some advisors would suggest &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; asking for an upfront deposit, no matter who the client is, unless you feel it is an important and valuable client and it may jeopordise getting the work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be careful what you sign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get an independent third party to check it if you are unsure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is easy to let your enthusiasm for the client and the brief get the best of you but keeping
your feet on the ground and taking your time to dot the i’s and cross the t’s will insure that
both your and the client’s expectations align and there will be no major misunderstanding
further down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;example-structure&quot;&gt;Example structure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The company details (for both parties)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A statement of intent (could be subject to change over the course of the project)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scope and deliverables
  The details of what is going to be developed. This is a chance for you to constrain the project
  and avoid feature creep. Concentrate on specifying the finer details such as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What platforms will be targeted?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How much content will be produced?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What formats will be used?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What performance benchmarks will be set?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What is the process of review?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revisions and Alterations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;important that you protect yourself from a never ending cycle of alterations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;maybe specify the maximum allowance of alterations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;opportunity to apply a fee once the maximum has been passed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;gives the client the freedom to make changes beyond the scope of the original contract but they will do it at a cost and not for free&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadlines &amp;amp; Approvals
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when should the work be completed and are there any consequences to missing deadlines?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;how the work will be broken down and what criteria will it be measured against for completion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who is the point of contact for agreeing the completion at each point in the development process (named in the contract)?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Matters
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How much will the work cost?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Are you charging by the hour or costing for the whole job?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Always ask for a deposit, usually 10 - 30%.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Termination
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sometimes things go wrong&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;allows you set the terms for termination that are balanced&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is shared but you do not end up fully out of pocket.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;important that the contract stipulates who owns the work before and after the project is complete&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signatures
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;making the contract binding&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;contract-generators&quot;&gt;Contract Generators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://gist.github.com/malarkey/4031110&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://docontract.com/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.freelancersunion.org/contract/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;non-disclosure-agreement-nda&quot;&gt;Non-disclosure Agreement (NDA)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both parties to promise not to release information about the invention before it comes to
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/non-disclosure-agreements&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Templates&lt;/em&gt; are good for getting started but It is important that you invest time
creating a contract that is unique to your business needs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are concerned that your contract is not appropriate to your needs then always get a second opinion from a
professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.sitepoint.com/5-critical-contracts-for-mobile-app-developers/
http://99u.com/articles/21927/dont-get-screwed-the-contract-provisions-every-creative-needs-to-know
http://www.hongkiat.com/blog/freelance-contract-clauses/
https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2009/10/freelance-contracts-dos-and-donts/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>