<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-25T22:29:02+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Creative Reflective Journal</title><subtitle>My Creative Reflective Journal towards the Falmouth University Creative App Development Masters Degree.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 Lock Down</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/covid-19-lock-down.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 Lock Down" /><published>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/covid-19-lock-down</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/covid-19-lock-down.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-gives&quot;&gt;What gives?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we’re all on government-inforced lock-down. Generally, this is already having a significant effect on everyday life, but how will it effect my MA development work and studies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m working from home&lt;/strong&gt;. This in itself is not a huge issue - it’s something I’ve done regularly for many years, albeit not for every day of the week and for such a prolonged period is this is set to be. However, this is not working from home (WFH) under normal cicumstances due to the fact that…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schools are closed&lt;/strong&gt;. My elder, year 7 age son is home from school and needs a certain amount of ‘assistance’ (or maybe coersion) with getting on with the limited quantity of available online schooling, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My younger son&lt;/strong&gt;, who is home-schools on an ABA (Applied Behaviour Analysis) programme, &lt;strong&gt;finds himself with no tutor&lt;/strong&gt; - one is self-isolating whilst the other is.. well, staying home. He is unable to be left to his own devices and requires full intensive interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My lovely wife is also working from home&lt;/strong&gt;. Between us, we have quite a load. We will need to use some - hopefully not all- of our annual leave to keep son two’s education going. Unfortunately, how I can find time for my usual once-per-week study day is not certain. Today, it was impossible. It’s now nearly 8pm and I’m just getting going - unfortunately I’m further delayed by writing about these issues!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will the NEC Expo go ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; Apparently so, but it has been postponed to 7th-9th May 2021! That’s right.. &lt;strong&gt;2021!&lt;/strong&gt; So it doesn’t really feel like it is postponed but, rather, cancelled for this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will the 2020 Rotary Convention in Honolulu go ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; Nope - it’s been cancelled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I’m thinking I will continue to build the app as though my deadline for a complete working version has not changed. Hopefully there will be further events this year and, in any case, whatever happens, it will be ready ‘off-the-shelf’ should it be required. I feel sure it will be - it’s the ‘when’ that is uncertain right now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What gives?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting down to building the app</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/17/getting-down-to-building-the-app.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting down to building the app" /><published>2020-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/17/getting-down-to-building-the-app</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/17/getting-down-to-building-the-app.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;serious-business&quot;&gt;Serious business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototyping phase was in large part about taking on an air of whistfulness and experimenting without too much to worry about - after all, the worst that could happen would be that things go wrong, you blog about it, learn your lessons, make improvements and decisions, and continue to iterate towards a working prototype. Ultimately, while of course you want to make something great and hope for it to be accepted to be taken forward for further development, only you and your client (including stakeholders) will get to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now in a whole new ball-park. Now, I’m thinking, “Gulp”! After all, the NEC will be watching!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have begun easing myself back into developing the app. It’s still surprising how difficult it can be to get going after three months away from it. Remembering where I was, how it works… all stuff that seemed so close to my psyche that I was living it and dreaming it has now become almost alien code in some places. I’ve been at it for a few days (a few hours each day) now and it’s come back on the whole. There’s a lot of code I’ve had to do away with because I’m only working not on one of the three main prototype ideas, but I am keeping it in place for now as I may regret losing it. It’s safety first here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve eased myself back into the process by bringing in gentle improvements: aesthetically at first, such as increasing the size of the monitors, replacing the free asset treasure chests with self-made boxes. I then added the rudiments for a new gameplay feature - the reducing budget. Each resource now has an associated cost which is used to respectively recude the starting budget everytime a resource is deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then organised that, in the prototype, random pile of resource objects are thrown into the boxes with an ordered selection, organised per type into their own resource ‘bins’. By this point I’m getting comfortable with coding this app again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added video players to each monitor screen - but now I’m aware I need to create videos as the ShelterBox asset bank does not appear to contain any - I had though they had. I think I’ll be able to cobble some slide-based videos together using photos. Not ideal, but it will do if I don’t find anyinb better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These additions, though, only go to highlight that a &lt;strong&gt;narrative&lt;/strong&gt; needs to be created and implemented. What happens with this budget when I get to zero! This is a moment when the narrative has stopped allowing the player to sit back. Ideas that I had that were slightly vague and unfocused are now needing to focus and move from the ephemeral to something that is real, existing in an actual gamespace and achieving goals that are predefined. There is still plenty of experimentation, plenty of unknown territory. But now this is underpineed and, in many ways, resulting form the new position I and my creation have found themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… what does happen when the budget has been exhausted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;power-up-the-budget&quot;&gt;Power-up the budget&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could potentially entirely replace the countdown timer. As a gameplay device, the countdown is not necessarily a great tool - an artificial way to create pressure. It would maybe worth finding a playful way to disguise the timer element in a gameplay device that is less obvious or crude. This is worth researching, but it would seem better to build the jeopardy into the narrative itself. For example, if it is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Game Over&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; when budget reaches £0.00 then keeping the budget in the black is essential. If it becomes increasingly difficult to do so, then this is the defining characteristic of the game’s problem. If it is made to be extremely difficult to play beyond 5 minutes then this becomes, in effect, the timer in another form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some thoughts on gameplay: How could a power-up work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The budget runs down as you assign resources and it needs regular replenishment. There are a number of fund-raising activities to chose from - selected from a touch-screen next to the player.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Or selected from a panel of buttons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each time an object is picked up there is a short countdown in which time the player has to assign the resource, or else it vanishes. This time gradually reduces as the game progresses. Alternatively, the time reduces as the budget decreases. The trick would be make sure that replenishing the budget is not too easy, or gets harder as the game progresses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Throw something through a hoop or hole, or at a target to replenish the budget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phone rings intermittently and a voice offers new donations to boost budget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The control room is gradually ripped apart by an increasingly fierce hurracane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter I would love to play with if I have time. It would require incorporating one of my prototypes from GAM740 - the disaster scene with high winds picking up and throwing cars and park benches etc. Perhaps I could place the control room in this high wind zone and add colliders to the building’s walls, ceiling, furniture etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Serious business</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colour Scheme Design Experiments</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/29/colour-scheme-design-experiments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colour Scheme Design Experiments" /><published>2020-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/29/colour-scheme-design-experiments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/29/colour-scheme-design-experiments.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;colour-wheel&quot;&gt;Colour Wheel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A simple colour wheel created using pastels. Guache or acrylic paint will have done a better job.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I will update this with a more professional job shortly!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;\images\colour-wheel-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;colour-wheel-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;colour-palettes-created-from-photographs&quot;&gt;Colour palettes created from photographs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task is to create our own palettes from our own images. As time is limited for me, I chose to use some of my favourite pictures from my travels in Central and South America some time back. The diverse habitats and colours to be found in Peru and Bolivia are stunningly diverse and have remained strong in my memory. I’m sure they will for a long time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to experiment with some of the online colour tools mentioned in my post on &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/19/colour-scheme-design-apps.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;colour tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I enjoyed the results, in terms of the number of colours that could be picked from to make a palette, produced by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colourlovers.com/photocopa&quot;&gt;ColourLovers Photocopa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by the makers of &lt;strong&gt;Copasa&lt;/strong&gt;. You do have to create an account - which is free - to be able to use this tool, but there are a number of benefits, such as being able to save your palettes and sharing with others in the &lt;strong&gt;ColourLover&lt;/strong&gt;’s online community of colour enthusiasts. It is possible to access the hexadecimal and RGB values for each colour - although it’s not as easy a task as it should be or is possible in some of the other apps. However, the ColourLovers site also includes a number of other useful-looking tools for a variety of colour work and image creating tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palettes extracted from photos taken on a trip in Central and South America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-1a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-5b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-5b&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-7&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-13&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-19&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\images\palette-20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;palette-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a palette from a photo in Photocopa and adding it to Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\playing-with-palettes.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Colour Wheel</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hand Tracking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/27/hand-tracking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hand Tracking" /><published>2020-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/27/hand-tracking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/27/hand-tracking.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-hand-tracking&quot;&gt;Why hand-tracking?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controllers in Virtual Reality are at once extremely well-designed, precision pieces of equipment that make interaction between human beings and virtual worlds a more than reasonably seemless and intuitive experience. However, these controllers, no matter how well-designed, insist on a certain amount of experience with this kind of thing. Not everyone posesses a reasonably extensive experience honing their video-gaming expertise whilst immersing themselves in worlds that can best, or perhaps, only be adequately accessed and fully appreciated through devices that allow them to be experienced on their own terms. In this sense they actually form a barrier - one that can be enjoyable and aid increased immersiveness for those searching for such experiences though videogames - but one that could potentially be off-putting to those who are inexperienced in such media. Simply teaching those who have never experienced virtual reality - easily representing the majorty of the potential audience at a non-enthusiast exhibition - would take time and effot, some of which will have been wasted when the a potential user decides that this is not for them after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hand tracking, then, could be a useful ‘leveler’, where almost anyone can relate their physical experience as human beings to actions interpreted and imagined within a virtual scenario.  In the case of ShelterBox, it may be that a reduction of the time needed to teach matters as mundane as using the controllers will allow more time to experience the media and to think about issues of great importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;setting-up-and-using-oculus-quest-hand-tracking&quot;&gt;Setting up and using Oculus Quest hand tracking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new feature for the Quest as of December 2019. It is steadily improving as the weeks roll by.
However, it’s new-ness and the continual roll-out of updates brings its own problems: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tutorials can become out of date very quickly and gradually become less relevant or realistic to follow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your own set up can get behind the curve and changes you need to incorporate in order to include the latest features can mean at least some headache.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is little community of knowledge to approach for answers, as everyone has similary questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began by following &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vSia7t_WlbQ&quot;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Valem (a Belgian guy called Quentin, I believe) and there were a few issues getting going, due to the video being a whole two-months old. In Quest years that’s way past the innocence of childhood and is now hitting puberty. Updating the Unity Oculus Integration package fixed some problems, and thinking around other problems fixed those. There’s not much point in putting too much detail here because it will likely have become irrelevant in a matter of months, or in Quest Years, before we hit late teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hand tracking was, when he made the video, only possible in Android mode and did not include the ability to work using Oculus Link, i.e. running the Quest from a PC connected via a (fast, quality) USB cable. A later update - v13 of the Oculus firmware - in February, has now made this possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went straight for the Link promise, with unexpected results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nighmare hands! .. oh dear, that wasn’t supposed to happen!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\hand-tracking-1.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, not totally unexpected, at least in terms of it not going right at first. But the actual look of the hands is very.. ahem.. interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hands correctly configured&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\hand-tracking-2.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hands, once configured correctly, do respond fairly well to realtime movements - there is a small amount of latency, but they do tend to ‘wobble’, or twitch a little, particularly at the ends of the fingers. Presumably this is due to inaccuracies when attempting to keep track. It feels like a slightly weak WiFi or telephone signal and there is the sense that, if only the signal were better then the results would be much tighter and more solid and, therefore, more realistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a point where the hands, when they come together to touch or interlace fingers, disappear from view, presumably due to the complexities of maintaining the calculations required to interprate and separate the jumbled information being passed to the sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact, though, that all this is achieved with just a headset, making use of no extra hardware or specialist software aside from Oculus’ own, provided for free (to those who have already paid for the equipment, of course), is impressive at this time. I would like to see if specialist hardware/software solutions, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultraleap.com/&quot;&gt;ultraleap&lt;/a&gt; become available for the Quest, particularly when not in Oculus Link mode. The main advantage of the Quest is that it can function perfectly well untethered - in fact, that is its primary focus and, as much as Oculus Link has provided another dimension, almost making the tethered-only Rift redundant, for me, the ability to be fully operational in any location and without any reliance on a computer with a reasonably high-end graphics card, is very important. But at the current time the in-built cameras on the Quest appear to do a reasonable job and the advantages - portability, simplicity and price - are not to be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be studying next how to grab and throw using hand-tracking. But it also concerns me how movement will be achieved with no joystick controls - just bare hands - and I will also be looking into this issue..&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Why hand-tracking?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Five - Concept Art</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/24/week-five-concept-art.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Five - Concept Art" /><published>2020-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/24/week-five-concept-art</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/24/week-five-concept-art.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unity And Graphics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/19/unity-graphics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unity And Graphics" /><published>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/19/unity-graphics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/19/unity-graphics.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;lighting-and-rendering&quot;&gt;Lighting and Rendering&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D object shading results from the intensity, direction and colour of the light falling on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Types of lighting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realtime lighting&lt;/strong&gt;
In Unity - directional, spot and point. Update every frame and are interactive with moving objects. Do not bounce.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baked  lighmaps&lt;/strong&gt;
More complex, static. Lighting effects are written to textures overlaid on top of the scene geometry.
Realtime lights can be overlaid &lt;strong&gt;additively&lt;/strong&gt; on top of lightmaps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precomputed realtime global illumination&lt;/strong&gt;
Offers us a technique for updating complex scene lighting interactively. Shifts some of the lengthy number-crunching from being a realtime process to one which is precomputed. An example is a time of day system, following sun position throughout the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choices of type of light to use is not only dependent on the effects required, but on expense in terms of performance as a result of available processing power of target platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-a-space-with-sketchup&quot;&gt;Creating a space with SketchUp&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketchup is a great tool for building 3D architectural spaces. I have been using an old version that was installed on my laptop for a few years and have found it fun to play with and useful for testing architectural designs. But one of the best things about it is that it was free….  ‘&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;’ free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now not so simple. When I first came across SketchUp it was part of Google’s output and didn’t cost a penny - and I was amazed! It is a well thought-out piece of software and, at the time, it really seemed incredible that something so well-designed and rivalled expensive commercial products could be available to the unwashed masses for nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, it appears to have been offloaded by Google and taken on by a company named Trimble (the history of SketchUp is summerised &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2012/04/26/sketchup-google-first-divestment/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;), with more recent versions covered by a subscription-style payment system - see the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sketchup.com/&quot;&gt;SketchUp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; site for details. However, it is possible to still download earlier versions - v8 from 2010 is a stand-alone desktop version that is totally free, and the 2017 iteration is free for non-commercial use. These older versions of SketchUp &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://designerhacks.com/get-the-google-sketchup-free-download/&quot;&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SketchUp files can be easily brought into Unity. I created a pretty close rendition of the ground floor of my house and am working on being able to walk around it in VR. This stems from the idea of trying to create an environment that is familiar, comfortable, relaxing, following my train of thought on autism and education (annunciated throughout this course and this blog). I find that SketchUp provides a way to create architectural renditions of real and imagined spaces much more naturally than using the graphical tools provided within Unity, including ProBuilder and the standard Unity tools. The fact that it is simply a case of dragging the exported models directly into Unity is very useful, and the older free versions of SketchUp are absolutely fine for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The model in SketchUp&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\sketchup-pentre-street1.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The model in Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\unity-pentre-street1.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lighting and Rendering</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colour Scheme Design Apps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/19/colour-scheme-design-apps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colour Scheme Design Apps" /><published>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/19/colour-scheme-design-apps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/19/colour-scheme-design-apps.html">&lt;p&gt;There are some very useful and simple free apps out there for creating or selecting a colour palette. As you’d expect from the world of design, the UIs are generally elegant and pleasant to look at, as well as very functional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;color-hunter&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://colorhunter.com/&quot;&gt;Color Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very useful browser-based app that allows uploading of an image which is then used to generate a palette.&lt;br /&gt;
Alternatively, it is also possible to search Flickr.com for images to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;paletton&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://paletton.com/&quot;&gt;Paletton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uses a simple browser-based UI to create complimentary colour combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;copaso&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colourlovers.com/copaso/ColorPaletteSoftware&quot;&gt;Copaso&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced colour palette creator that allows choosing colours, uploading of images, saving palettes and adding notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;colorzilla&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorzilla.com/&quot;&gt;ColorZilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chrome and Firefox extension. Reads colour from any point in browser. Can also inspect a page and create a palette of CSS gradients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;coolersco&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coolors.co/&quot;&gt;Coolers.co&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allows ‘random’ palette creation, cycling through palettes until you find the one you want. Then you can refine, edit it and save it. Also allows uploading of images for palett creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;color-hunt&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://colorhunt.co/&quot;&gt;Color Hunt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chrome extension or web-based UI. Quick way of browsing and selecting palettes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;colorexplorer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.colorexplorer.com/&quot;&gt;ColorExplorer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I more complex designing toolbox than the others with a large number of features and exporting options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;color-safe&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://colorsafe.co/&quot;&gt;Color Safe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helps to create color palettes based on WCAG Guidelines of text and background contrast ratios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;adobe-color&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://color.adobe.com/create/color-wheel/&quot;&gt;Adobe Color&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;material-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/design/color/the-color-system.html#tools-for-picking-colors&quot;&gt;Material Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google sanctioned Material palette generator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;online-colour-wheels&quot;&gt;Online Colour Wheels&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://color.adobe.com/create&quot;&gt;Adobe color wheel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canva.com/colors/color-wheel/&quot;&gt;Canva Color Wheel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sessions.edu/color-calculator/&quot;&gt;Sessions College Color Wheel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;w3schools-html-colour-mixer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3schools.com/colors/colors_mixer.asp&quot;&gt;w3schools HTML colour mixer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There are some very useful and simple free apps out there for creating or selecting a colour palette. As you’d expect from the world of design, the UIs are generally elegant and pleasant to look at, as well as very functional.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prologue - Assign | Deploy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/18/prologue-assign-and-deploy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prologue - Assign | Deploy" /><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/18/prologue-assign-and-deploy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/18/prologue-assign-and-deploy.html">&lt;div style=&quot;font-family: Courier New;&quot;&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Please enter your personal details:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Name: &lt;b&gt;Alex&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Gender: &lt;b&gt;Male&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
DOB: &lt;b&gt;04/07/1996&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Reason for being here: &lt;b&gt;looking for adventure&lt;/b&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;welcome-alex-thank-you-for-volunteering-we-have-a-critical-situation-there-are-a-number-of-disasters-that-require-your-urgent-attention&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Welcome Alex. Thank you for volunteering. We have a critical situation. There are a number of disasters that require your urgent attention…“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: 1.4em;&quot;&gt;
Alex is an office administrator. He volunteered for ShelterBox because it looked interesting and something different to do with his time. Well, okay.. it was partly this, but also it was because he’d watched and listened to the news for what seemed like his entire life feeling detached from the important and significant events around the world.. those he could only witness from a distance. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
He now felt he had discovered something new. Doors had been opened. Suddenly, he had found an opportunity to pack his bags and go out there, in person, to help those who had just experienced disaster at close quarters. In fact, maybe he didn't have to remain outside it all any longer. Perhaps he would now be able to look people directly in the eye and try to understand, to really understand, what they had been through. At the very least he could now maybe help out in some way - grab a warm blanket and put it around the shoulders of someone who had not experienced such simple pleasure for weeks, or drop off a box containing medication that could mean more than he could imagine to a family for whom only a few days ago things had looked so bleak!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At least, this was his ambition. But first, Alex needed to step into the uncomprising world of Distaster Response Preparation. It is a tough job, but someone has to do it, and why shouldn't that someone be Alex?!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alex walked into the &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Response Room&lt;/span&gt;. It was as he expected – a serious room defined by serious intentions. “Welcome Alex”, said a calm female voice that appeared to come from everywhere. “Your willingness to help is much appreciated. We are currently experiencing extremely high levels of disruption to everyday lives on a global scale. Current pressure ratings are at dangerous levels. We are relying on your calm efficiency, pragmatism and intelligence to help bring us back to within calm and sustainable levels. Are you willing to engage?”.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“Yes, I am”, said Alex.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The sound of well-insulated electronically controlled servers whirred into action with the kind of slick precision associated with German engineering. From within the rather bland looking counter incongruously sitting in front of him, three monitor screens slid into view that seemed to embody a cold, machine-grade sense of expectation. Simultaneously, an opening emerged and, from within, appeared the first of a series of disaster relief resource holograms. Alex had not noticed at first, but each screen appeared to be suspended above what looked like large, bottomless boxes, coloured in the standard ShelterBox Blue and designed to withstand the kind of treatment handed out by Ryanair on a short-staffed bank holiday weekend.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“These resources are precious. Please assign them carefully to the displayed disasters. Don’t forget: be cool; be careful. Diligent planning can help more people; too much attention to a single cause can mean failure for so many others.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“Alex, good luck!”

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week Four - Colour Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/18/week-four-colour-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week Four - Colour Theory" /><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/18/week-four-colour-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/18/week-four-colour-theory.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-on-colour-theory&quot;&gt;Notes on colour theory&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colour is subject experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perception of frequencies of light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part physical, part interpretational&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subconscious&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choice influenced by colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importance: shape –&amp;gt; colour –&amp;gt; content&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultural, non-universal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umberto Eco (1985) - neither psychologial nor aesthetic - cultural - linguistic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;verbal language makes the non-verbal recognisable
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So much in common with music!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important to make the right colour choices - evoke emotions
Colour mistakes can have a lasting negative impact on your brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Balingher&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appeal, usability, accessibility of app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/visual-design/color/&quot;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://brandpalettes.com/google-colors/&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; provide documentation about use of appropriate colour for their products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/fabric&quot;&gt;UI Fabric&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/design/color/the-color-system.html#&quot;&gt;Meterial Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessibility&lt;/strong&gt; - colour blindness - ‘colour vision deficiences’&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes on colour theory</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dog Walker Simulator - The Interactive Novel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dog Walker Simulator - The Interactive Novel" /><published>2020-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/17/dog-walker-simulator-interactive-novel.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-brief-create-an-interactive-novel&quot;&gt;The brief: create an interactive novel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Create an interactive novel using Ren’Py, loosely based on the game creation activity from Week 2. There must be at least three interactive moments within the novel.&lt;br /&gt;
In line with the previous activity, these decision points might be:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Choosing which character will save the day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Deciding how the character uses your app to save the day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Selecting an action to execute in battle.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ending the game, by choosing what the character will do once they have overcome the challenge, for example, do they go back to their normal life or choose to continue using their power for good or evil?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This activity is designed to encourage you to think outside the box and be creative with how you communicate a concept. There are no boundaries or constraints, apart from the minimum number of interactive moments in the novel. There are also no rights, wrongs or silly ideas. Do whatever feels right in regards to your main concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;renpy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renpy.org/&quot;&gt;Ren’Py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\ren-py-main.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ren’Py seems to be a simple way to produce interactive text (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autzones.com/din6000/textes/semaine09/Aarseth(1997).pdf&quot;&gt;Cybertext&lt;/a&gt;) which requires the reader/player to make choices along the way, causing the narrative to fork and head in directions that are the result of the decision that have been made. Its multi-platform nature and portability makes it particulary interesting due to the possibility of creating simple demos that are easily made available. Ren’Py scripts are simple text files that follow a simple syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fungus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assetstore.unity.com/packages/templates/systems/fungus-34184&quot;&gt;Fungus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\fungus-main.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A free asset for Unity, Fungus describes itself as being &lt;em&gt;great for making Visual Novel, Interactive Fiction, RPG, Point &amp;amp; Click &amp;amp; eLearning games&lt;/em&gt;.
It looks like an interesting option and, because it uses the Unity IDE, workflow and Asset Store, it could be very useful as I  increasingly make use of Unity for my projects. I believe it will also be relatively straight forward to turn the work done using Fungus into a ‘full’ Unity-based project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to trying out Fungus, but for this exercise I will be using Ren’Py, for it’s relatively simple workflow, small file size and ability to easily port to multiple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dog-walker-simulator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html#take2&quot;&gt;Dog Walker Simulator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My narrative will be based on my updated story idea which can be seen &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/04/dog-walker-simulator.html#take2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive moments could be: -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The dogs have broken freen from Crystal’s grasp and are heading in different directions. What should be her response?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which dog, or dogs, to go after first?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when she or a dog is facing imminent danger?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to do when she has collected all the dogs she is able to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to outline interactive moments in such a linear fashion is not as simple as it first appears to be, as the very nature of interactive, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.articleworld.org/index.php/Ergodic_literature&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ergodic literature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is non-linear. For instance, point 3 may not even come to pass depending on decisions made at points 1 or 2. Therefore, the suggestions above cannot be seen as the definitive set of choices available.  Perhaps it would be better to draw up a more complex network of possibiliies. I have a feeling the alternative, of simply making a start creating the narrative and seeing where it leads, could lead to huge confusion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\interactive-novel-sketch-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points: -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding images is going to be difficult - will have to make them myself to do a proper job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python - discovering Python through Ren’Py. The use of variables became necessary. Looking at the documentaion indicates that the whole Python vocabulary will be important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vastly reduced the number of possible options by reducing number of dogs from 5 to 3 then to 2 - potential first branches reduced and therefore number of possible outcomes etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began by creating a sketch, on paper, of a vague possible plan of an interactive narrative. At this stage it started to become clear how complex a web this could become given even what appeared at first to be be a reasonable number of points of choice and potential forking onto difference paths - I found it difficult to use this plan verbatim, at least in large part due to this very fact. It made me realise just how linear programming itself can be. The complexities in both providing and following instructions that involve a large number of divergent strands do not seem to sit easily within such a format. It’s a little like trying to describe a three dimensional oject in two dimensions. Or, perhaps it is clearer how difficult this can be when you consider how hard it is to imagine a four dimensional world when viewed from our own perspective as fully paid up and assimilated members of one that is simply three dimensional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, branching is possible but fraught with difficulties avoiding spaghetti and repetition. I used variables to help, for instance, differenciating when revisiting a certain scenario that could have been approached from a number of possible situations, for example, rescuing Trixie after Rusty had been reunited with Crystal, or the same scene, i.e. rescuing Trixie, after Rusty had been taken away by the dog warden. Variables can also be used for maintaining states - I used one for keeping track of energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the complexities of building this interactive novel meant it was more time-intensive than I had imagined it would be - although this would clearly improve with experience. I also found that I had little time to spend searching for good quality and suitable assets, such as character and background images. To do this properly one would really have to make their own, but of course, this is a skill in itself. As it was, I picked images very quickly with little consideration for aethetic quality or cohesive design - doing so would have been unnecessary with regard to the limited intentions of the exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I considered creating my own cartoon-like images, but quickly realised it would take a very long time to do so. I got as far as a single outline sketch, but to turn this into a set of usable png files (which they would need to be in order to have transparent backgrounds) would be a project in its own right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left; margin: 20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;\images\trixie-dog-sketch.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did use a music track that I created myself - &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/stephen-banbury/movement&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Movement (soundcloud)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - although clearly this was not created specifically for this project. Building a usable library of assets would make creating such an artefact much simpler and far quicker, as well as avoiding potential issues surrounding permissions and copyright. But as this would consume a huge amount of time it is certain that, at least, certain assets will always need to be acquired from suitable resources. The better quality assets are, of course, generally not free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do find it interesting that, awful though my selection of images are, they are still more engaging than none at all. After all, a sequential selection of visual images, even if the quality is questionable, make telling a story more immediate and engaging than textual or verbal forms alone. There is also a significant body of research looking at the use of music in film and TV, as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://rhythmcoglab.coursepress.yale.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/5/2014/10/Music-as-a-Source-of-Emotion-In-Film.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;source of emotional impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that plays its part in &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=YjZN-44Z8AcC&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PP11&amp;amp;dq=film+music&amp;amp;ots=0uDqu6CF7c&amp;amp;sig=LlmWuuKRq5v0hVDJSNLD9h1U48g#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=film%20music&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;setting a ‘tone’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video here demonstrates a number of different possible storylines, each dependent on the player’s choices. The differences here are fairly subtle but are resultant upon choices made earlier by the ‘reader’ who, through the effort required to move the story forward, in effect plays a part beyond simply its telling, but in its creation and, therefore, its manifestation into something real and unique in its own lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dog walker simulator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video style=&quot;width:720px;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;\media\dog-walker-simulator.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Woops! Your browser does not support the HTML5 video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ren’Py, and other applications with similar aims, such as Fungus, certainly appear to be fairly popular - judging by the number of hits when searching the internet - suggesting they have a number of potential uses. As well as testing ideas for story-oriented or game-like apps, I can see the opportunity for creating interactive presentations that could be very useful for pitching or promoting ideas. It is predominantly for this reason that I am glad to have engaged with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The brief: create an interactive novel</summary></entry></feed>